<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-anna-may-wong</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072054/1921-10-04/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Anna+May+Wong</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CHINESE CINDERELLA REFUSES TO
    FORSAKE LAUNDRY FOR FILM FAME
    By LINTON WELLS
    a-.i ',^<4..'E. A. Staff Correspondent
    1*00 A^OLS, Oct. 4.?Thn
    M veil known fairy prince la going
    'to. have a hard time persuading
    p lng Anna May Wong that the giid
    jO" ./'?d 'sMpper of moviedom can bring
    5- lier moro happiness than work in
    her fathor's little Chinese laundry.
    "Anna May, 16-year-olil Celestial
    fe '/Cinderella' of the studios, twink
    lea before the* acreen by day. and
    presides at the lronlng-hoard at
    .night.
    Well on her pretty way to fame,
    she says she will forego the prom
    I,/ Ised career without a righ if it
    'means'that her parents mnv lose
    pleasure or profit by her going.
    Enters Fairyland.
    Mavieland to Anna May holds
    all the thrills that fairyland offers
    her Occidental slsterH. Handsome
    lovers shower her with attentions
    Beautiful clothe* adorn her rlen
    der form. Jewels sparkle from
    her Jet black hair. Motor cars
    are"* at her beck anrl call. The
    thrill of the drama makes her for
    Vget that thn camera In recording
    all this for the beenfit of ar. amuse
    ment-loving public.
    All this until 5:30. Then her
    handsome suitors go home to their
    y wives and babies, her j||rels are
    placed in the studio safe over night,
    her beautiful clothes a-? tal: ?:s
    back-to the property room.
    Anna May pays the conductrv
    five cents and trolley-cars to the
    home above her father's laundry
    Hero there are hooks of the little
    laundry shop to he kept, and many
    shirt? to he pinned before they are
    wrapped to a wait, the rail of run
    tomers.
    In Laundry Home.
    Anna May Wong in her laundry
    home looks just an she does on the
    rcveen. The poat. would say that
    she stole her color or her fact
    .from a poppy, and that of h-?
    hands from a card en In.
    Anna Mny Wong Is a discover*
    of Marshall Neilan. It was while
    hunting for types for his produc
    Hon of V'DIntv" thai Neilan discov
    ?red her. and after much induce
    ment persuaded her father t ::llo\v
    her to forsake her shirt-pinning uc
    tlvities for the screen?at. leas* dur
    ing the day. Since then Anna May
    has played many good parts, for
    besides being an excellent "type.'
    she has unusual talent Her most
    f recent effort was a co-ftar part oti
    i:' posite I-on Chaney in "Mi' of
    Uf<\"
    Site has not yet been convinced
    'bat her studio work is greater :bar.
    her dntie* to her fnmf-v. if
    can achieve a motion picture renu
    t at ion and-still r.tron-1 to h?r feth
    .?r's affairs she will always be ban
    y,. py, if rot. then her mn?ion picture'
    K career must rro. r<>- filial devotion
    is inborn in the Chinese heart of
    Anna May.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1921-09-08/ed-1/?sp=14&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&st=text&r=-0.046,0.665,0.503,0.511,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Little Chinese Cinderella of the Screen
    SOME time ngo I told .vou nbont tho wonderful chnrncter part than I-on Chancy
    plnys In Nellnn's now film, ,,Mts of Life." In fact. I rnved for nlinont two
    columni of typo over the mnrvels of tills innn's work nnd his enreer.
    A friend of mine out on tlie vviwt const writes me, however, thnt Chnney
    rcolly isn't the nmrvel of "Kit of Life" he gives the honor to n little Chinese
    girl, Annn Mny Won, whom we linvo nil frcen in other films.
    If yon, (lornlilitic, lind onre been n drudge, keeping books nt night for your
    fnthcr's dingy little Nhop and then Maidenly the moles hnd discovered jou nnd
    jou had mndc such n success of It thnt jour earnings were twice the earnings
    of your father's shop but otir fnther refused to regard tho movies seriously
    nnd Insisted on jour still keeping his books nt night what would ou do?
    Father would have to get out n search warrant to find you, wouldn't he?
    You would turn up jour prettv little nub nose In independence and strut right
    out and live your own life on mnr own sala'rj wouldn't jou? Thnt would be
    the way with most American girls
    Hut Chlncc girls are bt ought up from childhood to regard their father's
    commands as nltnost of divine orlum the Chinese girl who disobeys her pnrents
    Is dlsgrnted bejond snlnilon Ami Annn Mny Wong is n Chinese girl.
    Annn Mnj could now buy her fnthor's little laundry if he would sell, she
    hns made lots of innnev nnd mivimI It Hut fnther merely tolerates the movies.
    They are an Intention of the foreign devils and. while he doesn't mind Anna May
    earning money In them In the dnjtinie. he considers her first duty to him and that j
    duty menns continuing to keep his books and check up the laundry each night.
    The Oriental Cinderella of movielnnd Is Anna Maj. Movlclar.d holds for
    her nil the thrills thnt fairyland offers her little sisters. Here hnndsome lovers
    iihower her with nil the attentions of Homeos. Iitautlful clothes adorn her
    Jewels sparkle from her jet black hair nnd motorcars are at her beek and call.
    The thrill of the drama makes her forjet that the cntnorn is recording all this for
    the benefit of tho amusement-loving public of the country.
    OUE ltrr in fairyland until 5.30.
    then her handsome suiiori no
    home to their icives and babies, fler jewels arc placed in the studio
    info overnight and her beautiful clothri arc taken back to the property
    room. It i fAen that Anna May steps from fairyland to reality, pays
    the conductor fire cents and trolley-cars to her home in Xorth Figucroa
    street, above her father's laundry shop. Here there arc books of the
    little laundry business U be kept and many shirts to be pinned before
    they are xrrapped and placed on the ihelvc aicatting the call of the
    customers.
    THOSE who remember "Dinty" will recall the pretty Chinese girl who nssists
    Wesley Barry rescue the white girl from the den of the Malay. This was
    Anna May Wong, and It marked her first work ns n screen nctress. It was
    while hunting "tjpes" for his production that Marshall Neilnn discovered Anna
    May and finally induced her father to nllow her to forsake her shlrt-pinnlng
    activities nt least during the day.
    Since then Anna Slay has foimd herself in great demnnd among movie
    producers, for in addition to being an exceptional "tjpe" she has unu-ual talents
    "Outside the Law" and "Shame" are other films in which she appeared, and
    then Mnrshall Neilan again took her to his studio for the co-star part opposite
    Lon Chaney in "Hits of Life."
    Anna May Wong in her laundry home, my friend writes me, lookw just as
    he docs on the screen. Quiet, beautiful nnd industrious, Anna May pins t.hirt
    and adds figures with equal djesterity. Once at home her movie fairjland i
    forgotten In the reality of hard work to be overcome before she again dons her
    finery and plays the queen.
    There is a difference, however, between this Chinese Cinderella of the movies
    nnd tho Cinderella of old. Unlike her predecessor, Anna May Wong loves her i
    mental duties at home. She has grown up in an atmosphere of industry, for
    any one who has ever lost n collar knows that tho ramifications of a Chinese i
    laundry demand ceaseless activitj. Anna May's laundry is a machine of human
    parts, ns complicated as one of springs nnd wheels. The wash goes in one end
    and vanishes, the shirts one way. the collars another, the socks here, the under
    clothing th'ere. And then they all come out together in neat piles.
    "Whether the producer needs n Chinese slave girl or a princess, Anna May
    always qualifies In her inovla work. In "Bits of Life," ns the wife of. a rich
    LOWLY ACCORDION
    NOW HELPS STIR
    SCREEN EMOTIONS
    Anna May
    Wong is the
    I t 'I'sr t pmn"f f yiT-s iMtHMlrriffT iirr'rTWlW IMlfWMf lMimWTtmHKKlMmUKwU
    sw?.w"f i!PMriJlaf1ff
    cwper of gambling nnd opium joints in San Francisco's Chinatown, she is
    asked to play one of tho most striking characters yet created by Hugh Wiley,
    whose Chinese fiction in the Saturday Evening Post has established him as the
    leading author of this typo of story.
    Very often the studio exacts much of her vitality and It is not uncommon
    for her to start work at 0 in tho morning nnd work until 0 In the evening
    before tho glaring light thnt bap one's strength. Yet Anna Mny never misses
    her work evenings nt the little Chin'-e laundry.
    TUB call of the Neic "World nil uniiccrcd by Anna and still it docs
    not cause her to octroy the filial duties of the Old. That is the
    Chinese xcay. To the ichite gul this icould be an unusual procedure.
    To the Chinese girl f is tho molt natural thing m the tcorld, Anna
    May has not yet been convinred thnt her studio icork is greater than
    her duties to her family. If she ran arhieie a motion-picture icputa
    Hon and still attend to her fathtr t afjntrn, hc cill alicays be happy
    Otherwise she Kill havo to desert hir fairyland.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1931-08-16/ed-1/?sp=77&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&st=text&r=-0.3,0.368,1.599,1.599,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Holly wood s New Chinese Star
          Anna May Wong, American
          ißPßfirah- Born Daughter of Chinese
          ■HhßSp®! Parents Who Ran a China-
          town Laundry in Los
          Angeles, Gota Start in the
          Movies Through Lon Chaney and
          Marshall Neilan, but She Had to Win
          Success in Germany, England and on
          Broadway Before She Could Get Real
          Recognition at Home.
          BY DAN THOMAS.
          A LITTLE Chinese girl hu become the
          toast of Hollywood—but she had to
          go to Europe to attain this position.
          Anna May Wong is this girl, the
          Anna May Wong who spent her early
          years living above her father's
          laundry, whose only farewells r. Lien she left for
          Germany were from her family and who re
          turned to Hollywood a few weeks ago to be
          greeted by a throng of film folk, reporters and
          photographers.
          To understand Anna May. you must go back
          many years to the marriage of her mother and
          father.
          Her father lived in Sunning. Canton, China.
          And her mother came from Northern China
          near Peiping. Immediately after their marriage
          they migrated to Los Angeles, where Wong ex
          pected to follow In the footsteps of his ancestors
          In the quest of knowledge.
          A aeries of unforeseen circumstances however.
          w ji nf
          3
          am IP. Tgjfr
          Mi
          fffij p I y* l v 1
          flp
          h Xtitir 4nna May V ong. cost annul for her neu' American Talkie.
          t
          forced him to give up his pursuit of knowledge
          •nd seek m means of livelihood a few years after
          their arrival. It didn't take Wong long to dis
          cover that America offers the Chinese but three
          alternatives in the matter of earning a living
          lie could become a day laborer household
          Servant or laundry mart
          Wong chose the Utter He found a big house
          several miles from the Los Angeles Chinatown,
          remodeled two rooms as a laundry and fixed up
          the reel of the house as living quarters for his
          haul? It was in this house that Anna May,
          Mm third child, Was bam and Used during the
          a i -»m A
          fiftOndl vMV' W nfr rnBPuOOu ft*id SuDWiuffi
          dm to so -n fame fiwwTWlWl
          THE SUNDAY STAR, WASHINGTON, D. C., AUGUST T 6, 193!.
          There are {seven Wong children, all of whom
          shortly after their births were given appropriate
          English names to simplify their contact with
          the outside world—that is. all except the eldest
          daughter, who preferred her Chinese nam
          Ytng Anna May at birth
          was christened Pros ted Wei
          low Willows The other
          children are James. Mary, jm
          Prank. Roger and jQaj/r*
          Richard
          Anna May her-
          self is a typical
          American girl from
          a standpoint of in- ajw
          dependence educa
          uon and self coo- /1 Tjjj W j},,
          fldencc But .site is
          inordinately proud ws
          #sk
          itage And she is ,^V
          proud of Uie way
          she was brought ip
          in her sheltered Chinese home, according to
          many of the Chinese customs.
          True to theee traditions and codes. Mr and
          Mrs Wong raised their children to be implicitly
          obedient, courteous, unselfish and studious. At
          home they wore the besuitiful silken robes of
          the land they never had seen, but tlwir school
          wardrobes were made of gingham and serge
          Anna May remembers her school days as a
          long episode of serious work and constant study
          She attended the Los Angeles public schools
          daily.
          BUT she pever was permitted to play qrith
          her American friends after school, hours.
          1-nrtmf she had to run home after schoei
          ft jß^ftHk
          i ft
          rW 1 i
          IgfP 5 F i
          JHT imy i -r
          Sf m MH
          pt JW v "iHH
          Sb^

          in «bl ;«i
          M*-* *®v"ftft fc> _.; '•°mj‘‘-Xsii'
          -m ||SSB?£jjflß9ra lip
          a*|s| li
          •y v.* v
          ■||^^B l I^HK' 1
          r ':^E
          fc _« V/wj Wong imitating
          V'" Vforv Firkford in “Thu*
          |p~ Taming of the Shrew."
          chance her English text books for Chlnesa
          volumes and tush off to a thiee-hour session tn
          Chinese private school.
          Many times Anna May and her sisters ob
          jected to the strenuous study and work forced
          upon them. Why should they learn to read,
          write and speak Chinese? What good would It
          do them? Their father merely replied that It
          was his wish that his children should know the
          language of their ancestors.
          “I am very glad now that father insisted
          upon us studying ChineseJi- the charming ac
          tress says. “Had I not done so I would have
          missed much that is beautiful in life. I now
          knew the wisdom and philosophy of my people
          through the knowledge of their language.
          Father knew what was ahead of us. How
          wise he was!"
          Vacations never were favored by the head
          of the Wong family As a result the children
          always attended Summer school. Consequently
          when Anna May entered high school she was
          the youngest student in that institution—and,
          you might say, the smartest
          Piano study was added to her list of high
          school subjects at this time, leaving her little
          time to dwell upon her secret longing to be
          come an actress.
          This longing was of several years duration,
          dating back to a Chinese New Year celebra
          tion when she was six years old and her father
          took his family to their first picture show.
          “To this day I can remember in detail the
          six pictures that were shown that night for
          live cents per person,” declares Miss Wong.
          Pearl White was in a serial. Eddie Polo was
          in another picture There was a Keystone eop
          comedy and a melodrama that gave me night
          mares for a week afterward."
          During her third year in high school. Anna
          May suffered a nervous breakdown. The fam
          ily's Chinese physician prescribed rest under
          the sun. true to the traditions of his people,
          who believe that the sun will cure many ail
          ments Pot weeks afterward Anna May haunt
          ed the beaches and parks in search of health.
          But she tired of spending long hours doing
          nothing but sitting So she ssked her oouain,
          James Wong, a film actor, to take her with
          to the studio This James consented to
          do, always her with him whenever he
          had a locatVy" call so that she could remain
          in the freeh air That was before the stuthos
          became ae particular about having visitors
          around.
          While visiting on the set during the time
          m Uigrdtiathu smile. Several times a day bp
          A characteristic photo of the A meri*
          can-born chinese girl who is riding
          the crest of the wove in Hollywood.
          Anna May Wong, as she will appear
          in "Daughter of the Dragon
          would wander over to where she was sitting
          and engage her In a conversation for a few
          moments at a time.
          The man was Marshall Neilan, at that time
          one of Hollywood's beat directors. It was huge
          ly through him that Anna May s life took a
          sudden turn and she found herself a scree*
          actress, far better known within a very short
          time than her cousin James.
          There was some consternation in the Wong
          household when Anna May came home one
          night and told of an offer she had received
          from Neilan to play a role in a picture, "DUsty.'’
          which he was about to start.
          Wong and his wife sat up that night long
          after the children had retired, discussing the
          proposition from all angles. They knew that
          she would abide by their decision if they ob
          jected to her taking the role. But would it be
          quite fair to rob their daughter of such an
          opportunity? The following morning Wfcng
          V called his daughter and said:
          "I haven’t much faith in these things called
          moving pictures. Yet the most honored pro
          fessional men in all China are acton. If feu
          will take your sister with you as a chaperon
          and get home every night in time for eur
          evening meal you may accept the offer.”
          Little did he realize when he made that
          statement that within a few years his daugh
          ter's name would be dancing In electric lights
          the world over.
          When Anna May first stepped In front of
          the cameras her fears were unbounded. But
          she soon was made to feel at ease by the Bnd’
          ness of Neilan and her fellow players, Wesl-jf
          Barry. Marjorie Daw, Pat O'Malley and Noah
          Beery.
          "Dinty” placed the young Chinese girl well
          on the road to success. No sooner had it been
          released than she was deluged with offers from
          casting directors in every studio. For more
          than a year she was kept constantly busy and
          her salary continued to grow.
          She easily was earning enough to take her
          family from their laundry house quarters, but
          th y preferred to stay there, and Anna Mag
          stayed with them.
          Then she signed a contract with a motion
          picture company operating in San Francisco.
          The company was unable to raise the necessary
          money for their production, but they refused
          to release Miss Wong until the termination of
          her contract one year later. Thus she was
          kept off the screen entirely for one year.
          piHE year is a long time In the film business.
          where every one forgets quickly. Anna
          Msy returned to Hollywood eager to don grease
          paint and get to work again.
          Studio executives end directors welcomed
          4 her with open arms—but they didn't offer hot
          any Jobs For 12 months she worked in ontt
          three films—t*o comedies and an exceOsWl
          rote in “Mr. Wu" with Lon Chaney.
          It was Chaney who kept her
          out of the business entirely at that time. Swm
          oms had eome to the young girl easily and Ad
          was wholely unprepared tor this sudden changa,
          n was only Chaney's encouragement that $pH
          earnmaot <*t ttiy*f*tt«t* pdjfh'
          9</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1932-04-13/ed-1/?sp=24&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&r=-0.1,0.118,0.783,0.419,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Face and Hands
          In Them You Read Character
          Wm JM jt j
          ANNA MAY WONG’S CLEVER POSE
          This shows the face and hands of Anna May Wong, young
          Chinese actress, born in the United States. There could be
          no better arrangement of a photograph to show, in condensed
          •pace, the spirit dwelling within.
          From the face and the hands you learn more than from all
          the rest of the body, all, in fact, that you need to know.
          The eyes reflect the mind and spirit, the mouth reveals
          emotions, cold, passionate or neutral.
          The forehead, in this case too much concealed, is most
          important of all, for that which is back of the forehead is
          really THE HUMAN BEING.
          As for the hands, they tell a thousand stories. The fingers,
          long, tapering, with the hand itself narrow, show what we
          call "refinement,” the absence of hard work through a num
          ber of generations.
          Fingers blunt at the end, with broad nails, tell one story.
          Too much "refinement” in the hands may show that a
          person belongs to a family dying out, losing energy. Refine
          ment is admirable, but there must always be STRENGTH, to
          make refinement efficient and useful.
          In the thumb alone you may read character.
          According to the Kiralfy brothers, theatrical men of long
          ago, you can tell from the thumb the shape of the whole body.
          The Kiralfys, producing the "Black Crook,” and other per
          formances in which young ladies were displayed in tights, in
          the old days, needed young ladies with well-shaped legs.
          But the Kiralfys said: "All we need to see is the girl’s thumb.
          As soon as we see the thumb we know just how she will look
          in tights.” This, presumably, saved the young ladies apply
          ing for jobs some embarrassment, and saved time for the
          Kiralfys.
          Study hands and faces, eyes for sincerity, the chin for
          force of character, the ears for generosity, or the reverse, the
          mouth for emotion, the forehead for intelligence, the hands
          for the physical and racial past, and you study a human
          being completely.
          In addition, you will be interested in this young face, com
          bining the mystery of the East with the Western influence of
          birth in this country.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1936-03-12/ed-1/?sp=11&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong, Hollywood film
          alar, la In the land of her ancestors
          now for the first time in her life
          Born and reared In Los Angeles.
          the American Chineae girl who sup
          plied the Oriental allure to the mo
          tion picture industry for 15 years,
          had her first glimpse of China here
          the other day when she stepped ofi
          the gangplank of a liner from San
          Francisco
          She plans to pa* a year in the
          Orient. After seeing Hongkong and
          Canton and after visiting her mother
          and sisters whom she hasn't seen
          for years. Miss Wong will travel
          throughout the country to see the
          ‘real" China, not the China she
          knew In the movies, from books and
          from hearsay.
          Hopes to Learn Language
          Incidentally she hopes to leam
          the Chines* language, but she un
          derstands It Is difficult.
          Rumors of a romance accompanied
          her arrival here. Fellow passengers
          on the steamer whispered Into ship
          news reporters’ ears when the liner
          docked that the son of a millionaire
          Canton merchant was waiting for
          her to be his bride. No such thing.
          Miss Wong denied promptly. She Is
          "wedded to her art."
          No Movte Actress Airs
          There Is none of the movie actress
          airs abcut demure, placid Anna
          Wong. She scorns make-up—a lit
          tle lipstick Is her only concession—
          snd she has some ideas of her own
          concerning the things she wears.
          "Years of experimenting with
          western clothing have convinced me
          that the only colors that really suit
          Orientals are black and white." she
          said. "It Is ridiculous for us to ac
          cept bllndl; the current fashions of
          New York and Paris."
          As if In demonstration, she was
          wearing an almost severe black suit
          with white waist, an outfit the sim
          plicity of which was well suited to
          her aopearance and manner.
          Her Opinion of Hollywood
          Hollywood?
          "What the mo* »e capital needs is
          freshness, freshness in everything
          characters, plots, actors and ac
          tresses.” she asserted. "No wonder
          such stars as Garbo and Dietrich
          had such meteoric success
          "The adaptation of commonplace
          stories no longer satisfies cinema
          audiences, and producers are in
          creasingly looking abroad for un
          usual material, which opens further
          opportunities for foreign playera.
          "When the talkies came everyone
          thought the foreign actors then In
          Hollywood would be thrown out of
          Jobs because they couldn’t speak
          English without an accent. It didn't
          work out that way arid now foreign
          players are In demand for films with
          foreign backgrounds Just because of
          that accent.
          Real Accent Needed
          Tor example. In a film with a plot
          laid In China, no American actor
          trying to impersonate an Oriental
          can fake an accent properly. Under
          such circumstances there is In
          creasing opportunity for Orientals to
          win a place for themselves in the
          films in competition with western
          Anna May Wong Sees
          Land of Ancestors
          For the First Time
          Anna May Wong, Hollywood (croon (Ur, la in China, tho land of bat
          ancaatora, for tho firat lima.
          en, and my trip to China Is being
          made with this thought In mind."
          Mias Wong's home still Is In Los
          Angeles, but lor the past two years
          she has been traveling In Europe
          Last year she toured Franca, Oer
          many and other countries with a
          theatrical troupe.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1937-03-24/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&r=0.17%2C0.799%2C0.96%2C0.514%2C0&st=text</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna Wong Guarded
          In Extortion Plot
          HOLLYWOOD, March 24*
          (I.N.S.).—A bizarre extortion plot,
          involving Anna May Wong, Chi
          nese film star, and the family of
          Producer David O. Selznick, was
          revealed by police here today.
          Both Miss Wong and Mrs. Selz
          nick received threatening notes
          demanding $20,000. Heavy police
          guards were placed about their
          homes today. At the same time
          police revealed they were hold
          ing Dr. E. J. Foote, chiropractor,
          as a material witness in the case.
          Dr. Foote himself turned over a
          similar extortion note in which
          he was instructed to obtain the
          money from Miss Wong and Mrs.
          Selznick and “hold it for the
          gang.”
          His name appeared below the
          notes received by the two women.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1937-05-07/ed-1/?sp=45&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong Is Ready
          To Resume Picture Career
          Actress, Playing Here, Tires of Pvetirement
          and Would Return to Screen, But
          Not as Villainess.
          BY HARRY Mac ARTHUR.
          HERE'S one motion picture star who was brought up on the way*
          of old and won't cast aside the traditions of the Hollywood of the past
          When she stepped from a train yesterday afternoon at Union
          Station, Anna May Wong, the young ladv who’s played more
          Oriental villalnesses than Myma Loy and five other actresses, was told she
          had reservations at two different hotels. Which one did she want to
          keep?
          “Oh. keep ’em both, she replied,
          blandly indifferent to the fact that
          getting even one hotel reservation in
          this town is often an achievement of
          no little note. "There’s no use being
          crowded.”
          Renewing her acquaintance with
          Linton Wells, meeting Broderick
          Crawford, chatting pleasantly with
          them, Miss Wong says she's about
          over the effects of those recent
          extortion threats.
          It took something of a breakdown
          at Palm Springs to let all of the
          nerves out of her system, she admits,
          but now all is well. When she first
          received the threats on her life, she
          tightened up inside and didn't let
          off steam. Could have loosened
          things up by tossing a bit of furni
          ture around, she knows, but she was
          at a friend's house and felt it would
          not be joropeT to toss a friend's furni
          ture about.

          T^OW she’s going back to work.
          For the last couple of years
          Miss Wong lias been loafing, trying
          to kid herself into thinking she’s
          retiring, she calls it. But it hasn’t
          agreed with her and she's putting an
          end to loafing right now with a pair
          of stage appearances—one here at
          the Capitol and the other in New
          York.
          New York, she likes, because it puts
          her in contact with people who are
          doing things. Seems to have given
          her a desire to get back in the lists,
          so *he probably will be homing back
          to the Paramount studios before many
          moons.
          The only reason she decided to
          retire from films In the first place,
          •ays Miss Wong, was this business
          of always making her a scheming
          villainess.

          'J'HE seeming endless succession of
          unsympathetic roles rubbed her
          the wrong way until, she says, she
          was afraid she was going to begin
          to believe them herself. She’s not
          different from any other girl. Miss
          Wong claims, and she doesn't see why
          she can't be a heroine Just once.
          When she does go back to Holly
          wood, however, there will be better
          things in store. The studio finally
          is planning to do a series of detective
          yarns, with Miss Wong on the right
          side of the law and not the lass who
          leers around a comer and lures the
          hero to his doom.
          It’s an idea she's been trying to
          sell to the studio for a long, long
          time, and the first scripts, she says
          look good.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1937-03-26/ed-1/?sp=16&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>EXTORTIONIST
          NOTE WRITER
          CONFESSES
          HOLLYWOOD, March 26 (I.N.
          S.). —Arresting one woman and
          .announcing they had cleaned up
          ,a new phase of the case, author
          ities today were still confronted
          .'with the bizarre extortion plot
          .directed against Anna May Wong,
          ;Chinese screen star, and Mrs.
          David O. Selznick, wife of the film
          ■producer.
          1 A middle-aged woman from Du
          luth. Minn., was arrested and
          charged with writing a new threat
          note to Evangelist Aimee Semple
          McPherson.
          At the same time police re
          vealed that the evangelist received
          another note yesterday signed “A.
          M. Foote.” the same signature
          that appeared on the notes re
          ceived by Miss Wong and Mrs.
          Selznick.
          The suspect, who gave her name
          as Mrs. Lydia Swenson, 51, was
          arrested in her home. After
          lengthy questioning she confessed,
          stating:
          "I needed S2OO for the down
          payment on a new car.”
          One of the notes received by
          the evangelist demanded that'
          amount and conveyed a warning
          of “The Black Hand.”
          Officers admited, however, that i
          Mrs. Swenson could not have had
          any connection with the other
          note received by Mrs. McPher
          son, nor with those received by
          the film figures.
          The second note received yester
          day by Mrs. McPherson demanded
          that she meet the writer to dis
          cuss a biblical picture which he
          planned to produce.
          In the two notes to Mrs. Selz
          nick and Miss Wong the writer
          demanded $20,000 from each, to
          aid him in producing the picture.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88063294/1942-05-08/ed-1/?sp=17&q=Anna+May+Wong+United+China&r=-0.016,0.778,0.562,0.301,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1961-02-04/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&r=0.168,0.235,0.675,0.361,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong Dies;
          Film Star Since 1924
          HOLLYWOOD, Feb. 4 (AP).
          —Anna May Wong, 54, who
          became Hollywood’s first Chi
          nese movie star when she was
          17, died unexpectedly of a
          heart attack last night at her
          home in nearby Santa Monica.
          Miss Wong’s delicate beauty
          and grace of movement
          charmed two generations of
          moviegoers.
          Her physician said the ac
          tress had no history of heart
          disease and, except for occa
          sional brief illnesses, her
          health had been good.
          A native of Los Angeles.
          Miss Wong was one of seven
          children born in an apartment
          above a laundry. Only her
          brother, Richard, with whom
          she made her home, survives.
          Miss Wong never married.
          1924 Success
          Her first big screen success
          was opposite Douglas Fair
          banks in "Thief of Baghdad,”
          in 1924. It was a role that es
          tablished the stardom she held
          through the silent era into the
          early 19405, when she retired
          for 17 years. She abandoned
          films at the outbreak of World
          War II to work for United
          China Relief and to partici
          pate in USO activities.
          In recent years, she became
          active in television drama and
          returned to movies about a
          year ago for a role in "Portrait
          in Black,’’ a current release.
          At the time of her death,
          Miss Wong was under contract
          to Universal-International for
          "Flower Drum Song,” sched
          uled for production in March.
          Became Symbol
          Soon after her Hollywood
          debut. Miss Wong visited Eng
          land and played opposite Lau
          rence Olivier on the stage in
          "Circle of Chalk." Film as
          signments in Berlin followed.
          ANNA MAY WONG
          —AP Wirephoto
          Upon her return to the
          United States in the early
          19305, she became one of Holly
          wood’s busiest actresses. Her
          roles in such top films as
          "Shanghai Express" 'and
          "Daughter of the Dragon”
          characterized her as a symbol
          of Oriental mystery—a velvety
          beauty of great poise and cul
          ture.
          During this period, she
          made a lengthy personal ap
          pearance tour of Europe, visit
          ing the major capitals.
          In 1936 Miss Wong went to
          China for the first time, re
          maining a year. American
          born, the actress was a full
          blooded Chinese. Among her
          other notable pictures were
          "Daughter of Shanghai,” "A
          Study in Scarlet,” and "Tiger
          Bay.”
          Her early-day Hollywood
          films included "Old San Fran
          cisco,” "Across to Singapore.”
          "Forty Winks.” "Toll ot the
          Sea" and "Chinatown Charlie.”</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84021917/1950-06-09/ed-1/?sp=2&q=chinese+cinderella&r=-0.192,0.228,1.329,0.711,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069873/1922-01-27/ed-1/?sp=8&q=chinese+cinderella&r=0.388,0.247,0.44,0.235,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1937-08-08/ed-1/?sp=82&q=anna+may+wong&st=text&r=-0.465,0.081,1.212,1.212,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Her first taste of hospitality in the land
          of her ancestors was a banquet of
          forty-three courses in Shanghai. For
          Anna May Wong, the beautiful
          'Chinese-American star of the screen, found
          that fame had preceded her and that an ova
          tion was waiting for her, when she made her
          first trip to the Orient some fifteen months
          ago. Everybody was eager to entertain her,
          including the delightful Chinese Ambassador
          to France and his wife. Dr. and Mrs. Welling
          ton Koo, who had tiffin in her honor. Or in
          plain American, they gave a luncheon for her.
          Anna May Wong, whose Chinese name,
          Wong Lu Taong, means Frosted Yellow Wil
          lows, spent her childhood on Flower Street in
          the Chinatown of Los Angeles. When she was
          twelve she stole away from school and got
          herself accepted as one of a large crowd in a
          movie scene. It was a disappointment for,
          when the picture was released, the child could
          not distinguish herself in the throng, let alone
          be distinguished by others to whom she had
          been boasting.
          Since then, however, the tall Chinese girl
          has made an international reputation for
          herself as a motion picture star. Unforgettable
          in the American pictures, “Limehouse Blues,”
          “Daughter of the Dragon,” “Mr. Wu,”
          “Shanghai Express,” Anna May Wong has
          also made splendid pictures in Germany and
          England. ‘Tsong” was a German film, while
          her favorite motion picture parts came to her
          in the English productions, "The Pavement
          Butterfly” and “Piccadilly.”
          Anna May Wong loves China. "And to
          me,” she says, "Peiping is China.” Here you
          find the gardens that have been lovely for
          centuries, and all the splendor and beauty of
          ancient China, which so entrance her.
          But she finds pleasure also in the China
          towns of our American cities. “As soon as I
          arrive in a city," she will tell you, “I am eager
          to find Chinatown. Ten years ago when I was
          in New York for the first time, I said: ‘I want
          to see Chinatown.’ And when we came there,
          I caught at once the fragrance of musk which
          I love to smell.
          “As for Chinese food I like it so much that
          I am almost intoxicated with the pleasure
          of it. I always try to reciprocate hospitality
          by giving a Chinese dinner once a fortnight.
          When I am stopping at a hotel I take my
          friends to a top restaurant in Chinatown.
          “The Chinese, you know, can take almost
          Anything and fix it up into a marvelous meal.
          Chop suey, which Americans usually think of
          as a particular dish, is really unknown in
          China, at least in the sense in which foreigners
          speak of it. The words chop suey merely mean
          Anna May Wong, the beautiful American-born
          Chinese actress of stage and screen, finds exhilaration
          in the foods of her ancestors
          by Grace Turner
          Color ohotoympby by Hawftt a Kim __
          ABOVE —ANNA MAY WONG. WEARING A CHINESE
          DRESS. HAS TEA IN LEON EB EL JACOBS' STUDIO.
          THE CHINESE REFRESHMENTS ARE SHOWN BELOW
          ‘small bits,’ and hash or Irish stew are really
          a chop suey as a Chinese looks at it. Probably
          that is why 1 am so fond of hash and stew and
          all dishes prepared by a method similar to the
          Chinese.”
          One of the most delightful meals Anna May
          Wong can remember in America was served
          in the house of a guest professor from Prince
          ton. The chicken had been almost pxjwdered
          to make the soup for the first course and there
          were mustard greens to give it an indescrib
          ably wonderful flavor. Then' came a lobster
          dish, with the lobster cut in small pieces and
          served with a creamy garlic sauce. 4
          The "gold coined chicken” which was served
          next is really barbecued ham cut into rpund
          pieces, the shapie and size of coins, and put,
          sandwich-fashion, into tiny, delicate biscuits.
          The next or main course was stuffed chicken.
          Each piece is stuffed with a dressing made of
          rice, lotus berries, mushrooms, bamboo
          sprouts and water chestnuts. Then the chicken
          is fried; and Anally the pieces are cleverly put
          together, so that it comes to the table looking
          like a whole chicken.
          There were three other courses, one con
          sisting of steamed Ash with a pickled soy
          bean sauce; another being prepared, in the
          chopvsuey manner, of virgin pieas in the p>od,
          bamboo sprouts, water chestnuts and mush
          rooms and the last consisting of a light cheese.
          Sweets, according to Anna May Wong, are
          not to be expiected in a Chinese dinner. In
          China itself rice or chow mein appears as the
          last course and its advent announces that
          dinner is over, just as dessert does to us.
          Sweets, on the other hand, are served separ
          ately, p>erhap>s with tea as a between-meals
          course. There are almond cakes, for instance,
          and conserved fruits, and a favorite of Miss
          Wong’s which goes by the enticing name of
          Eight Precious Sweets. It is like a pudding
          and is served wun a sugar sauce.
          Of all dishes that Anna May Wong has ever
          tasted, the one that stands out is Peiping
          duck which she had in the city of that name
          at a three-hundred-year-old restaurant, called
          Tung Shin Low. One of the last emperors of
          China, growing weary sometimes of the royal
          food, is said to have gone there incognito to
          feast on the duck specialty which delighted
          Anna May Wong.
          Practically every part of the duck is used
          for a separate course. From the carcass comes
          your soup. The skin you will eat in a form
          very like tortillas, with a chutney sauce and
          an accompaniment of spring onions. But it is
          the meat of the duck that will make you think
          you have never before known what it means
          to enjoy food. It is kept dripping with oil
          while it is barbecued over a fire made of palm
          leaves. There will also be a custard made of
          duck eggs. And all these things together are
          what a Chinese means when he speaks to
          you reverently of Peiping duck.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1935-03-19/ed-2/?sp=7&q=anna+may+wong&r=0.434,0.437,0.492,0.263,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1931-08-16/ed-1/?sp=77&q=anna+may+wong&r=-0.042%2C0.478%2C0.435%2C0.232%2C0&st=text</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Holly wood s New Chinese Star
          Anna May Wong, American
          ißPßfirah- Born Daughter of Chinese
          ■HhßSp®! Parents Who Ran a China-
          town Laundry in Los
          Angeles, Gota Start in the
          Movies Through Lon Chaney and
          Marshall Neilan, but She Had to Win
          Success in Germany, England and on
          Broadway Before She Could Get Real
          Recognition at Home.
          BY DAN THOMAS.
          A LITTLE Chinese girl hu become the
          toast of Hollywood—but she had to
          go to Europe to attain this position.
          Anna May Wong is this girl, the
          Anna May Wong who spent her early
          years living above her father's
          laundry, whose only farewells r. Lien she left for
          Germany were from her family and who re
          turned to Hollywood a few weeks ago to be
          greeted by a throng of film folk, reporters and
          photographers.
          To understand Anna May. you must go back
          many years to the marriage of her mother and
          father.
          Her father lived in Sunning. Canton, China.
          And her mother came from Northern China
          near Peiping. Immediately after their marriage
          they migrated to Los Angeles, where Wong ex
          pected to follow In the footsteps of his ancestors
          In the quest of knowledge.
          A aeries of unforeseen circumstances however.
          w ji nf
          3
          am IP. Tgjfr
          Mi
          fffij p I y* l v 1
          flp
          h Xtitir 4nna May V ong. cost annul for her neu' American Talkie.
          t
          forced him to give up his pursuit of knowledge
          •nd seek m means of livelihood a few years after
          their arrival. It didn't take Wong long to dis
          cover that America offers the Chinese but three
          alternatives in the matter of earning a living
          lie could become a day laborer household
          Servant or laundry mart
          Wong chose the Utter He found a big house
          several miles from the Los Angeles Chinatown,
          remodeled two rooms as a laundry and fixed up
          the reel of the house as living quarters for his
          haul? It was in this house that Anna May,
          Mm third child, Was bam and Used during the
          a i -»m A
          fiftOndl vMV' W nfr rnBPuOOu ft*id SuDWiuffi
          dm to so -n fame fiwwTWlWl
          THE SUNDAY STAR, WASHINGTON, D. C., AUGUST T 6, 193!.
          There are {seven Wong children, all of whom
          shortly after their births were given appropriate
          English names to simplify their contact with
          the outside world—that is. all except the eldest
          daughter, who preferred her Chinese nam
          Ytng Anna May at birth
          was christened Pros ted Wei
          low Willows The other
          children are James. Mary, jm
          Prank. Roger and jQaj/r*
          Richard
          Anna May her-
          self is a typical
          American girl from
          a standpoint of in- ajw
          dependence educa
          uon and self coo- /1 Tjjj W j},,
          fldencc But .site is
          inordinately proud ws
          #sk
          itage And she is ,^V
          proud of Uie way
          she was brought ip
          in her sheltered Chinese home, according to
          many of the Chinese customs.
          True to theee traditions and codes. Mr and
          Mrs Wong raised their children to be implicitly
          obedient, courteous, unselfish and studious. At
          home they wore the besuitiful silken robes of
          the land they never had seen, but tlwir school
          wardrobes were made of gingham and serge
          Anna May remembers her school days as a
          long episode of serious work and constant study
          She attended the Los Angeles public schools
          daily.
          BUT she pever was permitted to play qrith
          her American friends after school, hours.
          1-nrtmf she had to run home after schoei
          ft jß^ftHk
          i ft
          rW 1 i
          IgfP 5 F i
          JHT imy i -r
          Sf m MH
          pt JW v "iHH
          Sb^

          in «bl ;«i
          M*-* *®v"ftft fc> _.; '•°mj‘‘-Xsii'
          -m ||SSB?£jjflß9ra lip
          a*|s| li
          •y v.* v
          ■||^^B l I^HK' 1
          r ':^E
          fc _« V/wj Wong imitating
          V'" Vforv Firkford in “Thu*
          |p~ Taming of the Shrew."
          chance her English text books for Chlnesa
          volumes and tush off to a thiee-hour session tn
          Chinese private school.
          Many times Anna May and her sisters ob
          jected to the strenuous study and work forced
          upon them. Why should they learn to read,
          write and speak Chinese? What good would It
          do them? Their father merely replied that It
          was his wish that his children should know the
          language of their ancestors.
          “I am very glad now that father insisted
          upon us studying ChineseJi- the charming ac
          tress says. “Had I not done so I would have
          missed much that is beautiful in life. I now
          knew the wisdom and philosophy of my people
          through the knowledge of their language.
          Father knew what was ahead of us. How
          wise he was!"
          Vacations never were favored by the head
          of the Wong family As a result the children
          always attended Summer school. Consequently
          when Anna May entered high school she was
          the youngest student in that institution—and,
          you might say, the smartest
          Piano study was added to her list of high
          school subjects at this time, leaving her little
          time to dwell upon her secret longing to be
          come an actress.
          This longing was of several years duration,
          dating back to a Chinese New Year celebra
          tion when she was six years old and her father
          took his family to their first picture show.
          “To this day I can remember in detail the
          six pictures that were shown that night for
          live cents per person,” declares Miss Wong.
          Pearl White was in a serial. Eddie Polo was
          in another picture There was a Keystone eop
          comedy and a melodrama that gave me night
          mares for a week afterward."
          During her third year in high school. Anna
          May suffered a nervous breakdown. The fam
          ily's Chinese physician prescribed rest under
          the sun. true to the traditions of his people,
          who believe that the sun will cure many ail
          ments Pot weeks afterward Anna May haunt
          ed the beaches and parks in search of health.
          But she tired of spending long hours doing
          nothing but sitting So she ssked her oouain,
          James Wong, a film actor, to take her with
          to the studio This James consented to
          do, always her with him whenever he
          had a locatVy" call so that she could remain
          in the freeh air That was before the stuthos
          became ae particular about having visitors
          around.
          While visiting on the set during the time
          m Uigrdtiathu smile. Several times a day bp
          A characteristic photo of the A meri*
          can-born chinese girl who is riding
          the crest of the wove in Hollywood.
          Anna May Wong, as she will appear
          in "Daughter of the Dragon
          would wander over to where she was sitting
          and engage her In a conversation for a few
          moments at a time.
          The man was Marshall Neilan, at that time
          one of Hollywood's beat directors. It was huge
          ly through him that Anna May s life took a
          sudden turn and she found herself a scree*
          actress, far better known within a very short
          time than her cousin James.
          There was some consternation in the Wong
          household when Anna May came home one
          night and told of an offer she had received
          from Neilan to play a role in a picture, "DUsty.'’
          which he was about to start.
          Wong and his wife sat up that night long
          after the children had retired, discussing the
          proposition from all angles. They knew that
          she would abide by their decision if they ob
          jected to her taking the role. But would it be
          quite fair to rob their daughter of such an
          opportunity? The following morning Wfcng
          V called his daughter and said:
          "I haven’t much faith in these things called
          moving pictures. Yet the most honored pro
          fessional men in all China are acton. If feu
          will take your sister with you as a chaperon
          and get home every night in time for eur
          evening meal you may accept the offer.”
          Little did he realize when he made that
          statement that within a few years his daugh
          ter's name would be dancing In electric lights
          the world over.
          When Anna May first stepped In front of
          the cameras her fears were unbounded. But
          she soon was made to feel at ease by the Bnd’
          ness of Neilan and her fellow players, Wesl-jf
          Barry. Marjorie Daw, Pat O'Malley and Noah
          Beery.
          "Dinty” placed the young Chinese girl well
          on the road to success. No sooner had it been
          released than she was deluged with offers from
          casting directors in every studio. For more
          than a year she was kept constantly busy and
          her salary continued to grow.
          She easily was earning enough to take her
          family from their laundry house quarters, but
          th y preferred to stay there, and Anna Mag
          stayed with them.
          Then she signed a contract with a motion
          picture company operating in San Francisco.
          The company was unable to raise the necessary
          money for their production, but they refused
          to release Miss Wong until the termination of
          her contract one year later. Thus she was
          kept off the screen entirely for one year.
          piHE year is a long time In the film business.
          where every one forgets quickly. Anna
          Msy returned to Hollywood eager to don grease
          paint and get to work again.
          Studio executives end directors welcomed
          4 her with open arms—but they didn't offer hot
          any Jobs For 12 months she worked in ontt
          three films—t*o comedies and an exceOsWl
          rote in “Mr. Wu" with Lon Chaney.
          It was Chaney who kept her
          out of the business entirely at that time. Swm
          oms had eome to the young girl easily and Ad
          was wholely unprepared tor this sudden changa,
          n was only Chaney's encouragement that $pH
          earnmaot <*t ttiy*f*tt«t* pdjfh'
          9</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-stanford-white-murder</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-stories-by-mark-twain</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
