<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-anna-may-wong</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072054/1921-10-04/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CHINESE CINDERELLA REFUSES TO
    FORSAKE LAUNDRY FOR FILM FAME
    By LINTON WELLS
    a-.i ',^&lt;4..'E. A. Staff Correspondent
    1*00 A^OLS, Oct. 4.?Thn
    M veil known fairy prince la going
    'to. have a hard time persuading
    p lng Anna May Wong that the giid
    jO" ./'?d 'sMpper of moviedom can bring
    5- lier moro happiness than work in
    her fathor's little Chinese laundry.
    "Anna May, 16-year-olil Celestial
    fe '/Cinderella' of the studios, twink
    lea before the* acreen by day. and
    presides at the lronlng-hoard at
    .night.
    Well on her pretty way to fame,
    she says she will forego the prom
    I,/ Ised career without a righ if it
    'means'that her parents mnv lose
    pleasure or profit by her going.
    Enters Fairyland.
    Mavieland to Anna May holds
    all the thrills that fairyland offers
    her Occidental slsterH. Handsome
    lovers shower her with attentions
    Beautiful clothe* adorn her rlen
    der form. Jewels sparkle from
    her Jet black hair. Motor cars
    are"* at her beck anrl call. The
    thrill of the drama makes her for
    Vget that thn camera In recording
    all this for the beenfit of ar. amuse
    ment-loving public.
    All this until 5:30. Then her
    handsome suitors go home to their
    y wives and babies, her j||rels are
    placed in the studio safe over night,
    her beautiful clothes a-? tal: ?:s
    back-to the property room.
    Anna May pays the conductrv
    five cents and trolley-cars to the
    home above her father's laundry
    Hero there are hooks of the little
    laundry shop to he kept, and many
    shirt? to he pinned before they are
    wrapped to a wait, the rail of run
    tomers.
    In Laundry Home.
    Anna May Wong in her laundry
    home looks just an she does on the
    rcveen. The poat. would say that
    she stole her color or her fact
    .from a poppy, and that of h-?
    hands from a card en In.
    Anna Mny Wong Is a discover*
    of Marshall Neilan. It was while
    hunting for types for his produc
    Hon of V'DIntv" thai Neilan discov
    ?red her. and after much induce
    ment persuaded her father t ::llo\v
    her to forsake her shirt-pinning uc
    tlvities for the screen?at. leas* dur
    ing the day. Since then Anna May
    has played many good parts, for
    besides being an excellent "type.'
    she has unusual talent Her most
    f recent effort was a co-ftar part oti
    i:' posite I-on Chaney in "Mi' of
    Uf&lt;\"
    Site has not yet been convinced
    'bat her studio work is greater :bar.
    her dntie* to her fnmf-v. if
    can achieve a motion picture renu
    t at ion and-still r.tron-1 to h?r feth
    .?r's affairs she will always be ban
    y,. py, if rot. then her mn?ion picture'
    K career must rro. r&lt;>- filial devotion
    is inborn in the Chinese heart of
    Anna May.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1921-09-08/ed-1/?sp=14&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.046,0.665,0.503,0.511,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Little Chinese Cinderella of the Screen
    SOME time ngo I told .vou nbont tho wonderful chnrncter part than I-on Chancy
    plnys In Nellnn's now film, ,,Mts of Life." In fact. I rnved for nlinont two
    columni of typo over the mnrvels of tills innn's work nnd his enreer.
    A friend of mine out on tlie vviwt const writes me, however, thnt Chnney
    rcolly isn't the nmrvel of "Kit of Life" he gives the honor to n little Chinese
    girl, Annn Mny Won, whom we linvo nil frcen in other films.
    If yon, (lornlilitic, lind onre been n drudge, keeping books nt night for your
    fnthcr's dingy little Nhop and then Maidenly the moles hnd discovered jou nnd
    jou had mndc such n success of It thnt jour earnings were twice the earnings
    of your father's shop but otir fnther refused to regard tho movies seriously
    nnd Insisted on jour still keeping his books nt night what would ou do?
    Father would have to get out n search warrant to find you, wouldn't he?
    You would turn up jour prettv little nub nose In independence and strut right
    out and live your own life on mnr own sala'rj wouldn't jou? Thnt would be
    the way with most American girls
    Hut Chlncc girls are bt ought up from childhood to regard their father's
    commands as nltnost of divine orlum the Chinese girl who disobeys her pnrents
    Is dlsgrnted bejond snlnilon Ami Annn Mny Wong is n Chinese girl.
    Annn Mnj could now buy her fnthor's little laundry if he would sell, she
    hns made lots of innnev nnd mivimI It Hut fnther merely tolerates the movies.
    They are an Intention of the foreign devils and. while he doesn't mind Anna May
    earning money In them In the dnjtinie. he considers her first duty to him and that j
    duty menns continuing to keep his books and check up the laundry each night.
    The Oriental Cinderella of movielnnd Is Anna Maj. Movlclar.d holds for
    her nil the thrills thnt fairyland offers her little sisters. Here hnndsome lovers
    iihower her with nil the attentions of Homeos. Iitautlful clothes adorn her
    Jewels sparkle from her jet black hair nnd motorcars are at her beek and call.
    The thrill of the drama makes her forjet that the cntnorn is recording all this for
    the benefit of tho amusement-loving public of the country.
    OUE ltrr in fairyland until 5.30.
    then her handsome suiiori no
    home to their icives and babies, fler jewels arc placed in the studio
    info overnight and her beautiful clothri arc taken back to the property
    room. It i fAen that Anna May steps from fairyland to reality, pays
    the conductor fire cents and trolley-cars to her home in Xorth Figucroa
    street, above her father's laundry shop. Here there arc books of the
    little laundry business U be kept and many shirts to be pinned before
    they are xrrapped and placed on the ihelvc aicatting the call of the
    customers.
    THOSE who remember "Dinty" will recall the pretty Chinese girl who nssists
    Wesley Barry rescue the white girl from the den of the Malay. This was
    Anna May Wong, and It marked her first work ns n screen nctress. It was
    while hunting "tjpes" for his production that Marshall Neilnn discovered Anna
    May and finally induced her father to nllow her to forsake her shlrt-pinnlng
    activities nt least during the day.
    Since then Anna Slay has foimd herself in great demnnd among movie
    producers, for in addition to being an exceptional "tjpe" she has unu-ual talents
    "Outside the Law" and "Shame" are other films in which she appeared, and
    then Mnrshall Neilan again took her to his studio for the co-star part opposite
    Lon Chaney in "Hits of Life."
    Anna May Wong in her laundry home, my friend writes me, lookw just as
    he docs on the screen. Quiet, beautiful nnd industrious, Anna May pins t.hirt
    and adds figures with equal djesterity. Once at home her movie fairjland i
    forgotten In the reality of hard work to be overcome before she again dons her
    finery and plays the queen.
    There is a difference, however, between this Chinese Cinderella of the movies
    nnd tho Cinderella of old. Unlike her predecessor, Anna May Wong loves her i
    mental duties at home. She has grown up in an atmosphere of industry, for
    any one who has ever lost n collar knows that tho ramifications of a Chinese i
    laundry demand ceaseless activitj. Anna May's laundry is a machine of human
    parts, ns complicated as one of springs nnd wheels. The wash goes in one end
    and vanishes, the shirts one way. the collars another, the socks here, the under
    clothing th'ere. And then they all come out together in neat piles.
    "Whether the producer needs n Chinese slave girl or a princess, Anna May
    always qualifies In her inovla work. In "Bits of Life," ns the wife of. a rich
    LOWLY ACCORDION
    NOW HELPS STIR
    SCREEN EMOTIONS
    Anna May
    Wong is the
    I t 'I'sr t pmn"f f yiT-s iMtHMlrriffT iirr'rTWlW IMlfWMf lMimWTtmHKKlMmUKwU
    sw?.w"f i!PMriJlaf1ff
    cwper of gambling nnd opium joints in San Francisco's Chinatown, she is
    asked to play one of tho most striking characters yet created by Hugh Wiley,
    whose Chinese fiction in the Saturday Evening Post has established him as the
    leading author of this typo of story.
    Very often the studio exacts much of her vitality and It is not uncommon
    for her to start work at 0 in tho morning nnd work until 0 In the evening
    before tho glaring light thnt bap one's strength. Yet Anna Mny never misses
    her work evenings nt the little Chin'-e laundry.
    TUB call of the Neic "World nil uniiccrcd by Anna and still it docs
    not cause her to octroy the filial duties of the Old. That is the
    Chinese xcay. To the ichite gul this icould be an unusual procedure.
    To the Chinese girl f is tho molt natural thing m the tcorld, Anna
    May has not yet been convinred thnt her studio icork is greater than
    her duties to her family. If she ran arhieie a motion-picture icputa
    Hon and still attend to her fathtr t afjntrn, hc cill alicays be happy
    Otherwise she Kill havo to desert hir fairyland.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1931-08-16/ed-1/?sp=77&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.3,0.368,1.599,1.599,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Holly wood s New Chinese Star
          Anna May Wong, American
          ißPßfirah- Born Daughter of Chinese
          ■HhßSp®! Parents Who Ran a China-
          town Laundry in Los
          Angeles, Gota Start in the
          Movies Through Lon Chaney and
          Marshall Neilan, but She Had to Win
          Success in Germany, England and on
          Broadway Before She Could Get Real
          Recognition at Home.
          BY DAN THOMAS.
          A LITTLE Chinese girl hu become the
          toast of Hollywood—but she had to
          go to Europe to attain this position.
          Anna May Wong is this girl, the
          Anna May Wong who spent her early
          years living above her father's
          laundry, whose only farewells r. Lien she left for
          Germany were from her family and who re
          turned to Hollywood a few weeks ago to be
          greeted by a throng of film folk, reporters and
          photographers.
          To understand Anna May. you must go back
          many years to the marriage of her mother and
          father.
          Her father lived in Sunning. Canton, China.
          And her mother came from Northern China
          near Peiping. Immediately after their marriage
          they migrated to Los Angeles, where Wong ex
          pected to follow In the footsteps of his ancestors
          In the quest of knowledge.
          A aeries of unforeseen circumstances however.
          w ji nf
          3
          am IP. Tgjfr
          Mi
          fffij p I y* l v 1
          flp
          h Xtitir 4nna May V ong. cost annul for her neu' American Talkie.
          t
          forced him to give up his pursuit of knowledge
          •nd seek m means of livelihood a few years after
          their arrival. It didn't take Wong long to dis
          cover that America offers the Chinese but three
          alternatives in the matter of earning a living
          lie could become a day laborer household
          Servant or laundry mart
          Wong chose the Utter He found a big house
          several miles from the Los Angeles Chinatown,
          remodeled two rooms as a laundry and fixed up
          the reel of the house as living quarters for his
          haul? It was in this house that Anna May,
          Mm third child, Was bam and Used during the
          a i -»m A
          fiftOndl vMV' W nfr rnBPuOOu ft*id SuDWiuffi
          dm to so -n fame fiwwTWlWl
          THE SUNDAY STAR, WASHINGTON, D. C., AUGUST T 6, 193!.
          There are {seven Wong children, all of whom
          shortly after their births were given appropriate
          English names to simplify their contact with
          the outside world—that is. all except the eldest
          daughter, who preferred her Chinese nam
          Ytng Anna May at birth
          was christened Pros ted Wei
          low Willows The other
          children are James. Mary, jm
          Prank. Roger and jQaj/r*
          Richard
          Anna May her-
          self is a typical
          American girl from
          a standpoint of in- ajw
          dependence educa
          uon and self coo- /1 Tjjj W j},,
          fldencc But .site is
          inordinately proud ws
          #sk
          itage And she is ,^V
          proud of Uie way
          she was brought ip
          in her sheltered Chinese home, according to
          many of the Chinese customs.
          True to theee traditions and codes. Mr and
          Mrs Wong raised their children to be implicitly
          obedient, courteous, unselfish and studious. At
          home they wore the besuitiful silken robes of
          the land they never had seen, but tlwir school
          wardrobes were made of gingham and serge
          Anna May remembers her school days as a
          long episode of serious work and constant study
          She attended the Los Angeles public schools
          daily.
          BUT she pever was permitted to play qrith
          her American friends after school, hours.
          1-nrtmf she had to run home after schoei
          ft jß^ftHk
          i ft
          rW 1 i
          IgfP 5 F i
          JHT imy i -r
          Sf m MH
          pt JW v "iHH
          Sb^

          in «bl ;«i
          M*-* *®v"ftft fc> _.; '•°mj‘‘-Xsii'
          -m ||SSB?£jjflß9ra lip
          a*|s| li
          •y v.* v
          ■||^^B l I^HK' 1
          r ':^E
          fc _« V/wj Wong imitating
          V'" Vforv Firkford in “Thu*
          |p~ Taming of the Shrew."
          chance her English text books for Chlnesa
          volumes and tush off to a thiee-hour session tn
          Chinese private school.
          Many times Anna May and her sisters ob
          jected to the strenuous study and work forced
          upon them. Why should they learn to read,
          write and speak Chinese? What good would It
          do them? Their father merely replied that It
          was his wish that his children should know the
          language of their ancestors.
          “I am very glad now that father insisted
          upon us studying ChineseJi- the charming ac
          tress says. “Had I not done so I would have
          missed much that is beautiful in life. I now
          knew the wisdom and philosophy of my people
          through the knowledge of their language.
          Father knew what was ahead of us. How
          wise he was!"
          Vacations never were favored by the head
          of the Wong family As a result the children
          always attended Summer school. Consequently
          when Anna May entered high school she was
          the youngest student in that institution—and,
          you might say, the smartest
          Piano study was added to her list of high
          school subjects at this time, leaving her little
          time to dwell upon her secret longing to be
          come an actress.
          This longing was of several years duration,
          dating back to a Chinese New Year celebra
          tion when she was six years old and her father
          took his family to their first picture show.
          “To this day I can remember in detail the
          six pictures that were shown that night for
          live cents per person,” declares Miss Wong.
          Pearl White was in a serial. Eddie Polo was
          in another picture There was a Keystone eop
          comedy and a melodrama that gave me night
          mares for a week afterward."
          During her third year in high school. Anna
          May suffered a nervous breakdown. The fam
          ily's Chinese physician prescribed rest under
          the sun. true to the traditions of his people,
          who believe that the sun will cure many ail
          ments Pot weeks afterward Anna May haunt
          ed the beaches and parks in search of health.
          But she tired of spending long hours doing
          nothing but sitting So she ssked her oouain,
          James Wong, a film actor, to take her with
          to the studio This James consented to
          do, always her with him whenever he
          had a locatVy" call so that she could remain
          in the freeh air That was before the stuthos
          became ae particular about having visitors
          around.
          While visiting on the set during the time
          m Uigrdtiathu smile. Several times a day bp
          A characteristic photo of the A meri*
          can-born chinese girl who is riding
          the crest of the wove in Hollywood.
          Anna May Wong, as she will appear
          in "Daughter of the Dragon
          would wander over to where she was sitting
          and engage her In a conversation for a few
          moments at a time.
          The man was Marshall Neilan, at that time
          one of Hollywood's beat directors. It was huge
          ly through him that Anna May s life took a
          sudden turn and she found herself a scree*
          actress, far better known within a very short
          time than her cousin James.
          There was some consternation in the Wong
          household when Anna May came home one
          night and told of an offer she had received
          from Neilan to play a role in a picture, "DUsty.'’
          which he was about to start.
          Wong and his wife sat up that night long
          after the children had retired, discussing the
          proposition from all angles. They knew that
          she would abide by their decision if they ob
          jected to her taking the role. But would it be
          quite fair to rob their daughter of such an
          opportunity? The following morning Wfcng
          V called his daughter and said:
          "I haven’t much faith in these things called
          moving pictures. Yet the most honored pro
          fessional men in all China are acton. If feu
          will take your sister with you as a chaperon
          and get home every night in time for eur
          evening meal you may accept the offer.”
          Little did he realize when he made that
          statement that within a few years his daugh
          ter's name would be dancing In electric lights
          the world over.
          When Anna May first stepped In front of
          the cameras her fears were unbounded. But
          she soon was made to feel at ease by the Bnd’
          ness of Neilan and her fellow players, Wesl-jf
          Barry. Marjorie Daw, Pat O'Malley and Noah
          Beery.
          "Dinty” placed the young Chinese girl well
          on the road to success. No sooner had it been
          released than she was deluged with offers from
          casting directors in every studio. For more
          than a year she was kept constantly busy and
          her salary continued to grow.
          She easily was earning enough to take her
          family from their laundry house quarters, but
          th y preferred to stay there, and Anna Mag
          stayed with them.
          Then she signed a contract with a motion
          picture company operating in San Francisco.
          The company was unable to raise the necessary
          money for their production, but they refused
          to release Miss Wong until the termination of
          her contract one year later. Thus she was
          kept off the screen entirely for one year.
          piHE year is a long time In the film business.
          where every one forgets quickly. Anna
          Msy returned to Hollywood eager to don grease
          paint and get to work again.
          Studio executives end directors welcomed
          4 her with open arms—but they didn't offer hot
          any Jobs For 12 months she worked in ontt
          three films—t*o comedies and an exceOsWl
          rote in “Mr. Wu" with Lon Chaney.
          It was Chaney who kept her
          out of the business entirely at that time. Swm
          oms had eome to the young girl easily and Ad
          was wholely unprepared tor this sudden changa,
          n was only Chaney's encouragement that $pH
          earnmaot &lt;*t ttiy*f*tt«t* pdjfh'
          9</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1932-04-13/ed-1/?sp=24&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&amp;r=-0.1,0.118,0.783,0.419,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Face and Hands
          In Them You Read Character
          Wm JM jt j
          ANNA MAY WONG’S CLEVER POSE
          This shows the face and hands of Anna May Wong, young
          Chinese actress, born in the United States. There could be
          no better arrangement of a photograph to show, in condensed
          •pace, the spirit dwelling within.
          From the face and the hands you learn more than from all
          the rest of the body, all, in fact, that you need to know.
          The eyes reflect the mind and spirit, the mouth reveals
          emotions, cold, passionate or neutral.
          The forehead, in this case too much concealed, is most
          important of all, for that which is back of the forehead is
          really THE HUMAN BEING.
          As for the hands, they tell a thousand stories. The fingers,
          long, tapering, with the hand itself narrow, show what we
          call "refinement,” the absence of hard work through a num
          ber of generations.
          Fingers blunt at the end, with broad nails, tell one story.
          Too much "refinement” in the hands may show that a
          person belongs to a family dying out, losing energy. Refine
          ment is admirable, but there must always be STRENGTH, to
          make refinement efficient and useful.
          In the thumb alone you may read character.
          According to the Kiralfy brothers, theatrical men of long
          ago, you can tell from the thumb the shape of the whole body.
          The Kiralfys, producing the "Black Crook,” and other per
          formances in which young ladies were displayed in tights, in
          the old days, needed young ladies with well-shaped legs.
          But the Kiralfys said: "All we need to see is the girl’s thumb.
          As soon as we see the thumb we know just how she will look
          in tights.” This, presumably, saved the young ladies apply
          ing for jobs some embarrassment, and saved time for the
          Kiralfys.
          Study hands and faces, eyes for sincerity, the chin for
          force of character, the ears for generosity, or the reverse, the
          mouth for emotion, the forehead for intelligence, the hands
          for the physical and racial past, and you study a human
          being completely.
          In addition, you will be interested in this young face, com
          bining the mystery of the East with the Western influence of
          birth in this country.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1936-03-12/ed-1/?sp=11&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong, Hollywood film
          alar, la In the land of her ancestors
          now for the first time in her life
          Born and reared In Los Angeles.
          the American Chineae girl who sup
          plied the Oriental allure to the mo
          tion picture industry for 15 years,
          had her first glimpse of China here
          the other day when she stepped ofi
          the gangplank of a liner from San
          Francisco
          She plans to pa* a year in the
          Orient. After seeing Hongkong and
          Canton and after visiting her mother
          and sisters whom she hasn't seen
          for years. Miss Wong will travel
          throughout the country to see the
          ‘real" China, not the China she
          knew In the movies, from books and
          from hearsay.
          Hopes to Learn Language
          Incidentally she hopes to leam
          the Chines* language, but she un
          derstands It Is difficult.
          Rumors of a romance accompanied
          her arrival here. Fellow passengers
          on the steamer whispered Into ship
          news reporters’ ears when the liner
          docked that the son of a millionaire
          Canton merchant was waiting for
          her to be his bride. No such thing.
          Miss Wong denied promptly. She Is
          "wedded to her art."
          No Movte Actress Airs
          There Is none of the movie actress
          airs abcut demure, placid Anna
          Wong. She scorns make-up—a lit
          tle lipstick Is her only concession—
          snd she has some ideas of her own
          concerning the things she wears.
          "Years of experimenting with
          western clothing have convinced me
          that the only colors that really suit
          Orientals are black and white." she
          said. "It Is ridiculous for us to ac
          cept bllndl; the current fashions of
          New York and Paris."
          As if In demonstration, she was
          wearing an almost severe black suit
          with white waist, an outfit the sim
          plicity of which was well suited to
          her aopearance and manner.
          Her Opinion of Hollywood
          Hollywood?
          "What the mo* »e capital needs is
          freshness, freshness in everything
          characters, plots, actors and ac
          tresses.” she asserted. "No wonder
          such stars as Garbo and Dietrich
          had such meteoric success
          "The adaptation of commonplace
          stories no longer satisfies cinema
          audiences, and producers are in
          creasingly looking abroad for un
          usual material, which opens further
          opportunities for foreign playera.
          "When the talkies came everyone
          thought the foreign actors then In
          Hollywood would be thrown out of
          Jobs because they couldn’t speak
          English without an accent. It didn't
          work out that way arid now foreign
          players are In demand for films with
          foreign backgrounds Just because of
          that accent.
          Real Accent Needed
          Tor example. In a film with a plot
          laid In China, no American actor
          trying to impersonate an Oriental
          can fake an accent properly. Under
          such circumstances there is In
          creasing opportunity for Orientals to
          win a place for themselves in the
          films in competition with western
          Anna May Wong Sees
          Land of Ancestors
          For the First Time
          Anna May Wong, Hollywood (croon (Ur, la in China, tho land of bat
          ancaatora, for tho firat lima.
          en, and my trip to China Is being
          made with this thought In mind."
          Mias Wong's home still Is In Los
          Angeles, but lor the past two years
          she has been traveling In Europe
          Last year she toured Franca, Oer
          many and other countries with a
          theatrical troupe.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1937-03-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&amp;r=0.17%2C0.799%2C0.96%2C0.514%2C0&amp;st=text</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna Wong Guarded
          In Extortion Plot
          HOLLYWOOD, March 24*
          (I.N.S.).—A bizarre extortion plot,
          involving Anna May Wong, Chi
          nese film star, and the family of
          Producer David O. Selznick, was
          revealed by police here today.
          Both Miss Wong and Mrs. Selz
          nick received threatening notes
          demanding $20,000. Heavy police
          guards were placed about their
          homes today. At the same time
          police revealed they were hold
          ing Dr. E. J. Foote, chiropractor,
          as a material witness in the case.
          Dr. Foote himself turned over a
          similar extortion note in which
          he was instructed to obtain the
          money from Miss Wong and Mrs.
          Selznick and “hold it for the
          gang.”
          His name appeared below the
          notes received by the two women.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1937-05-07/ed-1/?sp=45&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong Is Ready
          To Resume Picture Career
          Actress, Playing Here, Tires of Pvetirement
          and Would Return to Screen, But
          Not as Villainess.
          BY HARRY Mac ARTHUR.
          HERE'S one motion picture star who was brought up on the way*
          of old and won't cast aside the traditions of the Hollywood of the past
          When she stepped from a train yesterday afternoon at Union
          Station, Anna May Wong, the young ladv who’s played more
          Oriental villalnesses than Myma Loy and five other actresses, was told she
          had reservations at two different hotels. Which one did she want to
          keep?
          “Oh. keep ’em both, she replied,
          blandly indifferent to the fact that
          getting even one hotel reservation in
          this town is often an achievement of
          no little note. "There’s no use being
          crowded.”
          Renewing her acquaintance with
          Linton Wells, meeting Broderick
          Crawford, chatting pleasantly with
          them, Miss Wong says she's about
          over the effects of those recent
          extortion threats.
          It took something of a breakdown
          at Palm Springs to let all of the
          nerves out of her system, she admits,
          but now all is well. When she first
          received the threats on her life, she
          tightened up inside and didn't let
          off steam. Could have loosened
          things up by tossing a bit of furni
          ture around, she knows, but she was
          at a friend's house and felt it would
          not be joropeT to toss a friend's furni
          ture about.

          T^OW she’s going back to work.
          For the last couple of years
          Miss Wong lias been loafing, trying
          to kid herself into thinking she’s
          retiring, she calls it. But it hasn’t
          agreed with her and she's putting an
          end to loafing right now with a pair
          of stage appearances—one here at
          the Capitol and the other in New
          York.
          New York, she likes, because it puts
          her in contact with people who are
          doing things. Seems to have given
          her a desire to get back in the lists,
          so *he probably will be homing back
          to the Paramount studios before many
          moons.
          The only reason she decided to
          retire from films In the first place,
          •ays Miss Wong, was this business
          of always making her a scheming
          villainess.

          'J'HE seeming endless succession of
          unsympathetic roles rubbed her
          the wrong way until, she says, she
          was afraid she was going to begin
          to believe them herself. She’s not
          different from any other girl. Miss
          Wong claims, and she doesn't see why
          she can't be a heroine Just once.
          When she does go back to Holly
          wood, however, there will be better
          things in store. The studio finally
          is planning to do a series of detective
          yarns, with Miss Wong on the right
          side of the law and not the lass who
          leers around a comer and lures the
          hero to his doom.
          It’s an idea she's been trying to
          sell to the studio for a long, long
          time, and the first scripts, she says
          look good.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1937-03-26/ed-1/?sp=16&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>EXTORTIONIST
          NOTE WRITER
          CONFESSES
          HOLLYWOOD, March 26 (I.N.
          S.). —Arresting one woman and
          .announcing they had cleaned up
          ,a new phase of the case, author
          ities today were still confronted
          .'with the bizarre extortion plot
          .directed against Anna May Wong,
          ;Chinese screen star, and Mrs.
          David O. Selznick, wife of the film
          ■producer.
          1 A middle-aged woman from Du
          luth. Minn., was arrested and
          charged with writing a new threat
          note to Evangelist Aimee Semple
          McPherson.
          At the same time police re
          vealed that the evangelist received
          another note yesterday signed “A.
          M. Foote.” the same signature
          that appeared on the notes re
          ceived by Miss Wong and Mrs.
          Selznick.
          The suspect, who gave her name
          as Mrs. Lydia Swenson, 51, was
          arrested in her home. After
          lengthy questioning she confessed,
          stating:
          "I needed S2OO for the down
          payment on a new car.”
          One of the notes received by
          the evangelist demanded that'
          amount and conveyed a warning
          of “The Black Hand.”
          Officers admited, however, that i
          Mrs. Swenson could not have had
          any connection with the other
          note received by Mrs. McPher
          son, nor with those received by
          the film figures.
          The second note received yester
          day by Mrs. McPherson demanded
          that she meet the writer to dis
          cuss a biblical picture which he
          planned to produce.
          In the two notes to Mrs. Selz
          nick and Miss Wong the writer
          demanded $20,000 from each, to
          aid him in producing the picture.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88063294/1942-05-08/ed-1/?sp=17&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+United+China&amp;r=-0.016,0.778,0.562,0.301,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1961-02-04/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=Anna+May+Wong+Chinese+actress&amp;r=0.168,0.235,0.675,0.361,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Anna May Wong Dies;
          Film Star Since 1924
          HOLLYWOOD, Feb. 4 (AP).
          —Anna May Wong, 54, who
          became Hollywood’s first Chi
          nese movie star when she was
          17, died unexpectedly of a
          heart attack last night at her
          home in nearby Santa Monica.
          Miss Wong’s delicate beauty
          and grace of movement
          charmed two generations of
          moviegoers.
          Her physician said the ac
          tress had no history of heart
          disease and, except for occa
          sional brief illnesses, her
          health had been good.
          A native of Los Angeles.
          Miss Wong was one of seven
          children born in an apartment
          above a laundry. Only her
          brother, Richard, with whom
          she made her home, survives.
          Miss Wong never married.
          1924 Success
          Her first big screen success
          was opposite Douglas Fair
          banks in "Thief of Baghdad,”
          in 1924. It was a role that es
          tablished the stardom she held
          through the silent era into the
          early 19405, when she retired
          for 17 years. She abandoned
          films at the outbreak of World
          War II to work for United
          China Relief and to partici
          pate in USO activities.
          In recent years, she became
          active in television drama and
          returned to movies about a
          year ago for a role in "Portrait
          in Black,’’ a current release.
          At the time of her death,
          Miss Wong was under contract
          to Universal-International for
          "Flower Drum Song,” sched
          uled for production in March.
          Became Symbol
          Soon after her Hollywood
          debut. Miss Wong visited Eng
          land and played opposite Lau
          rence Olivier on the stage in
          "Circle of Chalk." Film as
          signments in Berlin followed.
          ANNA MAY WONG
          —AP Wirephoto
          Upon her return to the
          United States in the early
          19305, she became one of Holly
          wood’s busiest actresses. Her
          roles in such top films as
          "Shanghai Express" 'and
          "Daughter of the Dragon”
          characterized her as a symbol
          of Oriental mystery—a velvety
          beauty of great poise and cul
          ture.
          During this period, she
          made a lengthy personal ap
          pearance tour of Europe, visit
          ing the major capitals.
          In 1936 Miss Wong went to
          China for the first time, re
          maining a year. American
          born, the actress was a full
          blooded Chinese. Among her
          other notable pictures were
          "Daughter of Shanghai,” "A
          Study in Scarlet,” and "Tiger
          Bay.”
          Her early-day Hollywood
          films included "Old San Fran
          cisco,” "Across to Singapore.”
          "Forty Winks.” "Toll ot the
          Sea" and "Chinatown Charlie.”</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84021917/1950-06-09/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=chinese+cinderella&amp;r=-0.192,0.228,1.329,0.711,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069873/1922-01-27/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=chinese+cinderella&amp;r=0.388,0.247,0.44,0.235,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1937-08-08/ed-1/?sp=82&amp;q=anna+may+wong&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.465,0.081,1.212,1.212,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Her first taste of hospitality in the land
          of her ancestors was a banquet of
          forty-three courses in Shanghai. For
          Anna May Wong, the beautiful
          'Chinese-American star of the screen, found
          that fame had preceded her and that an ova
          tion was waiting for her, when she made her
          first trip to the Orient some fifteen months
          ago. Everybody was eager to entertain her,
          including the delightful Chinese Ambassador
          to France and his wife. Dr. and Mrs. Welling
          ton Koo, who had tiffin in her honor. Or in
          plain American, they gave a luncheon for her.
          Anna May Wong, whose Chinese name,
          Wong Lu Taong, means Frosted Yellow Wil
          lows, spent her childhood on Flower Street in
          the Chinatown of Los Angeles. When she was
          twelve she stole away from school and got
          herself accepted as one of a large crowd in a
          movie scene. It was a disappointment for,
          when the picture was released, the child could
          not distinguish herself in the throng, let alone
          be distinguished by others to whom she had
          been boasting.
          Since then, however, the tall Chinese girl
          has made an international reputation for
          herself as a motion picture star. Unforgettable
          in the American pictures, “Limehouse Blues,”
          “Daughter of the Dragon,” “Mr. Wu,”
          “Shanghai Express,” Anna May Wong has
          also made splendid pictures in Germany and
          England. ‘Tsong” was a German film, while
          her favorite motion picture parts came to her
          in the English productions, "The Pavement
          Butterfly” and “Piccadilly.”
          Anna May Wong loves China. "And to
          me,” she says, "Peiping is China.” Here you
          find the gardens that have been lovely for
          centuries, and all the splendor and beauty of
          ancient China, which so entrance her.
          But she finds pleasure also in the China
          towns of our American cities. “As soon as I
          arrive in a city," she will tell you, “I am eager
          to find Chinatown. Ten years ago when I was
          in New York for the first time, I said: ‘I want
          to see Chinatown.’ And when we came there,
          I caught at once the fragrance of musk which
          I love to smell.
          “As for Chinese food I like it so much that
          I am almost intoxicated with the pleasure
          of it. I always try to reciprocate hospitality
          by giving a Chinese dinner once a fortnight.
          When I am stopping at a hotel I take my
          friends to a top restaurant in Chinatown.
          “The Chinese, you know, can take almost
          Anything and fix it up into a marvelous meal.
          Chop suey, which Americans usually think of
          as a particular dish, is really unknown in
          China, at least in the sense in which foreigners
          speak of it. The words chop suey merely mean
          Anna May Wong, the beautiful American-born
          Chinese actress of stage and screen, finds exhilaration
          in the foods of her ancestors
          by Grace Turner
          Color ohotoympby by Hawftt a Kim __
          ABOVE —ANNA MAY WONG. WEARING A CHINESE
          DRESS. HAS TEA IN LEON EB EL JACOBS' STUDIO.
          THE CHINESE REFRESHMENTS ARE SHOWN BELOW
          ‘small bits,’ and hash or Irish stew are really
          a chop suey as a Chinese looks at it. Probably
          that is why 1 am so fond of hash and stew and
          all dishes prepared by a method similar to the
          Chinese.”
          One of the most delightful meals Anna May
          Wong can remember in America was served
          in the house of a guest professor from Prince
          ton. The chicken had been almost pxjwdered
          to make the soup for the first course and there
          were mustard greens to give it an indescrib
          ably wonderful flavor. Then' came a lobster
          dish, with the lobster cut in small pieces and
          served with a creamy garlic sauce. 4
          The "gold coined chicken” which was served
          next is really barbecued ham cut into rpund
          pieces, the shapie and size of coins, and put,
          sandwich-fashion, into tiny, delicate biscuits.
          The next or main course was stuffed chicken.
          Each piece is stuffed with a dressing made of
          rice, lotus berries, mushrooms, bamboo
          sprouts and water chestnuts. Then the chicken
          is fried; and Anally the pieces are cleverly put
          together, so that it comes to the table looking
          like a whole chicken.
          There were three other courses, one con
          sisting of steamed Ash with a pickled soy
          bean sauce; another being prepared, in the
          chopvsuey manner, of virgin pieas in the p>od,
          bamboo sprouts, water chestnuts and mush
          rooms and the last consisting of a light cheese.
          Sweets, according to Anna May Wong, are
          not to be expiected in a Chinese dinner. In
          China itself rice or chow mein appears as the
          last course and its advent announces that
          dinner is over, just as dessert does to us.
          Sweets, on the other hand, are served separ
          ately, p>erhap>s with tea as a between-meals
          course. There are almond cakes, for instance,
          and conserved fruits, and a favorite of Miss
          Wong’s which goes by the enticing name of
          Eight Precious Sweets. It is like a pudding
          and is served wun a sugar sauce.
          Of all dishes that Anna May Wong has ever
          tasted, the one that stands out is Peiping
          duck which she had in the city of that name
          at a three-hundred-year-old restaurant, called
          Tung Shin Low. One of the last emperors of
          China, growing weary sometimes of the royal
          food, is said to have gone there incognito to
          feast on the duck specialty which delighted
          Anna May Wong.
          Practically every part of the duck is used
          for a separate course. From the carcass comes
          your soup. The skin you will eat in a form
          very like tortillas, with a chutney sauce and
          an accompaniment of spring onions. But it is
          the meat of the duck that will make you think
          you have never before known what it means
          to enjoy food. It is kept dripping with oil
          while it is barbecued over a fire made of palm
          leaves. There will also be a custard made of
          duck eggs. And all these things together are
          what a Chinese means when he speaks to
          you reverently of Peiping duck.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063730/1935-03-19/ed-2/?sp=7&amp;q=anna+may+wong&amp;r=0.434,0.437,0.492,0.263,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1931-08-16/ed-1/?sp=77&amp;q=anna+may+wong&amp;r=-0.042%2C0.478%2C0.435%2C0.232%2C0&amp;st=text</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Holly wood s New Chinese Star
          Anna May Wong, American
          ißPßfirah- Born Daughter of Chinese
          ■HhßSp®! Parents Who Ran a China-
          town Laundry in Los
          Angeles, Gota Start in the
          Movies Through Lon Chaney and
          Marshall Neilan, but She Had to Win
          Success in Germany, England and on
          Broadway Before She Could Get Real
          Recognition at Home.
          BY DAN THOMAS.
          A LITTLE Chinese girl hu become the
          toast of Hollywood—but she had to
          go to Europe to attain this position.
          Anna May Wong is this girl, the
          Anna May Wong who spent her early
          years living above her father's
          laundry, whose only farewells r. Lien she left for
          Germany were from her family and who re
          turned to Hollywood a few weeks ago to be
          greeted by a throng of film folk, reporters and
          photographers.
          To understand Anna May. you must go back
          many years to the marriage of her mother and
          father.
          Her father lived in Sunning. Canton, China.
          And her mother came from Northern China
          near Peiping. Immediately after their marriage
          they migrated to Los Angeles, where Wong ex
          pected to follow In the footsteps of his ancestors
          In the quest of knowledge.
          A aeries of unforeseen circumstances however.
          w ji nf
          3
          am IP. Tgjfr
          Mi
          fffij p I y* l v 1
          flp
          h Xtitir 4nna May V ong. cost annul for her neu' American Talkie.
          t
          forced him to give up his pursuit of knowledge
          •nd seek m means of livelihood a few years after
          their arrival. It didn't take Wong long to dis
          cover that America offers the Chinese but three
          alternatives in the matter of earning a living
          lie could become a day laborer household
          Servant or laundry mart
          Wong chose the Utter He found a big house
          several miles from the Los Angeles Chinatown,
          remodeled two rooms as a laundry and fixed up
          the reel of the house as living quarters for his
          haul? It was in this house that Anna May,
          Mm third child, Was bam and Used during the
          a i -»m A
          fiftOndl vMV' W nfr rnBPuOOu ft*id SuDWiuffi
          dm to so -n fame fiwwTWlWl
          THE SUNDAY STAR, WASHINGTON, D. C., AUGUST T 6, 193!.
          There are {seven Wong children, all of whom
          shortly after their births were given appropriate
          English names to simplify their contact with
          the outside world—that is. all except the eldest
          daughter, who preferred her Chinese nam
          Ytng Anna May at birth
          was christened Pros ted Wei
          low Willows The other
          children are James. Mary, jm
          Prank. Roger and jQaj/r*
          Richard
          Anna May her-
          self is a typical
          American girl from
          a standpoint of in- ajw
          dependence educa
          uon and self coo- /1 Tjjj W j},,
          fldencc But .site is
          inordinately proud ws
          #sk
          itage And she is ,^V
          proud of Uie way
          she was brought ip
          in her sheltered Chinese home, according to
          many of the Chinese customs.
          True to theee traditions and codes. Mr and
          Mrs Wong raised their children to be implicitly
          obedient, courteous, unselfish and studious. At
          home they wore the besuitiful silken robes of
          the land they never had seen, but tlwir school
          wardrobes were made of gingham and serge
          Anna May remembers her school days as a
          long episode of serious work and constant study
          She attended the Los Angeles public schools
          daily.
          BUT she pever was permitted to play qrith
          her American friends after school, hours.
          1-nrtmf she had to run home after schoei
          ft jß^ftHk
          i ft
          rW 1 i
          IgfP 5 F i
          JHT imy i -r
          Sf m MH
          pt JW v "iHH
          Sb^

          in «bl ;«i
          M*-* *®v"ftft fc> _.; '•°mj‘‘-Xsii'
          -m ||SSB?£jjflß9ra lip
          a*|s| li
          •y v.* v
          ■||^^B l I^HK' 1
          r ':^E
          fc _« V/wj Wong imitating
          V'" Vforv Firkford in “Thu*
          |p~ Taming of the Shrew."
          chance her English text books for Chlnesa
          volumes and tush off to a thiee-hour session tn
          Chinese private school.
          Many times Anna May and her sisters ob
          jected to the strenuous study and work forced
          upon them. Why should they learn to read,
          write and speak Chinese? What good would It
          do them? Their father merely replied that It
          was his wish that his children should know the
          language of their ancestors.
          “I am very glad now that father insisted
          upon us studying ChineseJi- the charming ac
          tress says. “Had I not done so I would have
          missed much that is beautiful in life. I now
          knew the wisdom and philosophy of my people
          through the knowledge of their language.
          Father knew what was ahead of us. How
          wise he was!"
          Vacations never were favored by the head
          of the Wong family As a result the children
          always attended Summer school. Consequently
          when Anna May entered high school she was
          the youngest student in that institution—and,
          you might say, the smartest
          Piano study was added to her list of high
          school subjects at this time, leaving her little
          time to dwell upon her secret longing to be
          come an actress.
          This longing was of several years duration,
          dating back to a Chinese New Year celebra
          tion when she was six years old and her father
          took his family to their first picture show.
          “To this day I can remember in detail the
          six pictures that were shown that night for
          live cents per person,” declares Miss Wong.
          Pearl White was in a serial. Eddie Polo was
          in another picture There was a Keystone eop
          comedy and a melodrama that gave me night
          mares for a week afterward."
          During her third year in high school. Anna
          May suffered a nervous breakdown. The fam
          ily's Chinese physician prescribed rest under
          the sun. true to the traditions of his people,
          who believe that the sun will cure many ail
          ments Pot weeks afterward Anna May haunt
          ed the beaches and parks in search of health.
          But she tired of spending long hours doing
          nothing but sitting So she ssked her oouain,
          James Wong, a film actor, to take her with
          to the studio This James consented to
          do, always her with him whenever he
          had a locatVy" call so that she could remain
          in the freeh air That was before the stuthos
          became ae particular about having visitors
          around.
          While visiting on the set during the time
          m Uigrdtiathu smile. Several times a day bp
          A characteristic photo of the A meri*
          can-born chinese girl who is riding
          the crest of the wove in Hollywood.
          Anna May Wong, as she will appear
          in "Daughter of the Dragon
          would wander over to where she was sitting
          and engage her In a conversation for a few
          moments at a time.
          The man was Marshall Neilan, at that time
          one of Hollywood's beat directors. It was huge
          ly through him that Anna May s life took a
          sudden turn and she found herself a scree*
          actress, far better known within a very short
          time than her cousin James.
          There was some consternation in the Wong
          household when Anna May came home one
          night and told of an offer she had received
          from Neilan to play a role in a picture, "DUsty.'’
          which he was about to start.
          Wong and his wife sat up that night long
          after the children had retired, discussing the
          proposition from all angles. They knew that
          she would abide by their decision if they ob
          jected to her taking the role. But would it be
          quite fair to rob their daughter of such an
          opportunity? The following morning Wfcng
          V called his daughter and said:
          "I haven’t much faith in these things called
          moving pictures. Yet the most honored pro
          fessional men in all China are acton. If feu
          will take your sister with you as a chaperon
          and get home every night in time for eur
          evening meal you may accept the offer.”
          Little did he realize when he made that
          statement that within a few years his daugh
          ter's name would be dancing In electric lights
          the world over.
          When Anna May first stepped In front of
          the cameras her fears were unbounded. But
          she soon was made to feel at ease by the Bnd’
          ness of Neilan and her fellow players, Wesl-jf
          Barry. Marjorie Daw, Pat O'Malley and Noah
          Beery.
          "Dinty” placed the young Chinese girl well
          on the road to success. No sooner had it been
          released than she was deluged with offers from
          casting directors in every studio. For more
          than a year she was kept constantly busy and
          her salary continued to grow.
          She easily was earning enough to take her
          family from their laundry house quarters, but
          th y preferred to stay there, and Anna Mag
          stayed with them.
          Then she signed a contract with a motion
          picture company operating in San Francisco.
          The company was unable to raise the necessary
          money for their production, but they refused
          to release Miss Wong until the termination of
          her contract one year later. Thus she was
          kept off the screen entirely for one year.
          piHE year is a long time In the film business.
          where every one forgets quickly. Anna
          Msy returned to Hollywood eager to don grease
          paint and get to work again.
          Studio executives end directors welcomed
          4 her with open arms—but they didn't offer hot
          any Jobs For 12 months she worked in ontt
          three films—t*o comedies and an exceOsWl
          rote in “Mr. Wu" with Lon Chaney.
          It was Chaney who kept her
          out of the business entirely at that time. Swm
          oms had eome to the young girl easily and Ad
          was wholely unprepared tor this sudden changa,
          n was only Chaney's encouragement that $pH
          earnmaot &lt;*t ttiy*f*tt«t* pdjfh'
          9</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-stanford-white-murder</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1906-06-26/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Harry+Thaw+Stanford+White+kills+Mrs+Evelyn+Nesbit+Thaw+JEALOUS+RAGE+jealousy+revenge+wife</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Thaw Tells Own Story StoryS v vOf a I
    S Of the Killing of White WhiteIn
    In Broken Sentences He Indicates Motive to toHave toHave I
    Have Been B en Jealousy Jealousyart Jealous Ya arid d J Revenge RevengeDeclares RevengeDeclaresDead Reve ReveDead n9eDeclare Declares DeclaresDead s
    Dead Man Ruined His Wife WifeKEW WifelEW WifeI
    KEW I EW YORK June Jun 26 26H 26Harry Harry ry K KThw Thaw millionaire assassin pf f Stan Stanrford Sbn Sbnford Stanford
    ford White the world famous architect early this morning told his h1 own ownstory ownstory I
    story of f the killing Jealousy hate and revenge were ere the motives He Hesaid Hesaid Hesaid
    said
    i
    We were all at a t party part at Martins the old Delmonico place MrsThaw MrsThaw Mrs MrsThaw
    Thaw and her stepfather W V J Holman a broker and others were werepresent werepresent cre crepresent
    present You will find out who they were later laterI laterI
    I was sitting at some distance from m my mywife wife Suddenly I saw her herget herget herget
    get very cry pale and begin to shiver I thought she was ill illI illI illI
    I made a motion to o inquire what was the matter She calir caP cal d a awaiter awniter awaiter
    waiter and wrote a note which she sent around the table to me The Thenote Thenote Thenote
    note said That dirty blackguard is here hereThen hereThen hereThen
    Then I turned and saw that damned scoundrel sitting there big bigfat bigfat bigfat
    fat and healthy and there she was vas all trembling and nervous nervousNO ncnousNO nervousNO
    NO REGRET FOR DEED
    Thaws face was covered with per perspiration perSDlraUon perspiration
    spiration as he talked but ho never neverasked neerasked neverasked
    asked about White He was seemingly seeminglycalm seemlnglycalm seeminglycalm
    calm although he must have been bee exert exerting exertIng exerting
    ing himself to be calm Thaw askedfor asked askedfor askeafor
    for a cigar cr ar and kept k t t puffing away a d at It Iteven Iteven iteven
    even rattc riser irter It had cone out outAgain outAgnln outAgain
    Again and again Thaw referred to
    the Incident IncIdentt i Martins MartinsThat MartlnaT DiartinsThat
    That T at poor delicate little thing all allnervous allnervous allnervous
    nervous and shaking la a reed reade be beI
    I
    said And there he was the big bighealthy blShealthy bighealthy
    healthy scoundrel God GodThis GodThis I IThis
    This man ruined my wife tEe He wontdo Wontdo wont wontdo
    do this any more or ruin any more morehomes morehomes morehomes
    homes White deserved all he gotThis got gotThis gatThis
    This statement by Thaw was made as as11e
    Tie sat In the Tenderloin station He Herepeated Herepeated Herepeated
    repeated parts of it time and time again againas a againas aln alnas
    as a man would do in the excitement excitementof
    of the moment The deathly pallor that thathad thathad thathad
    had marked him at the roof roo garden gardenhad gardenhadnot had hadsot hadnot
    not entirely goad ooe 1
    p
    THAW ALONE ALONEWALKS ALONEWALKS
    WALKS TO COURT COURTTO COURTTO
    TO SEE HUSBAND HUSBANDPolice
    Police Had Made An Un Unsuccessful Unsuccessful Unsuccessful
    successful All t Night NightSearch Nightt NightSe3rch NightSearch
    Search For Her HerNEW HerNEW HerNEW
    NEW YORK June 25 6EVeln Evelyn Nosbit NesbiThaw NosbitThaw XosbltThaW t
    tu
    Thaw walked 3lked into the detective bureaat bureau bureauat u
    I at police headquarters head uarters today a f few fowmlnutos fewminutes ow owminutes
    minutes after her husband HarryThaw Harry K KThaw KTh8w
    Thaw had boon taken from there t tJefferson to toJefferson toJe1erson o
    Jefferson Market court where where he was wasarraigned WaSarrnlgned wa waarraigned s
    arraigned charged with the murder Of OfStanford CCStanCord 0 0Stanford f
    Stanford WhiteMrs White WhiteMrs WhiteMrs
    Mrs Thaw was alone and evidently evidentlywalked cldQntlwalked evidentlywalked
    walked to headquarters from where she sheloft sheloft sh shloft e
    loft a 3 street car She was dressed al alIn all allIn allIn 1
    In black with a large lars black bhl k picture hat hatand hatand ha haand t
    and looked strikingly beautiful beautifulIs
    Is Harry Thaw here she asked a athe at atthe atthe t
    the desk deskNo deskuKo deskNo
    uKo No he has gone to Jefferson Market Marketcourt Marketcourt Markelcourt
    court she was was told toldThank tolduThank toldThank
    Thank you I will go fin there sh shsaid she shesaid shesa1d e
    saidShe said saidShe sa1dShe
    She walked out of the building bttUdln and up u uMulberry
    Mulberry street to Bleeckor street streetsvhoro streethero streetwhere tp
    where hero she turned i left toward Broadway Broad Broaday
    way wayNo ay
    No move was mode to take Mrs Tha Thaw Thawi ThawConUnued w
    i Continued on Third Page Paget Pager
    t
    t r
    CROWDMillionaire CROWDMillionaire CROWDMillionaire
    Millionaire Slayer Claims alms Famous Architect ArchitectRuined ArchitectRuined ArchitectRuined
    Ruined His Wife Before His is Marriage to toHer toHerHeld toHerHeld
    Her HerHeld Held for or Murder IVlurderby by Coroner Coroner2vEW
    NEW EW YORK YOrC rome ba i Harry Kendall Th Thaw w tho young Pittsburg Pittsburgmillionaire Pittsburgn PittsburgntillIonaire
    ntillIonaire millionaire n tlIonaire and brother of the Countess of Yarmouth was arraigned in inJefferson inJefferson inJefferson
    Jefferson Market court Garbed with the sensational shooting andkilling and andkilling andkilling
    killing of Staiictford Stan Staud ford ord White the millionaire architect during a performance perform performance performance
    ance late last night in Madison M dison Square SquftreRoof Roof Garden for some real or orfancied orfancied orfancied
    fancied wrong that tbatVhite White had done Evelyn Ev n Nesbit the actress and andatrists andntrlsts andatrists
    atrists model whose whos marriage to young Thaw a year ago was a so society societ society
    ciety ciet sensation sensationThaw sensntionThaw sensationThaw
    Thaw was quite calm when arraigned this morning He was stilldressed still stilldressed s ll lldressed
    dressed in his evening clothes and was somewhat bedraggled from his hislong hislong hislong
    long night nightin in the police station cell cellCOMMITTED cellCOMMITTED cellCOMMITTED
    COMMITTED TO THE TOMBS TOMBSThavtfs TOMBSThaws
    Thaws Than s arraignment before Magistrate Barlow was over within ithin a aminute aminute aminute
    minute minute and he was remanded to the custody of the coroner Once more morethe morethe
    the prisoner was bundled into the patrol wagon after afte being handcuffed handcuffedand handcuffedand
    and taken to the criminal courts building where he was arraigned be before before
    fore Coroner Dooley There was a tremendous cspwcl c owd in the office of ofthe ofthe ofthe
    the coroner and Thaw seeing that several photographers were try trying trying
    ing to take his picture hid his face behind bind his hat On an affidavit affidavitsigned affidavitsigned
    signed by Patrolman Debs that Thaw said to him4 MID 441 I shot him he was washeld Wadheld
    held without wit out bail and committed to the Tombs TombsIt TombsIt
    It Ittas was arranged that the inquest will iIl be held before Coroner Dooley Dooleyon
    on Thursday morning at 930 oclock The district attorneys attorne s office wag wagrepresented wafSrepresented
    represented at the thecoroner7s coroners hearing hearing by b Assistant Ass 5tant District Attorneys AttorneysKnott AttorneysKnott AttorneysKnott
    Knott Knott and Turnbull Thaw would make no statement after being beingtakeji beingtak
    taken tak n to his cell in the Bombs but spent some limo going oer o er the theevents theeenq theevents
    events eenq of the he night with his counsel counselFriends course counseFnends
    Friends say sa today that he h ht has ha ion long brooded over the wrong wron said saidto saidto saidto
    to have been done to his wife by White and said aid that he has recently
    I</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1906-06-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Harry+Thaw+MURDERER+Stanford+White+DENIED+BAIL+millionaire+Florence+Evelyn+Nesbit+Thaw+insanity&amp;r=-0.892,-0.034,2.785,1.49,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MTJRDFR PR THAW DFNIFD RAIT HFI AJ
    JLvA XJ LA-IS J_iAYJLI/JL\- A Xax^-L v \u25bc JL/ J_l/Jl 1 JL\-j\~J JJjTjLAJLjv A AAI/A^A>/
    jL JL JL X' VJL k/ .XL/, i. 1 I JJL V JL X \u25a0-- 1 A XX J— A V-/ 1» JL JL/ ky
    NEW YORK, June 26.— Frankly ..'admitting that he killed Stanford White, the famous architect, and pleading in justification of the deed
    that White -had ruined the life of his wife, the beautiful former chorus gifl and artist's model, Florence Evelyn Nesbit, Harry Kendall Thaw of
    Pittsburgh brother of the Gountess of Yarmouth, occupies a cell in the Tombs, awaiting the action of the Grand Jury on a charge of murder. His
    MILLIONAIRE
    SHACKLED TO
    A DETECTIVE
    Slayer of Stanford
    White Is Shown
    No Favoritism.
    Held to Grand Jury
    After Brief Ex
    amination.
    Alienists Pass Upon
    the Sanity of
    Prisoner.
    NEW YORK, June 26.
    Harry Kendall Thaw was
    examinee) by eminent alien
    ists, retained on his behalf and
    by the District Attorney's of
    fice. The Coroner's inquest
    will be held on Thursday and
    in all probability the case will
    then be considered by .the
    Grand Jury. The "prisoner's
    wife will be required to ap
    pear before that body, she
    having been served with a
    subpena today while in con
    sultation, at the offices of her
    husband's counsel. Every ef
    fort is now being made by
    both sides to expedite the
    legal preliminaries so that the
    arraignment and trial may
    take place at the earliest. pos
    sible date.
    Not since, the killing of
    James Fisk Jr. by Edward
    Stokes on the staircase of the
    Grand Central Hotel more
    than thirty years ago has the
    metropolis been shocked by
    so startling and dramatic a
    tragedy as that which was
    enacted last night in the view
    of an audience of more than
    1000 persons in the roof
    theater of Madison Square
    Garden. Not the least dram
    atic feature of the tragedy is
    the' fact that White met His
    death in the structure which,
    perhaps, is the most con
    spicuous memorial of his archi
    tectural genius.
    IN PATROL WAGON.
    Rarely has the case against
    any prisoner moved with
    more rapidity than did the
    proceedings today!: which
    ended in Thaw's formal com
    mitment to the Tombs. Save
    in this unusual and almost
    frenzied haste, the routine
    followed and the treatment
    accorded \to Thaw differed jiri
    no respect from that meted
    out to any prisoner y charged
    Continued \u25a0 on Paire 2, Column 1 1
    SAN FRANCISCO, WEDNESDAY, JUNE 27, 1906.
    LIFE STORY OF MAN
    WHO DIED AT HANDS
    OF HARRY K. THAW
    STANFORD WHITE—
    Born in New York, November
    9, 1853; son of Richard
    Grant White, "distinguished
    author.
    Murdered June 25, 1906, by
    Harry Kendall Thaw, mcm=
    ber of a millionaire Pitts*
    burg family and husband
    of Evelyn Nesbit, the act
    ress. x f.
    Millionaire architect.
    Graduate of the University of
    New York.
    Received architectural train
    ing with Charles D. Gam
    brill arid 51. 11. Richardson.
    Was Richardson's chief as
    sistant in the construction
    of Trinity Church in Boston.
    Traveled and studied in Eu
    rope, 1 878-1 880. Since 1881
    a member of the firm of
    McKim, Mead White of
    New York.
    Dssigned the pedestal of the
    Lincoln monument in On
    |i^oJn-Parki;Chicagp.:..
    Designed X the
    I prindpal:; statues byj Au«
    gustus St. Gaudens.
    Designed the house now own
    ed and occupied by White
    law Reid in New York; also
    Madison^ Square Garden,
    the Century and 'Metropolis
    tan clubs, the University of
    New York, the Washington
    Arch^and the University of
    Virginia/
    A fellow of the American In
    stitute of Architects, a mem
    ber of the Knickerbocker,
    Union, University, Players;
    Lambs,; Xjolf and other
    dubs.
    Resided in Grammercy Park,
    New York; had a summer
    residence at St. James, L. I.
    Married >\u25a0 Miss Bessie Smith,
    who survives him, with a
    son, Lawrence.
    LEDERER SAYS
    HARRY THAW IS
    A DEGENERATE
    Theatrical Man De fends
    \u25a0the Name of Stan
    \u25a0 r j TTTI V
    ford White.
    Relations of Architect
    With; Actress Always
    Proper.
    SPECIAIj DISPATCH TO.; THE CALL.
    CHICAGO, June 2Lederer, manager of the. Colonial
    Theater and one,, of the best known
    theatrical men >in the country, 1 who
    was Intimately' acquainted 'with^ Har
    ry Kendall {Thaw, his? wife and Stamf
    ord White, tonight gave; outran \hin
    terview In which he declared that the
    slayer of White was a moral degen
    ereta, a morphine and cigarette fieiid^
    and, owing to his mental condition/
    not respbrisible f o r his act ions.
    Lederer was the man who^'discov
    ered the pretty "young) artist's mod
    el and placed her in theVcast 'tof ,y the
    44 Florodora' company V which was
    then playing In New York. Lederer
    Continued on Vase 2, Column 3.
    MISS NESBIT
    LEADS A GAY
    STAGE LIFE
    Name Connected
    \u25a0' Long Ago With
    \u25a0\u0084.- White's.
    Uncharitable Views
    Expressed by
    \u25a0 Rivals.
    Friendly With Ar
    chitect While in
    Her 'Teens.
    SPECIAL DISPATCH TO THE CALL.
    \u2666NEW YORK, June 26-Ru
    mor, to put it mildly, had been
    busy with the acquaintanceship
    of. Florence Evelyn Nesbit, ac
    tress /and artists' model, with
    Stanford White years before
    Harry Thaw came to her ac
    quaintance. She is not old now.
    I She was considerably younger
    I 1I 1 then; In fact, she had hot got
    111 1 very far along in the early 'teens I
    I fcwfaen her name wasy f irst"*cb;n> j
    hected- in Rialto gossip with that j
    of the proverbially generous and
    generally popular architect.
    Just how old Florence Nesbit i
    j was when she went dn, the stage;
    !is a thing perhaps definitely
    known only to herself and par
    ents.;; She made her first ap
    pearance Hn the original "FJoro
    clora" company at the Casino be
    tween five and six years ago.
    HER FIRST "TURN."
    "Appearance" is perhaps a
    rather misleading word to apply
    to her first "turn" behind the
    footlights, as she was simply one
    of the six Spanish girls that fig
    ured in a minor, way in the pro
    duction.
    John C. Fisher, manager of
    the company, gave her her first
    engagement. Beyond that, he
    does not know much about her
    career on or off the stage while
    she was in his company.
    In "Florodora" Evelyn Nesbit,
    it has been said, did not stand
    out. When she met George
    Lederer, though, it was another
    story. One woman who knows
    the profession as well as the
    next gave a hint of this. She
    \u25a0 said: ;'r. \u25a0
    "Now, whenever we hear of
    anything of that sort we tear up
    their; cards— they are off our
    Books. We have to do this out
    of deference to the decent girls
    of tHe chorus. For ten to one of
    them, are decent, and the 'one
    that goes wrong is the only one
    that is heard of.
    "But it was when Miss Nesbit
    was with; Lederer in the 'Wild
    Rose,' the /production that Irene
    Bentley-J starred Jn—l think \u0084• she
    was Miss Bentley's understudy--^
    it was ithen x ;we began to hear
    Mr. White's name mentioned in
    connection with Hers. .You know
    how it was.V The Casino jiid not
    have the best reputation with all
    those v girls /there. .Then you
    know Misi] Nesbit": had never had
    moneys and I some; one coming
    around with automobiles and
    suppers and all that^ is enough
    to turn many^a girl's head." 1-
    LEADS BU^EI^LY^ LIFE.
    \u25a0 "From this time on, if the Rialto recol
    lection and \u25a0 the Rialto habit of putting
    Continued on Pase •2. Column 2.
    The Call prints more
    news than any other
    paper published in San
    Francisco.
    MRS. HARRY KENDALL THAW. FORMERLY FLORENCE EVELTN NESBIT. THE. BEAU
    TIFUL CHORUS GIRL .WHOSE FRIENDSHIP FOR STANFORD WHITE. THE FAMOUS
    ARCHITECT, COST THE LATTER. HIS. LIFE. \u0084 v</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058130/1906-06-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=INSANITY+Harry+Thaw+Florence+Evelyn+Stanford+White+William+Jerome+murder+Assistant+District+Attorney+Nott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>INSANITY Will RE THE THlPlA THEPLEA
          PLEA OF OFHARRY H RRY K THAW THAWSlayer THAWSlayer
          Slayer of Stanford Sta ford White Ex Exby Examined Examined
          amined by Alienists in theTombs the theTragedy theTombs
          Tombs Prison PrisonTragedy PrisonTragedy
          Tragedy Creates Creat s Greatest Sensation S nsation intham inGtham in iniQoitham
          iQoitham tham Since the Killing of ofJimFisk ofJim ofJim
          Jim JimFisk Fisk
          New York June 36 3IFnu1kly Frankly admitting admittinghat
          hat he killed ki led Stanford White the fa famous famous Ianous
          mous architect and pleading in justifica justification justltJ03110n just11cation
          tion of o the deed that White hd ruined ruinedthe ruinedthe ruinedthe
          the life of his wife the beautiful former formerhorus formerhorus formerhorns
          horus girl and artists model Florence FlorenceKvelyn FJerenceEvehl1 FlorenceEvelyn
          Evelyn Nesblt Harry Kendall Thaw of ofPittsburg ofPittsburg ofPittsburg
          Pittsburg brother of the Countess of ofYarmouth ofYarmouth ofYarmouth
          Yarmouth occupies a cell In the Tombs Tombsawaiting Tombswafting Tombswaiting
          awaiting the action of the grand jury on onP onp
          P 1 charge of murder His counsel will of offer offer ofthe
          fer the defense of insanity and today todaythe tode tode1h today1hc
          the 1h prisoner prisoner was examined by eminent eminentAlienists eminents eminentUenists
          Alienists s Uenists retained on His behalf and by bythf by111P bythe
          the district attorneys office officeInquest offloeInquest officeInquest
          Inquest Thursday ThursdayThe
          The Th coroners inquest will be heM he3 on onThursday ORThursda o oThursday
          Thursday Thursda and in all probability the case casewill Ciisewl1l ae aeciil
          will then be considered by b the grand grandjiry grandwIlen grandiry
          jiry when the prisoners wife will be re required reQulred required
          quired to appear before that body she shehaving shealng sheh
          having h been served serv with a subpoena to today todty toclny
          day while In consultation at the offlces offlcesof offcesf
          of If f her husbands counsel Every E eiy effort effortIs fortnow
          Is l now being made by b both sides to ex expedite expedite exiodtte
          pedite the legal preliminaries so that the thearraignment thearraignment thetrraignment
          arraignment and trial may m y take place at atthp atthp atthc
          thp earliest possible date dateNot dateot dateNot
          Not ot since sinceUie tile kilting of James Jam FIsk Jr Jrby jrIn Jrby
          by Edward Stokes on the t e staircase of the theGrand theGrand theGrand
          Grand Central hotel more than thirty thirtyrars thtrtytars th4rtyam
          tars am ago has the metropolis been beenshocked beeRR beenscked
          shocked R ocked by so startling and dramatic a atragedy aragedy aagedy
          tragedy as that which was enacted last lastr
          r r ght in the view of an audience of more moreman morean
          man 1 an 1000 persons In the roof theatre of ofMadison of1ladison ofMadison
          Madison Square Garden G rden Not the least leastdramatic JQRstdraJIlatic leastdramatic
          dramatic feature ot the tragedy is the thefact tIlefact thetart
          fact that Mr White met t his death do th in the thestructure thestructure thestructure
          structure wltf wh4c rcMch 1 is igpeJlh petiiaps ps the most con conspicuous conpicuous conpiuous
          spicuous memorial m n rJal of his architectural architecturalgenius architecturalgf architecturalgenIus
          genius gf nfus
          Events vent Moved Rapidly RapidlyRarely R ipidIyTd Pidly PidlyRarel
          Rarely Rarel Td rely ha 1wfiM in dtes se agjftlgt WML J Pgpn Pgpnr Ui Jl Jlnton
          4 r moved nton mo ed d with more re raarSsty then 41Id d the thej theJroceeding theroc1Seding
          j roweding to4ay which W ended in Thaws Thawsformal Thawsforma Thawsf
          formal f rmal coramitxftent com to tile Tombs Save Saven S Skyethis ve
          n 1 this unusual atMIImo aftd 1 aljo Insoet t frenated haste hastefVr bastethr
          fVr 1 r routiiH ffeHowed a4 the treatment treatmentr treatmentcordt treatmeotordd
          r corded cordt d to Thaw differed in no respect respectcm
          V cm m that meted out to any prisoner prisonernarged prisonerilarged prisonerirged
          narged with a capital offense offenseHoused offenseRoused offenseThused
          Housed early this morning from his cell cellin celli cellthe
          in i the West Thirtieth street station stationJuse stationJS
          Juse I JS Thaw attired in n fresh clothing clothingbrought c1otblnglQught clothingiought
          brought to him by his valet was wasshackled W85shackled wassdkled
          shackled inspite In Ii spite plte5of of his Jrote protestations ltaUons to toa toa toa
          a detective and taken in the patrol wagon wagonto
          to police headquarters Thereafter Thereafterawaiting1 Thereaftera Thereafterawaiting
          awaiting a ait1nJhls his turn in the long ong line of petty pettyi
          i S nmmals arrested during the night he hewas hewa hewas
          was wa photographed and his measurements measurementstaken measurementsI
          taken 1 ken on the Bertillon system Again in inihp inthp inlip
          ihp lip patrol wagon he was taken to the thecriminal thecriminal thecriminal
          criminal court building where a great greatmultitude greatmultitude greatmultitude
          multitude gathered to catch amassing amassingglimpse 8 AYasslng AYasslngslimpsfI jassingglimpse
          glimpse of him and was arraignecrin the thepolice theIH1i thep1iee
          police IH1i f court There the proceedings were wereof wereIf
          of If r the briefest and after the bare for formality formality I Iroa1it
          mality roa1it of arraignment had been under undergone underbon undergone
          gone bon Thaw was remanded to the custody custodrf custodyof I IIf
          of If f the coroner and on his order commit committ oommft1d
          t 1d d to the Tombs to await the result of ofhis of11is ofh1S
          his trial trialThaw trialThaw trialThaw
          Thaw Retained Composure ComposureThroughout Composure1hrougltout ComposureThroughout
          Throughout the proceedings Thaw Thawshowed Thawshowed Thawshowed
          showed little evidence of o agitation except exceptwhen excepthEn exceptwhen
          when hEn the detective approached him in the thestatfon thestatfon thestation
          statfon to affix the handcuffs to his wrist wristThrn wristThfn wristThcn
          Thrn he protested But on being beIngassured beIngassuredthat assured assuredfiat red redt1at
          fiat this was the invariable practice he hesubmitted hesubmitted hesubmtted
          submitted without further rther words While Whileleaving WhileIfavIng WhileiavIn
          leaving iavIn the station sta and even in the t e court courtTt courtroom courtmom
          room b h as compelled to run the gaunt gauntT
          Tt T r t of batteries of 0 cameras from which whichh whichhr
          h hr shielded bitJde himself Aim elf as well as he could couldT could1n
          T 1n w rovering his face with his unshackled unshackledlinml unshackled11nd unshackledI
          linml linmlThaw 11ndThaw I n d dThaw
          Thaw was registered at the Tombs as asHarry asHarn asHarry
          Harry Thaw born in the United States Statesyears StatesyeaLS Statesyears
          years old student and was assigned assignedt
          t coil 230 G cw the th second tier tie Shortly af after afpr afhis
          ter pr his arrival he was visited in his cell cellhv cenJ
          hv J h Dr Aurtin Flint FJI t Dr Carlos F Mac MacDonald MacJnald MacPnald
          Donald and Dr Mabon on behalf it was wast WSsaid
          t said aid of the district attorneys office and andiv and7i
          iv 7i y v Dr Maguire the Tombs physician physicianwho physicianWh
          Wh who was required to make an examination examinationof
          of the prisoners mental condition byrounsel byrounsel by bycounsel
          rounsel for the defense Drs MacDon MacDonrld
          rld ld and Flint later declined to say any anything anything anything
          thing but Dr Maguire said that he be befiered befIed beeyed
          eyed he discovered symptoms of emo emotional emotional omolIonel
          tional insanity and possible indications of ofSnipient ofniIl ofnipIent
          Snipient niIl nt paresis pare js The alienists will make makea
          a further examination of the prisoner to toirrrow tonrro torrrflw
          irrrow rrrflw Dr Maguire a tre meantime keeping keepingv keepingunder
          v 1 under observation observationPhysical obsenaUonPhysical observationPhysical
          Physical Condition Perfect PerfectMr
          Mr Ir Maguire said that Thaws physical physicalCondition physical1Jlldition physicaljiidition
          Condition was 9JiS almost perfect and his ap apjiftite apftite aprtite
          jiftite excellent excel nt Louis Delafield who took tookcharge tookrhargE tookcharge
          charge of Thaws interests immediately immediatelyifter Immediatelyftlr
          ifter ftlr his arrest announced that the firm firmi firmlor firmur
          i lor Black Olcott Bonynge of which for former former former
          mer Governor Frank S Black is the senior seniorpartner seniorpartner seniorpartner
          partner had been retained to conduct the thedefense th thdffense thedefense
          defense Later Mr Delafield and Mr Ol Oliott OII
          iott I ltt had an interview with the prisoner prisonerin
          in the th consulting1 room in the prison after afterwhich afterhieh afterhich
          which hieh Mr r Delafield declined to say any anytiiing anytling anyI
          tiiing I i n g about the case except ex ept to say that it itnas ItWa ItWI
          Wa nas now entirely m In the hands of Mr Mrlack lrM
          M 1 lack wk L 1c and Mr Olcott Mr Olcott de delined deIjiled dond
          Ijiled lined nd to make any statement statementfc statementAppearance statementAppearance
          fc Appearance of Mrs Thaw Thawfe Thawwhereabo Thawwhereabouts
          fe whereabouts ts of Mrs Thaw Th who whosafe whod whosared
          d safe sared ared red from Madison Jradi on Square Garden Gardenn
          m n 1 the th confusion that followed the trag tragedy tra traId tragremained
          edy Id remained rm 1ned a a mystery until this after afternoon aftert1fl
          noon t1fl m when accompanied by a1 a friend Miss MissMay MissMav MissMay
          May McKinsey she arrived at the offices officesof officesDeIafleld
          of I S Delafield Longfellow on Wall street streetwhere streetwhere streetiere
          where iere she remalrfed in consultation with withlier withllPr withr
          lier r counsel for fo several hours hoursWhile hoursWhile hoursWhile
          While there she be was served en ed with wlt a sub subruena ub ubT
          ruena T T lena na requTf9igher re4Ult r attendance ttGnd nce before b Core the thegand thednd themd
          gand dnd jury on Thursday Mrs rs Thaw wasr was MiShd
          1 Mnd r hd in l plain brown bro wn automobile costume costumei21 costume1SI
          1SI i21 1 i appeared ill and nervous and plainly plainlyTiage plainlyardly
          31 ¼ ardly strong enough to walk from t the theTriage e eTiage
          Triage Tiage to the door At the lawyers of ofV orr otk5
          k5 k5Mrs V f Mrs Thaw was joined by Mr and and5rs andr4 antirs
          5rs r4 rs George Carnegie said to be relatives relativesof
          of her husband husbandMrs husbandllrs husbandMrs
          Mrs Thaw was not seen to leave the thebuilding theb thebuilding
          building b ildingWhleh which was closely watched by bylearned byleporters bynrters
          leporters nrters and late in the afternoon It was was1earned W2ciried
          learned that she and Miss 1t ss McKlasey t lnsey had hadft bad1n hadI
          1n I ft the lawyers s of OffiCe fie on the e thirteenth thirteenthfloor t thirteenthr irteenth irteenthflttt
          floor r crossed the therooCs roofs ofjtwo ot tWO wO adjacent adjacentfuHdings adjacent1uUdins adjacentlitldifl5
          fuHdings 1uUdins and andenter entered a 1 wBKtow of the theCt theCity thetv
          Ct City tv National bank building bu ldiDg in front of ofwhich othlh
          which 1 hlh a carriage ca ge was waiting for them themWill themWill themWill
          Will RJmain main Close at Hand HandMr HandS
          S Mr r Delaflaltl Del Delaf fJ Id d declined to make any anystatement any8uttement mytatement
          statement on t1 JJefta Ju J alr of ofcept Mrs Tbaw ex except oxcept
          cept to say s y that she would not be spir
          f
          ited away and would respond to any sum summons sumI summons suminons I
          mons of the authorities authoritiesAssistant authoritiesAssistant authoritiesAssistant
          Assistant District Attorney Attomc Nott who whohas whohas whohas
          has charge of the prosecution said all allthe allthe allthe
          the witnesses would be examined by b him himbut bimbut himbut
          but that Mrs Thaws appearance at the tinsinquest theinquest theinquest
          inquest would not be required It was wasunderstood wasunderstood as asunderstood
          understood that this action was decided decidedon
          on because Mrs Thaw could stand on her herright herright herright
          right as a wife and refuse to testify testifyagainst testifyagainst testifyagainst
          against her husband She will be required requirodto
          to appear appearbefore before the grand jury however howeverMaking boweverMaking howeverMaking
          Making an Investigation InvestigationThe
          The district attorneys office is busily busilyengaged busilyengaged j jengaged
          engaged in looking up Thaws ante antecedents antecedents antecedents
          cedents his mode of living I 1 ng reported dis dissipations dissipations
          sipations and indulgences with a view to toanalyzing toaaalyzing toanalyzing
          analyzing their bearing on his mental mentalcondition mentaladltion mentalcnditlon i
          condition adltion On this subject Mr Ir Nott said saidHe saidHe saidHe
          He Is not insane now nor was he in insaae insaDe insane
          saDe at the time he shot White WhiteAsked WhiteAsked WhiteAsked
          Asked concerning the probable date of ofthe ofthe ofthe
          the trial Assistant District Attorney Nott Notts ott ottsaid
          s said id
          idI
          I know of no reason why wh Thaw should shouldbe shouldbe shouldbe
          be tr treated ted any differently dlfferentl than an ordi ordinary ordinary ordinary
          nary accused ufred murderer He will have haveto haveto haveto
          to wait his turn to be tried in all proba probability probabilit probability
          bility bilit However Mr 3erome will be back backin backin backin
          in town on Monday Iond y next and will decide decidethat deci decidethat e etbat
          that
          Grief Gri f of the Widow WidowUp WidowI
          I Up p to tonight the district attorneys of office office offlee
          fice has received no communication from frommembers frommembCl frommembers
          members of Mr Whites hites family famil Mrs MrsWhite MrsWhite MrsWhite
          White came in this thi morning from her hersummer hersummer hersummer
          summer home at St James Long Isl Island Island 1stand
          and accompanied aceomp nied by her sister Mrs MrsPrescott MrsPrescott errsPrescott
          Prescott H Butler and went to the town townhouse t tOwnhouse v1l v1lMuse
          house in Gramercy Park where she now nowIs DeWis newis
          Is with her son Lawrence who came camedown camedown camedown
          down from Harvard university yesterday yesterdayand
          and parted with his father only onl an hour houror houror houror
          or so before the tragedy tra y Mrs White is isr IsreHrted IsJeprtsd
          pfrted r to be completely prostrated by byshook byshook byshook
          shook and grief rief riefML eL eLJIr i iMe
          Me White s body was removed to the thehouse thehouse Uhehouse
          house thfe th tterweon tterweonThe tterueenThe fter t on onThe
          The autopsy held today showed thai thaithree tIt8fthree tltathree
          three bullets bad taken effeet one in inthe intbe inthe
          the corner rftt rflerof of the left eye e e which w1c pene penetrated peneLrated penstrated
          trated the brain and was Instantly ffc ffctai ittal 1 1tal
          tal and one in the upper lip knocking knockingout
          out several teeth and striking the left leftshoulder leftshoulder
          shoulder shoulderFuneral sbouk1erFuReral shoulderFuneral I
          Funeral services serri s will be held at St Bar Barthotemews Bartho1 Bartholomews
          thotemews tho1 mews church with Coadjutor Bish Bishop Blsbp Bishep
          op p Green officiating officiatingThaws officiatingThawtsAppctite officiatingThaws
          Thaws ThawtsAppctite Appetite Good GoodThaws GoodThaws GoodThaws
          Thaws bearing in the Tombs was a asource asource asource
          source of much wonder to the wardens wardenswho wardenswho wardenswho
          who hid him in charge While lle he ap appeared appearoo appeared
          peared to be in a sort of a daze and un unable unable unahie
          able to comprehend his position his ap appetite appEltite appetite
          petite was unimpaired for he disposed disposedof dlspo ed edof
          of three substantial sub taltial meals during the aft afternoon a alternoon t ternoon
          ernoon and having dined at 6 oclock oclockwith oclockwith oclockwith
          with every appearance of enjoyment he heremarked heTe herernake
          Te remarked Jitked that he expected cted to spend a acomfortable acomfertable acomfortable
          comfortable night nig nightDID t tDID j jDID
          DID NOT KNOW WHITE WHITEMother WHITEMother WHITEMother
          Mother of Mrs Harry K Thaw Ap Apprised Apprised Apprised
          prised of the Tragedy TragedyPittaburg TragedyPlttsburg TragedyPittsburg
          Pittaburg June 26 6Mrs Mrs Charles J JHolman JHolman THolman
          Holman mother of Mrs Harry Kendall KendallThaw KendallThaw KendallThaw
          Thaw who lives Uvesat t Broojkline a suburb suburbof
          of this citY was apprised today toda of the theshooting thehooting theshooting
          shooting of Stanford White ite by Mr Thaw ThawShe TbawShe ThawShe
          She said she did not know Stanford StanfordWhite StanfordWhite StanfordWhite
          White the dead architect had in fact factnever factnever factnever
          never heard of him himWilliam WmWiltlam himWilliam
          William Thaw jr a a brother of Harry Harrycame Harrycame Harrycame
          came from his home in Sewickley this tbJsmorning tbismorning thismorning
          morning and left Jeftat at 10 oclock for New NewYork NewYork NewYork
          York YorkAt YorkAt YorkAt
          At the home of Mrs frs William Thaw Thawmother Thawmoth6l Thawmother
          mother of Harry who sailed from New NewYork NewYork NewYork
          York last Saturday to spend the summer summerwith summerwith summerwith
          with her daughter Alice the Countess of ofYarmouth ofYrmOu ofYarmouth
          Yarmouth it was said that she would be bereached bereacbed bereached
          reached as quickly as possible and noti notified notified not notlied
          fied of f the unfortunate affair It wasUkely waslikely was waslikely
          likely It was said that she would take takethe takethe takethe
          the first vessel for home homeMother homeMother homeMother
          Mother Far From Well WellMrs WellMrs WellMrs
          Mrs Thaw was not in the best of health healthwhen healthwhen healthwhen
          when she left the city and it is expected expectedthe expectedthe xpectedthe
          the news will have a serious effect on onher onber onher
          her condition conditionUp conditionUx conditionTJil
          Up until a comparatively short time ago agobut ag agbut agObut
          but little had been seen of Harry Kendall KendallThaw KendallThaw KendallThaw
          Thaw In Plttsburg for fo a number of yars yarsShortly Jar5Shortly yarsShortly
          Shortly aftr his fathers death he went wentabroad wentabroad wentabroad
          abroad and there made his residence r liv living living flytug
          ing most of the time in Paris After his hisreturn hisreturn hisreturn
          return from Europe and his marriage he hepurchased bepurchased hepurchased
          purchased a fln fine piece of property in inFifth inFifth InFifth
          Fifth avenue and it was said that it was washis washis washis
          his intention to put p t up a handsome home homeOne homeOne homeOne
          One of the th reports current here today todaywas todaywas todaywas
          was that Thaw had had some talk with withthe withthe withthe
          the man killed relative to some of the thearchitectural tbearcbltectural thearchitectural
          architectural features of the house houseTHAW bouseTHAW houseTHAW
          THAW RESIDENCE ROBBED ROBBEDMurder ROBBEDMurder ROBBEDMurder
          Murder Brings to Light an Occur Occurrence Occurrence Occurrence
          rence Suppressed by Police PolicePittsburg PolicePtttsburg PolicePittsburg
          Pittsburg June 2S 2WhhIe fi While ile seeking in information information information
          formation of the Thaw family it was waslearned waslearned waslearned
          learned tonight that the home of Mrs AirsWilliam MrsVllllam MrsWilliam
          William Thaw mother motberof of Harry Thaw Thawwho Thawwho Thawwho
          who is charged withthe with witthgjnurdQr h xaurder of Stan Stanford Stanford Stanford
          ford White WhlteJn In Newrork Newi New TYork fKlast last nfght was wasrobbed wasrobbed wasrobbed
          robbed of o jewels and silver s ver plate within withinthe witblnthe withinthe
          the past few weeks the value of which is issaid Issaid issaid
          said to amount to S 65WO tOO The matter matterwas matterwas matterwas
          was reported to the police but because becauseof
          of the prominence of the family the inci incident Incident mcdent
          dent was suppressed All the cities of the thecountry thecount thecountry
          country count have been notified of the rob robbery robbery robbery
          bery and a description of the jewels has hasbeen hasbeen hasbeen
          been sent to the various police depart departments departments departmeats
          ments mentsDisclosures mentsDisclosures meatsDisclosures
          Disclosures of Ute robebry were made madethrough madethrough madethrough
          through a leak unconsciously dropped droppedby
          by y on veiy v lY close to the family The Theexact Tbeeoract Theexact
          exact time of the robbery is not known knownbet knownbut knownbet
          bet it occurred while the Thaw family familywa familywatt
          wa watt in the city cIt and nd although the police policeand pOliceand policeand
          and detective forces of the city were im immediately immediately immediately
          mediately notified the matter has been beenkept beenkept beenkept
          kept under cover until the present time timeThe timeThe timeThe
          The jewels are sa4d to be some of rare rarevalue rarevalue rarevalue
          value gathered gath red by b Mrs Irs William Thaw in inh Inher inher
          h her r travelings ann Include IiCIUder Stfinga tln of ofpearls orpearls Ofpearls
          pearls diamonds of rare value va ue and per perfe perfett perfedI
          fe fett t color and silver plate that was con convenient convenient eonySnient
          venient for the Obbers to take away awayHeavier awa awaH awayHeavier
          Heavier H Rer pieces or plate of cumbersome cumbersomebalk cumbersomebalk cumbersomebeik
          balk were left behind behindThe behiudThe behindThe
          The PittsburgPost Plttsburg Pest tomorrow will say sayof sayof
          of 0 the robbery robberQpntiJ1le99n robberyQpntIepfiea</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1906-06-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=EXPERTS+SAY+THAW+SANE+Stanford+White+Eveyln+Nesbit+Harry+Thaw+Assistant+District+Attorney+Nott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>EXPER11S AGAIN SAS
          H THAT THAW IS SANE
          1 Former Actress Visits the Millionaire
          Slayer in Prison and Sobs as
          She Throws Herself
          Y
          Into His Arms
          HE REPULSES EXPERTS
          SHOUTING IM NOT CRAZY
          Effort to Besmirch Deputation of Dead Man
          Has Led to the I Charge that a Clergymans
          n
          Son Brought Evelyn Nesbit to New
          7 7
          YorK Before White Knew Her
          In llc ipinion if th three alienists retained by the State Harry Thaw
          is a taie ian I
          TI three exjcrt1 Mbrn Flint and McDonald trade Ws report In
          n DisintV n n Nrtt after their ecrrd inspection of Stanford
          SnL j aver cinfirrmiK ihe opiiicn exporeJ after their first visit i
          Th lIgh the psorc I cornnc s they had ieen unable tn examine I
          I m rry iy Cr to nrpi Y Ihe orinary tests for detecting inanity They i
          lacd ir relief nlth npn hU manner his appearance and his i
          tlaher i
          her the first time since he killed Stanford White Harry Thaw and
          ls slime Evelyn ehit Thaw met this ntternonn in the Tomb prison I
          They rrr into each others arms she weeping and moaninc he show
          crn cr fe with DISC For half an hour they were toother on the 1
          tri lacony of Vuulerer Row I
          TI re tree Ol twr wttnesua 10 the mpfllnp of the milHontim rom
          r crard I P AVT i on wsa aroimt IIP leak Whites life They were
          l
          r iiixis rr r frs N sir a the wtu den ol Lbp pI op
          TIt n in of Imo or pli r tfhuwrcl en the heels of n ttormy scene across
          til1 lrt rf letr r tr C iminl Court Building when Thaw over tio
          jrjfM of hio i rri tot I flu ti to subm In irothp rtiTuinntlnp by
          rl Q Izts
          bulled ill Viisptr
          Xr 7iw s vvv h r hucl thirty mJtas ThVy tJlkd IOEcthr
          In vvhlsprs flu t Varrp Flrr amdlng n dozen feet awn could not
          lC titiij I en Paiji firs Flat Column</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85052114/1906-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=NOT+GUILTY+PLEA+Harry+Thaw+Stanford+White+Evelyn+Nesbit+Nott&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.1,-0.027,0.479,0.513,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NOT GUILTY PLEA I
          IENTERED BY THAW
          Counsel 1crniitteil to Change
          Uy Tuesday
          Wife Is Treated With Coiixlilrrullou
          lljr Htatoii Attorney Before
          Jnuul jury
          j jliiolUl S OK oiiiKDERUD MAN
          I
          4
          Now York Junq DlIarry K 1
          Thaw pleaded not guilty to tho mur
          1 der ot Stantord White today Hit
          counsel former JudgiS Olcott made a
          formal request of Judge Cowing be
          fore whom Thaw was arraigned to
          withdraw the pica by next Tuesday
          f J Inc rder that Puny motion might bo
          f rInado or other plea entered Tho re
          quest wag granted and tho prisoner
          I Iremanded I back to the Tombs
          Subject Too 1llItlllI
          0 New York Jun 21lrl Thaws
          J testimony before the grand Jury was
          ar follow
          followAra
          Are you the wife ot Harry K
          Thaw accused ot tho murder ot
          Stanford White asked Assistant
          District Attorney Garvnn
          9 nm replied lira Thaw
          Were you present Hi tho time of
          tho shooting of White went ou
          r Mr Oarvnu i
          That Is too painful a question for
          I mo to answer raid Mn Thaw
          t4 o Did you know anything of tho
          trouble between your husbanj and
          1 While
          I
          That Is too painful a subject for
          t me In discuss ngaln replied Mrs
          Thaw
          Did yon know Mr White previ
          ous to tho shooting
          That is too dreadful a question
          a i for mo to discuss was all Mrs
          p 4I Thaw would ay
          LL Turning to tho jurors Mr Garvnn
          rtdm said I
          1 think wo arc all agreed on that
          subject thyn addressing Mrs Thaw
          ij tha assistant district Attorney saMi
          You may go
          4 Tho most Important testimony at
          the Inquest was given by Lionel Law
          Jrenco stago director at the Madison
          Square Hoof Garden Theater Law
          a renco said that immediately after tho
          ehootlng Mrs Thaw rushcj up to her
          I
          husband and throwing her arms
          around his neck said
          f Never mind Harry I will stick
          to you thick or thin
          Thaw turned to tho crowd which
          f
          a surrounded thorA and said
          That ruined my wife and I
          4got him and 1 fixed him for It
          What was the nppoaranco of
          Thaw
          Thawio I was very white and his eyes
          4 were staring out of his head
          Edward If Conway a foreman of
          laborers at Madison Square Garden
          i said that ho saw both White and
          Thaw the night of tho murder Ito
          f described Thaws movements Haying
          that Thaw had passed him twice go
          ing back and forth behind tho tAblr
          Lat i which Whlto sat Tho second
          tlhiq Thaw approached Whites table
          Itho saw Thaw extend his arm and tho
          three shots followed In quick succos
          l
          v clon
          ol Mora WlliutuMii
          The district attorneys office com
          pleted tho examination of the compe
          tent witnesses so far discovered yes
          1terda 1 and Immediately shifted Its
          t attention to the Investigation of tho
          1 relations exIsting between Evelyn
          Nesblt and Stanford White prior to
          t tho girls marriage and tho attitude
          Jasunied by Thaw after ho had made
          her his wife
          i lam Investigating every sty ro
          fi t Kllrlllilg the lIfo situ dlsshwltlonl ot
          i the parties to the tragedy Mr Nott
          sald There are many of them I got
          a now talq liver minute and so far
          J neither the police nor the force ot
          this office hall been able to lub tall
          tlalo one of them
          TTho report that White hindo an
          a Insulting remark about Mrs Thaw
          on tho night of thovshootlng which
          was overheard by hf r husband U
          groundless so tar as I have been able
          to learn
          I am perfectly satisfied that noth
          ing that happened Monday night had
          anything to do with tho shootlngThe I
          L deed was planned before then Thai
          r White talked about Mrs Thaw after
          her marriage Is heard on all side
          but I have been unable to run down
          a single specific instance In which
          her name was mentioned by him In
          r
          a derogatory manner I never know
          of a cast in which there were so ma
          I
          t fftfttjaned on Page Four</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1906-06-30/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=DOGGED+TOLD+BODYGUARD+Stanford+White+Harry+Thaw+Bergoff+Murdered&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.216,0.56,0.748,0.748,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>HOW WHITE WASI
          I DOGGED TOLD BY
          BODYGUARD

          Amazing Revelations of a Private De
          tective Employed by the Murdered
          Architect to Protect Him and
          Watch Shadowers
          WHITES ACTRESS FRIENDS
          FOLLOWED DAILY ALSO
          Architect Spent 6000 in About a Year to
          Learn Who Put Detectives on His Track
          and the Purpose of the Relent
          less Espionage
          Ii The following astouding story told from the diary of P L
          l B rboff a detective and bodyguard employed by Stanford White
          B is a revelation of the conditions that preceded the tragedy on the
          Madison Square Roof Garden last Monday night when Harry K
          S iThav shot and killed the architect
          I P It shows that White undoubtedly feared for his life that he
          I took minute precautions to guard against a surprise and that equally
          I ingenious plans were made to keep track of every movement of the
          luckless manalxiuttown
          i Mr BergotT has been subpoenaed to appear before the July
          I Grand Jury on MonJay
          I The diary is a surprising exposure of life among the highflying
          i Bohemian set in N v York and carries with it a moral all of its own
          J7y P I l1er off Manager of the Vigilant Detective
          llnrcnn mill Personal llodynnurd of tho
          late Stanford White I
          Thero Is a slilc 10 the story cf the ainssnation of Stanford Whlto
          nhlch has not been tOld nml I am going to toll It The blR rTcliltcyt was
          square with mo and I am not afraid to speak out the truth although UN
          attorneys and others have been strangely silent
          Between Feb H 1905 anil Juno 25 1000 Mr White paid mo over 0000
          which sum was disbursed durluir that period In the protection of his per
          eoa and tho shadowinc of a band of privatn detectives hired by Marry K
          Thaw the Plttsburj mllllonalie
          I further charge thM Mr White was followod by Thaws sleuths up
          to S oclock on the night of MB death and that it was a very easy matter
          for young Mr Thaw to know where Mr YVhlto Wilt Inst Monday night for
          his paid sleuths wrro on then still ou tho job and In an automobile four
          of them followed tho nrchltivl when he of bls olllce at No 11iO Fifth ave
          nue at the precise hour t have named
          ACTRESSES ALSO SHADOWED</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1906-07-01/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=WHITE%27S+VICTIMS+CONFESS+Stanford+White+Orgies+Harry+Thaw+Mrs&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.226,-0.379,1.012,1.012,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WHITE'S
          VICTIMS
          CONFESS
          Little Girls Attend
          the Midnight
          Disrobing Act Alwnys a
          Part of Evening's
          Program
          Ice Cold Twenty Dollar Gold Pieces
          Slipped Down Misses' Backs
          Just to "See Them
          Wriggle"
          Special to The Herald.
          NEW YORK. :une 30.— Every turn of
          backward track which detectives are
          following In order to clear up minute
          circumstances bearing 'upon the killing
          of Stanford White by Har/y K. Thaw
          brings to light some unthought of de
          velopment.
          Thaw's attorneys have emeployed de
          tectives to find a man supposed to be
          White's private secretary. This man
          was manager of White's orgies. He
          hired "studios" in whfCh' White enter
          tained, employed discreet waiters and
          saw that waiters were sent away from
          "studios" at a certain stage of the
          performance before the disrobing be
          gan.
          Among witnesses who have been ex
          amined at the district attorney's of
          fice are several little girls who are said
          to have attended White's entertain
          ments. The same gjr^s have told their
          Ptorles to Thaw's counsel.
          The Disrobing Act
          One of the incidents developed In the
          district attorney's office and corrob
          orated by, Attorney Olcott's inquiries
          gives an idea of things done at White's
          parties. One aged roue used to place
          ten and twenty dollar gold pieces In
          cracked ice in his glass and await an
          opportunity of slipping them down the
          bucks of girls who were guests, i
          "See 'em wriggle! See.'em wriggle!"
          he would ejaculate between spasms of
          laughter thnt almost threw him Into
          apoplexy. The girls' struggles and
          scjvnms sis the icy metal touched, their
          flesh was supposed to be almost as good
          fun as a sigh ti of the victims afforded
          the company when they proceeded to
          disrobe to find the money.
          Attorney Olcott said today: "Mrs.
          Thaw will be the principal witness In
          her husband's defense.- She will tell a
          thrilling story. I cannot give details,
          but her testimony will open the eyes of
          New Yorkers and people all over the
          world. Her story has astounded me."
          WIFE TO TELL LIFE'S HISTORY
          Mrs. Thaw Declares Revelations Will
          Open Eyes of New Yorkers
          By Associated Press.
          NEW YORK, June 30.— "Mrs. Thaw
          will be the principal witness in her
          husband's defense. She will tell a
          thrilling and startling 1 story. I cannot
          make the details public now, but her
          testimony will open the eyes of New
          Yorkers and people all over the world."
          This statement was made today by
          Former Judge Olcott of counsel for
          Harry K. Thaw.
          Some interesting sidelights j were
          thrown on the Thaw-White tragedy by
          a private detective, who declared that
          he was employed by White as a body
          guard for more than a year before the
          shooting.
          In extracts from his diary the de
          tective says that White undoubtedly
          feared for his life; that he took minute
          precautions to guard against a sur
          prise; that equally Ingenious plans
          were made by a corps of detectives em
          ployed by Thaw to keep track of
          White's movements', and that on the
          day that White was shot he had dei
          cided to apply to the authorities to
          prevent the continuance of tha espion
          age to which he had been subjected.
          Body Guard Expensive
          According to the detective, White
          paid over $6000 between February 14,
          1005, and the day of his death for the
          protection of his person/ and for the
          shadowing of the detectives who were
          pursuing him.
          The detective thus describes a meet-
          Ing between White and himself, when
          he told the architect that Thaw .was
          the employer of the detectives who
          were annoying him. According to the
          statement. White said:'
          "This man Thaw Is crazy. He Imag
          ines that I have done him some wrong.
          I used to know his wife. I befriended
          her and .her family. Thaw is Insanely
          Jealous of his wife. He doubtless im
          agines that I am meeting her, and be
          fore God I am not.
          "My friendship for the. girl was taken
          from a purely fatherly interest, and
          since her marriage she has repaid my
          kindness by annoying .me greatly by
          making remarks to mutual acquaint
          ances intended to arouse the jealousy
          of her husband. I cannot understand
          it. I never In my life Injured man or
          woman."
          According to the diary on June 25,
          White said he had decided It was time
          to close up the affair. White said he
          was a nervous wreck, and that on the
          following Tuesday he was going to
          take final action In the, courts. That
          night he was shot.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1906-07-10/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Chorus+Girls%27+Testimony+Damaging+Harry+Thaw+Insane+Jealousy+Stanford+White+murder+Nesbit&amp;r=0.527%2C1.069%2C0.703%2C0.376%2C0&amp;st=text</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Chorus Girls' Testimony
          Damaging to Harry Thaw
          District Jerome is flooding the New York theatrical*
          X district with* subpenas for chorus girls in the Thaw murder case.]
          assert that jealousy, alone was responsible for t
          thefmurter of Stanford White. ;\u25a0 \u25a0'
          Friendslof^ Murderer's "Wife. Tell of the Young
          Millionaire's Insane Jealousy.
          MB. AND MRS. V HARRY KENDALL THAW. WHOSE DOMESTIC INFELICITIES ARE XOWJ
          BELIEVED TO lIAVE SUPPLIED THE MOTIVE FOR THE HUSBAND'S MURDER
          ING OF ARCHITECT PTAXFOBD WHITE.
          NEW ..YORK,, July. 9.— A .witness
          whose., testimony r may-be of consider
          able .importance in connection with the
          White-.Thaw.i' murder, case is --Warren
          Hammond,'" who one .time was em
          ployed'by ./.Thaw jas a. valet. Until to
          day;". It-: had,, been 'supposed '.that when
          William Bedford," .Thaw's valet, died
          the* testlmdny'rbf "tlier'only, person who
          ever occupied .the position of a body
          servant*^ to Ithe:*young "'man. 'had been
          Irrevocably^ lost/ however,
          acted f as 1 substitute 'for Bedford during
          four months vwhen r the latter was ill
          about' three* years- ago. -It -is expected
          that Hainrnond^ will ;be examined at the
          District /Attorney's' office" \u25a0 tomorrow.
          -'Amongthe persons questioned by As
          slstantjPistrict:Attorney' Garvan today
          was'; f Charles 3 Hafnett, t who. was .em-]
          ployed jby; Stanford Whlte as^a-secre
          tary;-It^ls. understood that
          testimony tended \io\ contradict the dis
          creditable ln^ White's private life.
          Mrs: -Beatrice Schwjirtx, who lives in
          West Thirty-second stre*t and; who is
          an -intimate friend" of Vnaw'. 'will bo
          questioned .by Garyan tomorrow.' It Is
          said that shortly 'after- Harry Thaw and
          Miss Nesbi t we're married Thaw threat
          ened, mV presence of Mrs. 'Schwartz,
          to shoot; Stanford iWhite,: and. it Is to
          ascertain -if r this': threat was _ actually
          made. that Garvan. will Interrogate Mrs.
          Schwartz.'. \u25a0
          The investigation »by '.the pjstricf At
          torney's.office to discover rthe motive
          for. the -killing of '-.White' Is bringing to
          the'bfflce'of -Ahe prosecutor many young
          women of »\the^,stage.J; The; Broadway
          theatrical district has .been flooded with
          subpenas. MAny chorus (iris have' left
          PRICE FIVE CENTS.
          the city and others remain at 0 their
          homes to avoid the subpena servers. 1
          Two young jwomen whom the District
          Attorney's office has been eager 'to In
          terview 'are'-Mlss'Pa'ula Desmond'and -\u25a0
          Miss Gertie \u25a0 Grant. It is alleged that
          these "young, women were followed -andl 1
          annoyed by detectives who had beejjl
          employed to .watch White. ,_^
          Paula Desmond, whose \u25a0 real Mm« 1»
          Pauline Kf Herman, is now at her homa
          In Kingston. N. V.. and a representativ«
          of ,*\u25a0 the"^D v fBt'rlct Attorney's offlce" ha.s
          gone'.there^to see her.
          »B£r*IfIOI94BStr4BIH3BPSBEPV'V t
          Miss Grant has been abroad for somi
          time, ,bnt returned last Saturday: D«^/
          tectlves were .watching all the steam
          ships, but the girl- slipped ashore un^s
          seen 'and. her whereabouts .now ii-no*\
          known. \u25a0'",."
          Both Miss Grant and: Miss Desmond!
          are known ;to have '.been friends r"of.
          Stanford White.
          \The activity of the District Attor;-'
          ne^s office in running.- dawn all jclewV
          InUhe theatrical district is largely d\x&lt;%
          to "the story told Assistant District At»
          torney Garyan "by Edna McClMre,.,*!
          show-girl and former friend of,, Mrs.;
          Thaw. Miss'McClure told the Assist^
          ant*' District •Attorney,' that White ;*«£•\u25a0
          tertalned .a. number of guests *in a
          Broadway restaurant I one nlghti t Tha w.
          saw;.Whlte. enter ,th« place. He begaa'
          to ''abWe White, Miss McClure "saysV and
          said to. his .wife: t- y.
          goes that blackguard now
          that owned you before I did."
          Mrs. Thaw is reported to have an
          swered:
          vstop .raking 'up. my past. Harry.*
          Continued -on Pajt 2, Colama T.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1906-07-25/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=NESBIT+GIRL+KILL+HER+Harry+Thaw+Stanford+White+Evelyn+Anna+Crane+Turnbull+Bergoff&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.16,0.597,0.736,0.736,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NESBIT GIRL SAID THAW WOULD A KILL HER
          1 DistrictAttorney Gets Extraordinary
          Statement from Ann Crane Sent by
          White in 1904 to Rescue Actress
          from Pittsburg Millionaire
          i
          IM DREADFULLY AFRAID
          SHE DECLARED IN PARIS
          important Witness Found by Detective Bergoff
          71 rm1g stifalrW ff f Pt mm frWm
          t
          c Art Iiy Begtrn Whit the oung
          Womans Protector
          J In exclusively publishing the story of Anna Crane the newtstand
          thfi strongest witness In the Thaw case The Evening World today fur
          nishes the most amazing contribution to the story of the murder of Stan
          I ford White that has been put into type For the first timethe woman
          who knows well of the relations existing between Harry Thaw and
          Evelyn Nesbit before their narriage than any living person makes a full
          free statementa statement that is as astounding as it was unexpected
          Ann Crane who went to Europe at Stantcrd Wtltoa b heJt to bring
          Efelrii KesUtrhoinea terth i l rus slrLhal IMl nlntp Uarrr Thawa
          hind paJnta a picture of almost Incredible condition She aaya that
          Harry Thaw virtually hold the roung actress a prisoner in Pa lii that he
          beat htr Until her flesh WILl a mUll ot black bruli that ha frequently
          tD tidbufn6 roontsiille Jjewent out to ratct women ot thb Part pafo
          r tnentltl4t he Vept her In terror at her lift Anti 11I1thilli conduct t 5Wftn3
          tboci1L ithnm JiiSllitaJluejJlj HtStf e M m yfitlifcMtiiair that orA
          h1ndM rgwAf
          d 1n1u ud Im ad t I1 On the other hind WiJtfl o iiU Qriai Mjri WM
          at aU UmM a pxtrpnaud A protA tdr orBr tyn lclabtt
          Xo Clhlr pliMleIInn that 11111I spprril In connection With fhl
          ertwe ermted HaltAce moth tushlta hHlrii A The Kvrnjn fVorlrt
          wrrativo of Anna Crnnra torn U It lA IdweiN 10 Iit the Jrtry M
          the rll or Hurrr 1bAtt It vrlllno billed tA ryrra enir cttl more Mean
          any other tolnK lo gyred Tilm to IJM rltrfrlf tmlr unUk tUt Ula4oul
          bli pier ut JuatfAttktlon ttnd icrbc ftffII In M jICIII at lu Mllr
          j Story Told by Anna Crane
          J This is the extraordinary story of Miss Anna Crane 1 the masseuse
          sent by Stanford White to Paris in the summer of 1901 to bring
          Evelyn Nesbit back to this Country with funds supplied by him She
          has told the story to Assistant DlstrictAttomey Robert J Turnbull
          and her testimony will be most important if Thaw Is placed on trial
          for his11fe n
          u MIss Crane was Tooted 6nJyaft niii cleverdetn tive work by
          PLBergofTlhe private detective now attached to the DistrictAttorneys
          office whose defense of Stanford White printed exclusively The Even
          Ing VorkJ was tlit luming P9lnt in tlifi most abjorbin miirdeijasc of
          t century
          Miss Crane is fifty years old with gray halt and fmnk fc1tUtd
          She cupiClnt de l apartrrhettCtnfiie Jil cs whet she was visited
          today by a reporter for The Evening World
          This ald st tool masseuse was the mysterious woman who yesterday
          I Visited the Criminal Courts Building and was closeted With Jr Ttimbull
          foe three hours
          rtfas Crone ffitlJ li aN follow
          t I I hang known Br Trn Keablt errs nee ehe anent on the etegd X
          L mt the poor young woman when ihe Wit nliylne In Th Wild R6s
          r eompnr fa 11 wllvtbE with tr mottos at the Hotel Wol1lnrtontt
          VM tSirtnMjrto IfS Ncsblt and her lau htef that I became aojttalnuxl
          with BUnford WlilU
          We then called Evelyn Neoblt by hw right tame of FTdrencei flh
          I ConUnul1 on Ekcond Page</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1906-08-09/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=FINDS+MOTIVE+SLAYING+Stanford+White+Harry+Thaw+Wiilliam+Jerome+Evelyn+Nesbit+murder</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>FINDS A MOTIVE
          FOR SLAYING
          OF WHITE.
          Jerome Has Evidence That
          a Chorus Girl's Prank
          Moved Thaw to Homicide
          MASQUERADED AS
          EVELYN NESBIT
          Architect Fell Into Trap
          and Wrote Note That
          Enraged the Husband
          SPECIAL DISPATCH TO THE CALL.
          NEW YORK. Aug. B.— New and
          important evidence, providing a
          plausible motive for the mur-
          tier of Stanford- White, has
          lately come into District Attorney
          •Jerome's posseslon. The inkling of the
          facts was conveyed to the District At
          torney indirectly from Florence Zieg-
          Xeldt, a theatrical manager, who is the
          "husband of Anna Held, and who is at
          present living in Paris.
          The story is that Stanford White
          \u25a0ent a note and a basket of flowers to
          Mrs. Evelyn Nesbit Thaw the after
          r.oon of his. murder, and that the
          tragedy grew out of the thoughtless
          ir.ischief of three chorus girls.
          VISITED WHITE'S STUDIO.
          "The tragedy occurred some days
          prior, to my last trip from America,"
          said Mr. Ziegfeldt. "and I was full of
          It on my way over. Among the pas
          sengers was a young woman very well
          lmoTi-n to the amusement-loving New
          York public, who was a prominent
          member of the chorus in one of my
          productions. Naturally we chatted.
          and naturally the Thaw tragedy was
          touched upon. I knew that this girl
          was one of White's acquaintances, and
          drew her out. I found that she knew
          eomething which the District Attorney
          w&lt;>u]d give a good deal to know. She
          \u25a0 jjw. tK?.?- -cN* \u25a0 \u25a0 '-\u25a0*" Vf T'i»2ni»d t'arC'i
          other members of my old company to j
          pay a farewell visit to Mr. White^ in j
          the tower of Madison Square Garden j
          the night prior to Mr. White's death, i
          They were to sail in a few days. Mr. I
          White was not there, and as they were
          leaving the place an attendant asked
          what- names he should report to Mr.
          White as those of his visitors.
          "Oh," said one of the girls, laugh- j
          Jng, 'Say that Mrs. Harry Thaw
          calied.'
          SENDS XOTE TO MRS. THAW.
          •Nex.t day, Mr. White, according to
          this girl, sent a neat little note to Mrs.
          Thaw, expressing his regret at his ab
          sence at the time of her call and dis
          patched a basket of roses to her ad
          drers..
          "My informant believed that Thaw
          Ea-a- the roses, read the card attached
          lo the basket, and perhaps read the
          rote which accompanied them. She
          was inclined to believe that White
          o^ved his sudden cutting off to the whim
          cf a chorus girl."
          It is known this young \u25a0woman is
          nov.- in New York, having returned, it
          is said, at the request nf Mr Jerome.
          It is believed that she will be o*re of
          the most important witnesses for the
          people.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045389/1915-08-08/ed-1/?sp=41&amp;q=harry+thaw&amp;r=-0.088,0.563,0.629,0.337,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1913-10-12/ed-1/?sp=51&amp;q=harry+thaw&amp;r=-0.055,-0.019,1.397,0.747,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>j HJi l i:\liLlS-DISPATCH: RICHMOND, VA., SUND.AY, OCTOBER 12. .1913.
          Evelyn Thaw's Own Frank Revelations of Her Kaleidoscopic Career Which Touched
          Life at All Points--The Innocent Little Beauty Who Almost Starved to Death
          p Forlorn Poverty and Suddenly Burst Into the Most Brilliant Star That Ever
          Illuminated New York's Gay World
          could cot breast; I must go tor a time at any
          rate with the stream if I would find my bear
          ings.
          An enormouB catyclyfim which comes to a
          young life leaves little impression on the spir
          its of the child. Doctors say that children who
          lose their limbs in aocidents come to maturity
          with a sense of haying been born as they are,
          without any recollection of previously having
          been better equipped for the battle of life.
          Young people wholo3e their parents u.t my age
          have the greatest difficulty iu retaining a mem
          ory of those parents, however kindly and how
          ever apparently indispensable they may have
          been in their lifetime. It may seem a shock
          ing thing -that 1 did not become melancholic,
          or so depressed as to take no interest in life;
          but a healthy child?and I was only sixteen, be
          it remembered?abhors bad memories and. all
          the gloomy, morbid machinery of Introspection,
          and I found myself almost 6a I had been before
          that night, with interests as keen, with as
          poignajit a sense of humor as ever, though a
          change 'had come to me and though my anglo
          of vision had altered.
          There was one frolic into which I got which
          alarmed White. I believe that ho was genuinely
          fond of me, and that he took an unselfish pleas
          ure in making my life brighter. He arranged
          holidays for me, saw that I should not surfer
          from lack of work, and generally was pood and
          kind. But an all-night party, of which I was
          a member, irked him.
          I must go to school, too said. I was not fitted
          for the work I was doing; I iriust fit myself for
          life as I would find it
          It was a dismal prospect for me, to be lifted
          out of the light and glitter of Broadway to the
          quiet and peaceful dullness of a convent school,
          and it did not appeal to me. But he and my
          iTitf i-i' v u -ri V' 'i
          F Copyright by Campbell Art Company.
          gvaph in the Wortd?Evelyn in tfye Gorgeous Kimono Stanford White Bought for Her, "Asleep" Upon the
          White Bear Rug in the Twenty-fourth Street Studio.
          she hadn't told things about people she would have been In a
          splendid position. "Don't talk. Evelyn?tell nobody, and nobody
          ?will know.'
          Most Important of all I must not tell my mothor. To tell one's
          mother things meant all the world knowing. Mothers never kept
          things to thomsolvea.
          So he went on, sometimes pleading, sometimes covertly menao.
          Ing, and I listened, dazed and bewildered, as all the fair fabrics of
          my faith crumbled into dust. He was convincing to a point, and
          that point was the instinct which Is implanted In every heart?
          Ihe scale which weighs good and evil. He wa3 older and so
          touch wiser and cleverer?and I was so young.
          No human soul can stand alone. Cut out the faith and the
          (trust and you must substitute something for it to lean upon. 1
          listened and disbelieved and trusted. I had to build up a new
          faith, and I needed a scaffolding, a shell from whence to work.
          J never wholly accepted Stanford "White's creed, it was too rotten
          a foundation to build any life upon, but from a raging sea even
          a quicksand makes solid foothold to the wrecked mariner,
          and quicksand served until I reached firm earth.
          Courted by Thaw Under a False Name.
          I oannot remember now whether 1 knew Harry Thaw before the
          events recorded In the last chapter. 1 used to receive at the
          theatre letters from a very persistent correspondent, asking me
          out to lunch. They were written under an assumed name, and
          were evidently from a man of some refinement. Once they came
          accompanied by some money, which I sent back. As in the case
          of White, my actual meeting with him was through the instru
          mentality of a girl friend.
          I My first impression of Mr. Thaw, was an unpleasant one.' I
          met a man whose face alike attracted and repelled me. There
          was a curloue look In his eyes, a. sinister brutality about the
          mouth which had an unpleasant effect upon me, and our first
          meeting?it was at a restaurant, and, as I say, I had the society
          of another girt?was made up of a fairly harmless quarrel be
          tween himself and myself, the subject being the beauty of a
          e member of the chorus. Harry Thaw spoke unkindly of her and
          5 i remember I defended her. 'I left him with the sense of relief
          one secures when one gets through with b disagreeable person.
          1 had no desire to meet him again. I was not very much In
          terested, If the truth be told; at best, he was a pleasant young
          man who paid me the compliment of admiring me from the other
          who wrote me letters expressing a ,wish to make my acquaint
          ance. A girl on the stage receives' shch letters In" shoals from
          all sorts of people, good, bad and'indifferent, and when I had
          met him 'I thought merely that his curiosity was satisfied and
          'there was an end of It
          f But he was indeed persistent. He pursued nie'with bis harm
          8j leas attentions. It was after another such pfarty to which 1 had
          1 been Invited, and the Invitation to which I had accepted, that he
          revealed himself to me. We had come from the restaurant, and
          1 I was entering the theatre, when all of a sudden he said, with
          3 almost dramatic earnestness: "I am not (the man whose
          u name be had given), I am Harry Thaw, of Pittsburgh."
          d i looked at him with some amusement He was bo earnest;
          there was such trembling pride in his voice; a disguised
          Napoleon revealing himself to a near-sighted veteran could not
          1 have made the revelation with greater aplomb. I. do not know
          2 what he expected me to do. 1 had an uncanny feeling that I
          should stagger back, or should turn pale, or should do something
          I do not say thla unkindly, but it struck me as funny at the time
          and so very like Harry. 'Indeed, eo characteristic was it that I
          do not think I ever knew him much bette' at any subsequent time
          than I did at that moment
          I contonted myself by saying, "Indeed!" There seemed little
          else to say. He was "Harry Thaw, of Pittsburgh"?that was
          enough. In one minute he had told me the full story of his con
          descension, the explanation of those let
          ters written under the nom de plume.
          Harry Thaw, of Pittsburgh, was Some
          body.
          It Irritated and amused me, this atti
          tude of his. But even a pose, so long
          as it is consistently upheld. Is lmpres-
          slve. Men -who acclaim their own im-
          portance persistently and with no sign
          of'hesitation as to ther own convlctoin
          on the subject, cease to be nobodies and
          become Somebodies. And the egotism
          which promoted Harry's sentence and
          whlch appered in all his dealings with v
          the remainder of humanity at once fas
          olnated and annoyed.
          Harry Thaw was an earnest young
          man. There was a side of him which
          was rather terrible, as you may learn. j
          He was very earnest, no philanderer, no S
          ilght liver; even In his Infidelities he
          was absorbed and sincere. Such mat
          ters were serious propositions, present
          ing aspeots which would not oocur to
          the normal man.
          When hifi mind took that turn he
          played at reformer with all the entihu
          elasm of a Savonarofta. He was very
          earnest about himself. He took Harry
          Tliaw and his position in life very seriously. It has always been
          a wonderful thing *jo me that ho has not written the story of
          his life. Perhaps it is because hfe does not possess the Bense of
          humor -which makes sucii a performance possible.
          He took hl3 position seriously; his world value too seriously.
          Like many egotists there was a very gentle and kindly side to
          him. It would be an ungracious thing to say that such gentle
          ness and' BweretnesB was part of hlB egotism. Letjhe put all his
          generosity to his ciedlt, for It was only.his arrogance oklhought
          and action which was to bring about his downfall.
          My Acquaintance with White Continued.
          His persistence was of a fine order. He never left me alone;
          he was everlastingly following me up. iHe was not offensive, nor
          was his attitude one to which. I could take any exception. In
          course of time 1 grew to like him and to regard him as a dear
          and reliable friend. He introduced me to his mother, and be
          came acquainted with my own mother, and the course of> our
          friendship ran fairly smoothly. It was long after- the events
          which 1 have described In a previous chapter that he became a
          factor In my life. The miserable friendship jbetween Stanford
          White and myself was In progress. 'Faithful tp my. promise, 1
          had told nobody. I had accepted his conception of life with .a
          dull sense of helplessness. Here.was a phas^ ot hinanity which
          1 could not change* lwr* was, a strong, strettm running, which 1
          Evelyn as Harry Thaw First Saw Her in
          "The Wild Rose."
          mother insisted, and off to school I waa packed. It wa3 an amus*
          ing experience, because Mr. White had made laborious, arrange
          ments that my association with the stage should not be men
          tioned. but it leaked out somehow. 1 found myself among these
          girls as something of a. horoine. I was a real live actress trans*
          planted into their midst. We used to have little plays and make
          up with some home-made cosmetics. Toothpowder laid on with
          .piece of wadding was an excellent substitute for poudre do rlaf,
          and I shudder when I think of the substitutes w? employed for
          rouge and lip salve.
          From time to time Mr. White came down to see me, and at
          other times I went to New York to see him. Exactly what would
          have happened had I not been seized with an attack of appendi
          citis, I do not kuow. The attack was so sudden that it wa3
          necessary for the doctors who were called In to operate on. mo
          in the school, and while I was there Mr. Thaw was a frequent
          visitor. During the operation Itself he and my mother walked
          up and down the garden outside discussing my future, though
          there seemed at that moment to be little future for me.
          Mr. Thaw seemed absorbed in ray welfare, so far as my health
          and happiness were concerned. Evelyn will never recuperate
          unless she goes for a voyage, he told my mother, and wo must
          get her to Europe
          I needed little persuasion to explore the wonderful new world
          which was awaiting me beyond the seas. Our plana were mado
          and we sailed, Mr. Thaw, my mother and myself, to Europe.
          The voyage mado all the difference to mo. I began to pick up
          health and strength the moment wo sailed. Harry was most
          good and attentive. I began to lose the subtle sense of oppres
          sion which had weighed on me during the months I was at
          school. The Influence of Stanford "White grew smaller; a new
          life was opening before me. Harry had proposed to me before
          we sailed. I think he proposed twice, but ou both occasions I
          had refusod him. I realized I could not marry any man unless
          he knew everything there was to bo known about me. This was
          a matter of common honesty, and I take no credit for desiring
          to be frank and above board with my future husband.. For the
          moment I had no wl3h to tell him. I was quite happy in tha
          enjoyment of the present, quite willing to let the past slip from,
          memory and the future take care of Itself.
          Some women have a conscience, some have a sense of self*
          preservation; they frequently exist together, but most often ona
          does duty for the other. Conscience is an uneasy desire for
          frank dealing, and I suppose It was a suppressed consclenoe which
          made me sweep aside what would have been a very advanta?
          gecus offer. Had Thaw been any other kind of man he might
          have been satisfied to let matters slide, to take such happineBS
          as the gods gave him in the way their chosen Instruments chosa
          to offer It.
          I Tell Harry About Stanford White.
          But he was, as 1 say, persistent. He wanted to marry. Noth*
          lng etee, nothing less would satisfy him. We were tho best oC
          friends in London, though It was in London that I first had soma
          idea of his perversity. A bmtal assault committed upon a boy
          at one of the leading hotels, a flogging which was unjustifiable
          and wicked, almost ruined Harry, and It coBt him $6,000 to square
          the matter. The story as I have heard It was that Harry put a
          lot of money upon a table and watched behind a screen when a
          boy who had been summoned to the room came In. The tempta
          tion of tho money was irresistible, and the boy took two gold
          r.olna. Immediately Harry pounced_upon him. took him to a
          bathroom and tlogfeea him so terribly that the poor child had to
          go home. A doctor was called In, and eventually a lawyer. Thera
          can be no doubt that Harry's object in laying a trap for a boy
          who had shown no disposition to steal was to administer a
          flogging?a practise which in some way seemed to gratify him.
          Contrast this' side of his character with the scene which fol
          lowed when mother had gone back to America and Harry and I
          wore alone in Paris. He came into my suite one night. He said
          he wanted to speak to mo. I thought ho looked haggard and
          worried, and I closed the door and Invited him in.
          Without any preliminary he came to tho ooint.
          "I want you to marry me," he said.
          He was as dogged and as porsistent as over. There was aqi
          fending him off with excuses, with reasons or with expanatlons
          as to why marriage was not desirable. I knew in an instant
          that now he must known the truth, must take his answer for
          good or evil.
          "I cannot marry you." I said.
          "Why not?"
          "Because"-^
          '"Do you not love me?"
          I nodded.
          "Then why?" he repeated.
          "Because"
          He walked toward me and laid his hand on my shoulder. look
          In? straight into my eyes.
          "Is it because o? Stanford White?" he asked, and I nodded
          again.
          1 hesitated a moment.
          "Sit down over there and I wi'ii tell "cu everything"
          U was a story that was difficult to tell. But it had to be donis.
          Very slowly, very deliberately, making no excuse for myself, giv
          ing r.o place to prejudice against White, 1 toid him all'that had
          happened from the very beginning.
          He sat in silence for a while, his hands shakfng, hit? facft
          ghastly, then lie rose and walked up and down the room, lite
          shaking hands gesticulating as he muttered.
          Then when I reached tho climax of the story he cat down
          suddenly, burying his face in his hands, ar.d burst into tears.
          You saw all that was best in Harry Thaw then, all the finer
          side of him, all the womanliness in him, all the Quixote that was
          In his composition.
          He sat there sobbing "Poor child! poor childl"
          The relationship between Mr. Thaw and myself at that time
          was one o2 complete sympathy. There had bi>en some unpleas
          antness lu Lonc'or. Mother had returned to the States as a
          result of a disagreement, and Mr. Thaw, who saw ancient castleo
          in every windmill and armies In every flock of sheep, was pre
          pared to repudiate the suggestion that he had kidnapped me.
          Here is a letter he wrote to Mr. Longfellow, his attorney. It
          deals with my mother. "She states that I have kidnapped
          her daughter. Before she lands she will know that I have
          done the best 1 could." That he had the most extraordinary
          ideas may be gathered from one extract; "Telephone Mrs. Nes
          blt,' he instructs, "but not In your own name, and ask her if
          she saw Thaw abroad; as soon as she answers hang ud the
          receiver."
          It was here that he adopted the role of reformer. He began
          writing letters to the vigilance societies, exposing White.
          You might think very well, indeed, of Harry Thaw, his gener*
          osity, his boyish enthusiasm for the cause he had suddenly
          espoused, and there is no reason why he should not have all
          the credit that is due him for his impressive championing of
          righteousness, but It has to be remembered that .Thaw himself
          was something of a degenerate. Of his flogging propensities
          there is no need to tell. He was given to practices which ara
          not pleasant to relate. On one occasion, as I was told, he had
          amused himself by pouring boiling hot water over a girl In a.
          bath, and on another he had Hogged a young girl who had been
          strapped to a bedpost. Such a mixture of good and evil could
          hardly be found without mental derangement. My own view is
          that at that time the melancholia which dominated him had be
          gun to take firm hold.
          I sailed to New York before him, with ray marriage practically
          arranged for, and ho followed a short time after.
          All this time Harry was in correspondence with his mother.
          She was in many ways a remarkable woman, and enjoyed the
          confidence of her children. He took his intentions very seri
          ously. and was not inclined to accept any advice which might
          be offered.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045366/1906-06-26/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=harry+thaw</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THAW IN TOMBS
          ONMURDERCHARGE
          Continued From First Pago.
          for. Peoheau, who examined White's
          Body after the shooting.
          Committed to Tombs.
          TJpon the strength of this affidavit
          Coroner I)oolt directed that the pris
          oner be comnuttled to the Tombs with
          out bail.
          S:lle.e
          x.
          During almost his entire stay va. the
          coroner's office, Thaw sat with his
          hands pressed to his face to conceal
          himself from the score or more of
          photographers who had crowded mlo
          the room. Several times the coroner
          directed that the room be cleared, but
          just as often the photographers and
          other spectators crowded back into the
          room.
          In remanding the prisoner to the
          Tombs Coroner Dooley announced that
          the inquest into White's death would
          be held on Thursday. He added that
          this early day had been decided on be
          cause of the expressed desire of counsel
          both for the prisoner and the prosecu
          tion to have the case taken before this
          month's grand iury instead of letting
          it go over until next month. At the
          conclusion of the proceedings Thaw
          was taken thru a side door to avoid "the
          great crowd which had gathered in the
          corridois of the criminal court build
          ing and across the "Bridge of Sight*"
          to the Tombs.
          Assigned to Cell.
          After his pedigree had been taken,
          he was assigned to a cell on the second
          tier of the prison, where all prisoners
          charged with homieicte are confined.
          He received a visit a few minutes
          later from the prison physician and
          was then left alone.
          After Lawyer Delafleld had taken
          leave of his client he was asked if he
          would have any statement to make c^on
          serning the case later in the day.
          "Certainly not," he replied, "and
          have instructed my client not to talk
          to anyone."
          White Funeral Thursday.
          The funeral service over the body of
          Mr. White probably will be held at St.
          Bartholomew's church on Thursday,
          Bishop Coadiutor Greer officiating.
          SHOOTING IN DETAIL
          JChaw Deliberate in His Movements
          Before He Acted.
          foumal Special Service.
          New York, June 28. Stanford
          White, architect, millionaire and art
          Sonnoisseur,
          was shot to death at the
          rst performance of "Mile. Cham
          pagne" at the Madison Square Eoof
          garden last night by Harry K. Thaw,
          ie well known Pittsburg millionaire,
          who created a sensation in society cir
          cles not long ago by marrying Evelyn
          wesbit, poor but beautiful artists'
          bodel.
          Three friends were with White. All
          were enjoying the show, which is of
          ihe conventional summer comic-opera
          Ityle, full of fun and dancing. There
          s/as a big crcowd and not a vacant
          leat could bo seen anywhere.
          Suddenly, about 11 o'clock, a tall,
          well-made young fellow, who had been
          pitting with a strikingly beautiful
          roung woman at a table near the Mad
          ison avenue end of the roof garden, on
          the Twenty sixth street side, arose,
          made some excuse to the young woman
          ind sauntered away He did not ap
          pear to be in anv way excited, altho
          persons who sat near him said after
          ward that he had been peering and
          itaiang about the place for many min
          ates, as if he was seaichmg for some
          The young woman was serene,
          (leither her face" nor her manner shew
          ing any trace of apprehension.
          As the young man strolled among the
          tables, seemingly at ease, he never
          [eased to watch Stanford White. Harry
          Short, a comedian, who plays "Fuller
          Bpice," had lust finished singing I
          tould love a million gills," and the
          ihorus of twenty girls was prancing
          tbout the stage.
          First Shot Missed.
          At this moment the tall young man
          Irew near to Stanford White, whipped
          revolver out of the breast pocket of
          lis coat, aimed quickly at White's head
          ind pulled the trigger. He missed. The
          ihot was loud, but no one in the crowd
          teemed to heed it, least of all did
          Jtanford White, whom the bullet barely
          mssed.
          Then in quick succession the young
          pan fired the revolver twice more, both
          toilets taking effect, causing White to
          kitch forward in a heap on the floor.
          The assassin was singularly calm.
          "Well, he ruined my wife and I got
          tim," he remarked, as he started
          tway, still holding the pistol.
          No one in the audience was alarmed
          (ry the three shcts, for only a little
          hil before one of the girls of the
          Champagna company had run up
          of the aisles and lumped upon tho
          itage and the crowd thought the shots
          urere simply a part of tho play. But a
          foung woman who sat at the next table
          n White's right, Seeing the limp body,
          ihe blood and the pale face, lumped up
          tod screamed:
          Young Woma Starts Panic.
          ray God! He's dead,' she
          "Ob,
          iried.
          Instantly the thousand men. and wo
          nen leaped to their feet in wild panic
          ind pressed toward the exits. The
          eopl on the stage halted in confusion,
          the orchestra kept on playing the
          ^husic for the dance that should follow
          slarry Short's song.
          Lionel Lawrence, the stage manager,
          lumped up on a table and called to
          the excited crowd: "Keep still it's
          dl right."
          But the well-dressed men and women
          lid not cease for a minute to trample
          me another in their wild flight. Pres
          tntly, however, the crush ceased.
          Manager Lawrence ordered the cho
          ins to dance, and the twenty girls began
          jo caper to the music. A few seconds
          later Lawrence climbed over the foot
          lights and began to push the chorus
          people away, crying: "Leave the
          stage."
          White Died Instantly.
          Sechtner, summoned from the
          ^ience. pronounced Mr. White dead.
          Two waiters spread a tablecloth over
          the body. Manager Lawrence said to
          the audience:
          "Ladies and gentlemen, a most se
          rious accident has occurred. Please
          leave the house as quickly and quietly
          as possible.''
          The crowd began to move awav. A
          dozen women who had fainted were re
          vived.
          As Thaw, with the revolver, ap
          proached one of the elevators, Fireman
          Paul Bruden of engine companv No. 60,
          detailed at the show, grabbed the hot
          pistol from his hand. He made no re
          sistance, but stepped into the elevator.
          Cause of the Shooting.
          "He deserved it," Thaw said very
          calmly to Bruden. "He deserved it,
          and I can prove it. He ruined my wif
          and left her helpless."
          Policeman Debbs hurried into the ele
          vator and touched the young man on
          the shoulder. "You're under arrest,"
          he said.
          "All right. It's all right," the pris
          oner replied.
          Just before the elevator started a
          slender, dark, very pretty young wo
          man, the same one with whom Thaw had
          been sitting before ho sauntered away
          on his errand to death, came rushing
          into the car. She threw her arms
          around the prisoner and kissed him.
          "Oh, JTarrv,'' she cried. "Why did
          you do it, Harry?"
          "It 's all right, dear he answered,
          kissing her. "He ruined you and I
          fixed him. It's all right.'"'
          Thaw Sends for Carnegie.
          To a man who had been in the ele
          vator before he was arrested the pris
          oner now turned. He opened his pock
          etbook and handed the man a $10 bill.
          I wish," he said, "that you would
          call up Andrew Carnegie at 1098 Fifth
          avenue and tell him I'm in trouble. I
          am Harry Thaw of Pittsburg."
          When the elevator arrived at the
          floor the voung woman who had
          issed Thaw thru crowd,^
          quickly1
          got intslippedg a bi tourinthe auto ajnd
          was driven away. Policeman, Debbs
          took Harry Thaw to the Tenderloin
          police station.
          When Thaw was taken to the West
          Thirtieth street-station his "pedigree"
          was taken by the sergeant in the usual
          manner, and a search of his pockets
          discovered cards bearing his name. Af
          ter he had been locked up, the police
          held, pending the arrival of the coroner,
          the following witnesses to the shooting:
          Witnesses Held.
          Lionel Lawrence, stage director of
          the Madison Square Garden roof: H. N.
          Rnben8tein, 22-4 Henry street: Marion
          Panchnor, 84 West One Hundred and
          Thirteenth street Warner Paxson, 146
          East Thirtieth street, and Paul Brndi,
          130 West Thirty-seventh street.
          At the station Policeman Debbs, who
          arrested Thaw, repeated that the pris
          oner had said on handing the pistol to
          him, that White had ruined his wife
          and that he was glad he had killed
          him. The fireman detailed at the roof
          corroborated Debbs.
          Lawyer "Dan" O'Beilly arrived at
          the police station soon after the arrest
          with Tod Sloan, the lockey, saying
          they were present to look after Thaw's
          interests. Neither was permitted to
          see the prisoner.
          Son Is Notified.
          Lawrence White, a son of the mur
          dered man, did not learn of the murder
          of his father until a late hour last
          night. He returned from the New Am
          sterdam roof garden about midnight.
          A reporter awaited him with the sad
          intelligence that his fattier had been
          shot. He Said*'
          I have been home from college but
          a few days," said Lawrence. "Mother
          is at her country home at St. James,
          L. I. Father and I have had the house
          to ourselves. I have had breakfast at
          home, as has father, but luncheon out
          side and dinner outside.
          Dined at Cafe Martin.
          I was at home this evening when
          father stopped in. He said that he had
          declared a proposed trip to Philadelphia
          off and that he was going to remain
          in town and dine. He invited me to
          go with him to the Cafe Martin for
          dinner. Another gentleman, a guest,
          dined with us.
          The three of us then got in an elec
          tric hansom and were driven to the
          New Amsterdam roof. Father left us
          there, saying he was going to the Mad
          ison Squaro roof for a while, and that
          he would see us later at home. I do
          not know anything of his inovements
          after he left us at the New Amster
          dam roof."
          It pould not be learned who the third
          person was at dinner at the Cafe Mar
          tin. Young White said that his father
          may have gone to the Madison Square
          roof on business, as he was a director
          of the garden.
          Beginning of Tragedy.
          The beginning of the tragedy was in
          the Cafe Martin, its end was at the
          roof garden.
          In the first scene Mr. and Mrs. Thaw,
          her father and another man were (fin
          ing together when Mr. White and two
          others entered and took places nearby.
          According to Mr. Thaw's own words
          to a reporter, he did not know of the
          presence of the architect until the agi*
          tation of his wife attracted his atten
          tion. He asked a question to be an
          swered by a note saying:
          "That dirty blackguard is here."
          White left the cafe soon afterward,
          visiting his studio in the tower of Mad
          ison Square Garden, which is one of the
          many buildings he designed, then going
          to his club and finally to the roof gar
          den.
          Mr. and Mrs. Thaw were there. Mrs.
          Thaw had gone back of the scenes to
          visit some friends and immediately her
          husband began pacing up and down
          the floor. It was while Thaw was on
          the western side of the building that
          White came in, sat down and chatted
          a moment with Harry Stevens, and
          then as Stevens left, looked at the
          ?tage.onThafwthe
          watched him a moment
          rom entrances then began
          threading his way forward.
          White Started to Rise.
          Without looking to the right or left,,
          brushing into several men and women,
          he walked slowly toward the table an*
          til he leaned forward over its edge op
          posite to his victim. As he Aid this
          White recognized him and made a move
          as if to arise. But there was no
          With some muA
          *ere imprecationtime. the
          young man drarTing a large automatic
          revolver began nring. Three shots
          rang out but two took effect, and White
          was dead. Turning Thaw faced the
          audience, and "broke" the weapon,
          throwing all the cartridges out, and
          started away. It was then he was ar
          rested, and soon afterward Mrs. Thaw
          rushed up and putting her arms about
          his neck kissed him.
          White Disturbed Wife.
          A statement credited to Thaw imme
          diately after the arrest is this:
          "We were all at a party in Martins..
          You can find out the name of the others
          there, but I was sitting some distance
          from my wife. Suddenly I saw her get
          vpry pale and begin to shiver and I
          th~- she was iU.
          made a motion to inquire what
          VVJ. the matter and she called a waiter
          and wrote a note which she sent around
          the table to me.
          "The note read: 'The dirty black
          guard is here.' Then I turned and ft
          NS NESBrTr^t.
          after the shooting. She was a noted
          showgirl and artist's model when Thaw
          married her a few years ago. His fam
          ily disapproved.
          Thaw and his wife came to New York
          a few days ago from Pittsburg and
          stayed at the Hotel Lorraine. Last
          evening they dined with two friends
          upstairs in the Hotel Martin, at Twen
          ty-sixth street and Fifth avenue. Stan
          ford White dined in the same restau
          rant, but on the lower floor.
          Shortly after 1.30 o'clock last night
          young Thaw received an answer to the
          many messages which he had dispatched
          to his attorneys. Lawyer Heightman
          of the firm of Delafleld Sturgis sent
          a messenger to say that he was on his
          way to the station.
          I won't talk to him, so you needn't
          bring him in here," Thaw told the
          doorman, when the message was taken
          to him in his cell. I want to see Dela
          fleld, and if I can't talk to him I won't
          saj' anything."
          Detectives Seek Mrs. Thaw.
          Detectives Foster and McDonnell
          were sent from the station shortly after
          1 0 'clock with orders to find Mrs. Harry
          Thaw and bring her to the station.
          Harry Thaw was to have sailed today
          with his wife to join his mother, who
          sailed Saturday.
          Miss Ivan Richardson, who was in
          the audience at the roof garden told
          this story: "When the three pistol
          shots were heard everybody in the au
          dience seemed to think they were in
          some Way a part of the show. The
          chorus and soloist were on the stage
          singing. In some other acts there had
          been so much noisy work that I, at
          least, thought for a moment that the
          shots wereu^rt of the*act and looked
          for something to happen ."to explain
          them.
          Chorus Girls Took Fright*. &amp;-J
          "Then we heard the long-drawn
          scream of a womanthrilling and agon
          izing. The chorus girls began to
          scream and run off the stage.
          A panic in the audience was immi
          nent. Just then Cassius Fleimann, the
          composer of the songit was his first/
          production and he was leading the or
          chestra, flung his music aside and said
          to the musicians: 'Strike up "Johnny
          Jones" and keep playing.' The stage
          director, Lionel Lawrence, rushed on
          the stage in his shirtsleeves, and urged
          the chorus girls back to their places,
          shouting, 'Dance, sing, keep it up.'
          "They danced and sang, with their
          faces showing deadly white under their
          makeup. We could see their excite
          ment. I call it game for the composer,
          a little man not more than five feet tall,
          who perhaps never had led an orches
          tra before, to think of the right thing
          to do and prevent a rush of people.
          "When Mr. Lawrence saw that the
          man was dead he dismissed the audi
          ence, and all went out quietly.''
          Thaw Brooded Over Wrong.
          "Stanford White wronged my wife,
          he is the scoundrel he ought to be put
          out of the way."
          So said Harry K. Thaw at luncheon
          with a friend down town several
          weeks ago. ._
          "Little Evelyn Nesbit came to New
          York almost four years ago," Thaw
          told his friend. "Her father, a Pitts
          burg lawyer and vicepresident of the
          League of American Wheelmen, had
          just died.
          Mrs. Nesbit came on here with Eve
          lyn and her little brother, and they all
          lived at No. 245 West Twenty-second
          street. Evelyn was an artist's model
          and posed for photographers. She was
          a sweet, innocent girl, almost a child,
          and one of the most beautiful girls
          that ever lived.
          '.Lederer heard of her and gaveher
          a place in the chorus of the "Wild
          Bose" at the Casino.
          "Then Stanford White found her
          out. Do you know him?" Thaw looked
          furious. ''Ask any of your friends who
          know about fast life in this town and
          they'll tell you he was notorious as a
          seeker out of young girls on the stage.
          "He became acquainted with Eve
          lyn took her to after-theater suppers
          andl out in his automobile. You can
          guess the rest.
          Sent Girl to School.
          "He aent her, after awhile,, to a
          school in Madison, N. J., to finish her
          education. It was on one of her visits
          home from that school that I first met
          her.''
          Thaw's eyes blazed when he talked
          of White. Other friends of his said to
          night that he had told a like story to
          them and seemed always to be brood
          ing over
          White'sealleged e" Whit Warned
          W
          1
          Mr. White *s friends even warned him
          to be careful, but he declared that there
          was no reason for the feeling and went
          about his business as usual. Mr. and
          Mrs. Thaw lived in Pittsburg and the
          incident was fast being forgotten, until
          the early part of this spring, when the
          vrs ryr- ,v i)ie c-nrin to this city and took
          apartments. The warnings were re
          vl
          THE MINNEAPOLIS JOURNAL.
          that ever lived,'' said Manager Lederer.
          "He became interested in Miss Nesbit
          when she was playing "Florodora"
          and tried to help her when he knew
          what a struggle she and her mother
          wero having to get along. I know of
          many cases where White has aided
          voung people striving to obtain a foot
          hold on the stage. He was a most kind
          ly generous man."
          MRS. WHITE" RECEIVES NEWS
          Starts at Once for Her Home in New
          York.
          St. James, L. L, June 26.Mrs. Stan
          ford White, widow of the man whom
          Harry K. Thaw shot and killed at Mad
          ison Square roof garden, was informed
          of the tragic death of her husband early
          today.- She at once started for the fam
          ily's city home in New York. When
          Mrs. White reached the railway station
          to take the train for New York she was
          in a highly nervous state and denied
          herself to everybody.
          THAW A HEADY YOUTH
          He Has Always Had Money and His
          1 Own Way.
          Pittsburg, June 26.Harry Kendall
          Thaw is about 36 years old and is the
          son of the late William Thaw, who was
          vice president of the Pennsylvania
          lines west. He was a graduate of the
          Western University of Pennsylvania,
          and when in Pittsburg made his home
          with his mother'at Lyndhurat, Beech
          wo^d boulevard, in the East End of the
          city,' Since his graduation from college
          and "the attainment of his maiority
          Thajw'harj^ *T&amp;$lB. in Pittsburg.
          Much of his tim% nan been spent abroad,
          and it was whilej\in Paris that he met
          Evelyn Nesbit. fy
          Harry Thaw is a*brother of J. Cope
          ley Thaw, the countess of Yarmouth,
          who was Alice Thaw, and also of Mrs.
          George Lauder Oarnegie of Cumber
          land, JFla. He is also a- half-brother of
          Benjamin Thaw.,
          Mrs. William Thaw, mother of Har
          ry, sailed for Europe Saturday on one
          of the slow steamers. She is on her
          way to visit her daughter, the coun
          tess of Yarmouth^ Harry and Ids bride
          were booked to sail on Wednesday of
          this week.
          While attending the university
          Pittsburg, Harry Thaw was a student
          of quiet habits. After he attained his
          majority, however, he appeared to de
          velop a fancy for traveling, and after
          a short residence in "New York he left
          for Paris.
          The prospective trip upon which he
          was to start on Wednesday was for the
          purpose of joining his mother in Eu
          rope and visiting his sister, the coun
          tess.
          Married "Flossie, the Fuss."
          Harry Thaw estranged himself from
          his family when he married eighteen
          months ago Evelyn Nesbitt, the beau
          tiful model, known among her girl
          friends as "Flossie, the Puss." The
          marriage was denied and confirmed and
          denied again and then reconfirmed.
          Pittsburg society was shocked. With
          the earl of Yarmouth in the family, tho
          Thaws did not relish the alliance of
          the eldest son, with his income of $80,-*
          000, to a girl whose only fortune was
          a beautiful figure and face.
          There never was any doubt that Harrv
          Thaw was desperately in love and wtw
          headstrong enough to go his own way.
          He concealed his marriage as long as he
          oould and when concealment became no
          longer possible he became defiant, fol
          lowing a threap from Pittsburg that
          his income was to be cut to $2,500 a
          year.
          The marriage was celebrated at Paris
          in October, 1904. On Nov. 1 Thaw and
          his bride arrived in New York on tho
          Kaiser William II. Immediately after
          coming ashore Thaw denied positively
          that he had married. He went to a hotel
          and engaged a suito of apartments for
          himself and a man servant, a maid
          and a lady." The ladv was his bride.
          The proprietor of the hotel declined to
          {0
          o^Lii ou the part of some, but at
          all these the architect laughed.
          GQOD WORD FOR WHITE
          Theatrical Manager Defends Architect's
          4^5 Character^'
          Chicago, June 26.George W. Led
          erer, manager of the Colonial theater
          in this ctiy, who was the employer of
          Mrs. Thaw when
          assaid
          erml
          wTongs to his
          the young Pittsburg millionaire
          register with ner except as Harry
          Thaw and wife.
          Society Was Offish.
          Thaw refused to do this and went
          and took rooms in the hotel apart from
          those of his bride. She denied the mar
          riage the next day and so again did
          Thaw, but eventually it was admitted.
          Then came an effort to placate Pitts
          burg society. Mrs. William Thaw, tho
          she had bitterly opposed tho union,
          bent all her energies to have hor son's
          wife recognized.
          The "newly rich" in Pittsburg did
          their best to snub and humiliate the
          bride and bridegroom. Mrs. Thaw's
          ?astor
          Evelyn she
          the stage todaNesbitt tha he
          went onn
          _ __ [believed that the interest takra in her
          6aw that fat scoundrel Bitting there, I career by White was merely that of a
          big and healthy ami then 3 5ftw her and^sfood friend who desired to see her ad-
          how she was. vanced in her prof ession.
          3&amp;Evelyn Nesbit Thaw vanityU soon
          "Whit was one of the finest men
          Rev. William L. McEwan of the
          hird Presbyterian church, had married
          Eleanor Colwin, who had been his ste
          nographer. Mrs. Thaw, besides giving
          a most handsome wedding' present, sug
          gested to her pastor that it would be
          nice for her to give a double reception
          when the pastor and his bride returned
          from their tripf
          "Double receptionf'" echoed the Rev.
          Mr. McEwan. To whom 1
          "To Mrs. McEwan and inv daughter
          in-law, Mrs. Harfv Kendall Thaw, who
          is a recent bride*" said lrs, William
          Thaw. i.A
          This double reception waft not held.
          How Rev. Mr. McEwan extricated him
          self has never been made'' known. Some
          years ago, ReV. Mr. McEwan had a
          birthday party and Mrs. Thaw was 4he
          first one invitedw She attended and
          left as a birthday present a check for
          $3,000.
          It cannot be said that the lepprted re
          fusal of the pasfor to allow jlia wife
          to take part in a double -reception in
          jured the chances of the young bride.
          THE MURDERED MAN
          Stanford White Had Won Foremost
          Place in His Profession.
          New York, June 26. Stanford
          White was born in New York in 1852.
          A public school boy, he graduated from
          New York university and then studied
          architecture under Charles D. Gam
          brill and Henry H. Richardson. In
          ^878 he went to Europe, and spent three
          'years in study. In 1881 he entered into
          partnership with Charles F. McKim
          and William R. Mead. Their business
          association has continued until the
          present.
          In his home, tho old Moses Taylor
          house at Lexington avenue and
          Gramercy Park, Mr. White had many
          beautiful and rich objects of art, not
          least of which was an antique statue
          of Venus Genitrix, recovered from the
          bed of the Tiber, over which he had
          fought and won a conflict with the cus
          toms authorities.
          He was a large stockholder in the
          Madison Square Garden company. For
          years the enterprise did not pay ex
          penses. White from the beginning said
          it would grow up, and he was rewarded
          for his faith by seeing the first divi
          dends in 1903. Mr. White was a mem
          ber of the Knickerbocker, Automobile,
          Metropolitan, Players, Lambs and New
          York Yacht clubs. His wife was Miss
          Bessie Smith.
          Had Studio in Tower.
          Mr. White had a studio or snuggery
          in the Madison Square Garden, which
          looks down upon the scene of his death.
          The tower itself is one of White's most
          celebrated pieces of work, and he, as
          an architect, had at the age of 53, come
          to be accepted as one of the foremost
          men in his profession in this country.
          "Diana's chums" people called the
          three men who dwelt in the tall tower
          whose lines were adapted by White
          from those of a famous old Spanish edi
          fice. Peter Cooper Hewitt makes his
          experiments there, in a cold, greenish
          electric light made in a mercury vapor
          in vacuum. Duffield Osborne, the au
          thor, wrote several of his books in the
          tower. One or the other on rare occa
          sions has given dinners or entertain
          ments there which society has always
          been glad to attend.
          White had a way of making his par
          ties chic and far out of the ordinary.
          His studio, one big room occupying
          all of the area of a section of the
          tower left by the elevator shaft, except
          for a bathroom and a kitchen, was one
          of the most artistically furnished in
          teriors to be seen anywhere, and every
          bit of ornament or decoration was
          something of value and rarity.
          Madison Square's Architect.
          Stanford White was proud of Madi
          son Square Garden, which he made over
          from the unsightly old Harlem railroad
          freight depot used for many years as an
          amusement hall. He made it one of the
          show sights of the city, and MacMon
          nies, the sculptor, made the statue of
          Diana, which, poised at the top -of the
          graceful weather vane, is regarded as
          a sort of a guardian divinity of the
          metropolis.
          White's other famous works in town
          are the hall of fame at New York uni
          versity the University and Metropoli
          tan clubs: the Washington arch, the
          Century club, William C7 Whitney resi
          dence at Sixty-ninth street and Fifth
          avenue, now owned by James Henry
          Smith the Freundschaft club, White
          law Reid's magnificent country house.
          Ophir farm, in Westchester county, and
          the pedestal of the Farraguet statue in
          Madison Square.
          PITTSBURG EXCITED
          Minister Who Married Young Thaw
          Almost Swoons.
          Pittsburg, June 26.The news that
          Harry Thaw had killed Stanford White
          last night caused the wildest excitement
          in Pittsburg, where for years the Thaws
          have been the great social leaders.
          The only one closely connected with
          the Thaw family who could be reached
          last night was Rev. W. L. McEwan,
          pastor of the Third Presbyterian church
          of Pitttsburg, who, on April 4, 1905,
          married Harry Kendall Thaw to Flor
          ence Evelyn Nesbit. Mr. McEwan,
          when called out of bed and told of the
          tragedy, almost swooned.
          "Oh, this is awful, awful," he cried,
          "and he was a young man of such
          promise and such opportunities. I never
          thought this would come when I mar
          ried that couple in my study more than
          a year ago. It is awful."
          Mrs. Charles J. Holman, mother of
          Mrs. Harry Kendall Thaw, who lives
          at Brookhne, a suburb of this city,
          was apprised early today of the shoot
          ing. Mrs. Holman listened to a re
          cital of the tragedy, but beyond ask*
          ing a few questions as to further de
          tils, said little.
          She said she did not know Stanford
          White, the dead architect, had, in fact,
          never heard of him, and that she did
          not know what she was going to do
          regarding the matter. The information
          came in the nature of a distinct shock
          to her. She was naturally unprepared
          to hear of an accident in which her
          daughter's husband cut so tragic a fig
          ure.
          The shooting came as a distinct
          shock to the Thaw family in Pittsburg
          and was a matter for discussion today
          in all prominent clubs and homes in
          the two cities. All efforts to find a
          member of the family in this city have
          proved fruitless,.
          Mrs. Thaw was not in the best of
          health when she left the city, and it
          is feared the news will have a serious
          effect on her condition. She will prob
          ably start home at once.
          After his return from Europe and his
          marriage, he purchased a fine piece of
          property in Fifth avenue and it was
          said that it was his intention to put
          up a handsome home. One of the re-
          Ead
          orts current here today was that Thaw
          had some talk with the man killed
          relative to some of the architectural
          features of the new house.
          Mrs. Thaw Not Arrested.
          New York, June 26. After a
          consultation between Mr. Delafleld
          and Assistant District Attorney
          Nott this afternoon, it was announced
          that Mrs. Harry K. Thaw had been in
          communication with her husband's
          counsel and that she would appear any
          time her presence is desired. Mr. Nott
          said it was possible that Mrs. Thaw
          might be called for examination this
          afternoon, but that she might not be
          summoned until tomorrow. A subpena
          will be issued for her at once, how
          ever, and she will be kept under sub
          pena as long as the district attorney's
          office feels that her presence in the
          case may be needed.
          As the -witnesses at the inquest com
          plete their evidence they will be taken
          before the grand jury to repeat their
          testimony.
          Indictment Thursday.
          It is expected that Thaw will be
          indicted on Thursday.
          Mr. Delafleld informed Mr. Nott that
          the defense would rely on the insanity
          plea to answer the charge, and acting
          on this information, Mr. Nott sum
          moned three alienists. Dr. Austin Flint,
          Dr. Carlos F. MacDonald and Dr. Wil
          liam Mabon, who conferred with Po
          lice Captain Hodgins and several of
          the witnesses of the tragedy, ascertain
          ing from them the exact manner in
          which Thaw acted both before and af
          ter the shooting.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062224/1907-04-12/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=harry+thaw&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.102,0.135,0.588,0.588,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ÏAM0ÜS CASE NEAR AN END
          _
          trial of Harry 1C Thaw for the mur
          der of Stanford White will have been
          written into history. With an ora
          DELMAS' PLEA
          TO SAVE THAW
          Appeals to ''Unwritten Law" and
          Lauds Prisoner as Hero.
          New York, April 10.—One more day
          and the concluding chapters of ths

          torlcal appeal to both the written and!
          tha "unwritten law" for the Justifies

          tlon of bis client, Delphin M. Delmas,
          the California lawyer, concluded his
          exhaustive summing up address to the
          Jury. District Attorney Jerome will!
          close In a three or four hour address
          and Is expected to make a plea which I
          will be accounted one of the best ef-l
          Justice Fitzgerald 1
          not he i
          feste of bis life.
          would not say whether
          the directly follow i
          or
          lag the district attorney's closing re
          marks, but the general Impression is
          that he will do so. In this event thers
          seems little doubt that the case will
          be turned over to the Jury by this
          (Tuesday) evening.
          With the exceptions of moments
          when he was reading from testimony
          Mr. Delmas speech was one of sus
          tained oratorical effort He threw
          about the form of Harry Thaw the
          cloak of chivalrous knighthood.
          "Why," he shouted, "should we who
          admire the chivalry of the knights ot
          the middle ages who went about re
          dressing wrongs and rescuing maidens
          In distress, withhold our sympathy
          from this brave man?"
          Bitterly Denounces White.
          Bitterly the attorney again assailed
          Stanford White. He declared White
          aought to play with the girl so long i
          as her beauty remained and then j
          would have thrown her away "like a
          dirty rag to float down life's sewers j
          to a grave in the Potter's Field.'' i
          Again ho said "Harry Thaw had
          snatched the girl from the old lecher
          who saw In her but a toy to gratify i
          a moment's lust and then be cast aside I
          to go her way down the paths of fall- 1
          en women." I
          f ^Oith dramatic emphasis Mr. Del- j
          mas cried out that when Harry Thaw
          beheld Stanford White on the Madi
          son Square roof garden the story of his
          wlfe's wrongs overcame him. He pic
          tured in an Instant_as a dying man
          Stanford White had done—"the ruin
          he had wrought, and he struck; struck
          as tho tigress strikes In defense of her
          young; struck for the home, struck
          for American womanhood, struck for
          humanity and Stanford White fell."
          "Ah. gentlemen the advocate went
          on, "If Harry Thaw believed he was
          thé Instrument of Providence, who will
          say he was mistaken?"
          Mr, Delmas discussed but briefly tha
          testimony of the expert witnesses, de
          vlarlng that whatever weight might
          attach to their utterances was on tha
          He declared
          side of the defendant
          the burden ot proof as to Thaw's san
          ity at the time of the homicide rested
          with the prosecution, which had failed
          to make out its case.
          It was In discussing Thaw's mental
          state that Mr. Delmas came at last to
          the "unwritten law." He declared the

          experts had been at a loss to classify
          the form of Insanity from which Thaw
          suffered.
          "Dementia Americana."
          "I will suggest Its name," he declar
          ed. "I would call It 'Dementia Ameri
          cana.' It Is a species of Insanity
          which has been recognized In every
          state of this union. It Is that species
          of Insanity which makes the American
          man believe his home, his wife, his
          daughters, are sacred, and that who
          soever stains the virtue of his thresh
          old violates the highest of human law."
          Bringing into play all the eloquence
          at his command, Delmas pictured the j
          martyrdom of Evelyn Nesblt when she j
          refused the hand of Thaw and the
          broken heart of Harry when his offer j
          of marriage was spurned.
          He drew In almost glaring colors ths
          storm that was gathering in "the four
          comers of the clouded horizon," when
          Evelyn told Harry that "because sh«
          loved him, because she did not want to
          see the finger of scorn pointed at him,
          because she would not tear him from
          his noble mother and dear sisters, be
          cause she did not want to tie her un
          fortunate existence to his, because she
          wanted to go back and make her own
          living and go down in the world where
          so many, many others had gone be
          fore her, and disappear from his life
          forever, she, Evelyn Nesblt, could not
          become the wife ot Harry Kendall
          Thaw."
          This sacrifice he characterized as
          "sublime renunciation," and to it he
          attributed the restlessness which soon
          thereafter became manifest In the con
          duct of Thaw.
          Mr. Dolmas had no hesitation In call
          tng Evelyn "an angel child," and Harry
          Thaw "a noble, honorable lover, with
          only one purpoeo, to make Evelyn Nes
          bit, the little girl he loved, his hon
          ormble wife."
          Calls Hummel a Perjurer.
          That Evelyn Nesblt'* story was true
          and was told to Harry Thaw formed
          the subject of the argument for more i
          than an hour. Mr. Delmas declared
          the only evidence the district attorney
          had to bring against the girl was the
          "miscalled affidavit" procured by Abra
          ham Hummel. Speaking of Hummel
          Mr. Delmas again drew heavily upon
          his bitterest Invective and declared
          that It would require more than the
          word of a perjured man to send Harry
          Thaw to an ignominious death. Hum
          mel was accused by Mr. Delmas of
          having committed deliberate perjury
          upon tho stand in the present trial

          when he swore he was not acting as
          atclyn Nesblt's counsel and that no
          actios was contemplated In her behalf.
          |«e said the so-called affidavit Itself
          i^nvlcted the man of these falsehoods.
          He denounced Hummel as a man ready
          I to commit crime for money.
          All of Thaw's family were in the
          court room. They sat unmoved as
          usual throughout the course of Mr.
          Delmas' argument, their features be
          traying no emotion. Thaw turned to
          them from time to time as his attor
          *ey seemed to strike soma telling
          blow. Thaw also turned frequently to
          bis wife, who seemed to be standing
          the brunt of the storm. She had a re
          Bponslve Bm ii 8 ready for his every
          District Attormoy Jerome was not in
          court tQ hear Mr Delmas Bp8 ech. Mr.
          Jerome, It was said, was busy with
          the p repara tion of his own address,
          Humor That Mrs. Thaw Had Given
          Son's Wife $250,000 Is Denied,
          Pittsburg. April 9.-"The statement
          that Mrs William Thaw has or had
          settled $250,000 on Mrs. Harry K.
          NO SETTLEMENT ON EVELYN
          Thaw Is untrue and might be charac
          terlssd by even sponger language,
          said Prank Sample, financial agent of
          Mrs. William Thaw.
          "Mrs. Thaw has not settled $250,000
          or any other sum on Mrs. Harry K.
          Thaw, and so far as I know she has no
          Intention of so doing. These rumors,
          which seem to arise when other af
          fairs In connection with the case are
          dull, are very annoying to Mrs. Thaw
          and the rest of the family, and I hope
          this denial will settle the matter."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96060002/1913-08-25/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=harry+thaw</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THAW ESCAPES
          FROM ASYLUM
          THAW IS AT LARGE.
          MATTKAWAN, N. V., Aug. IS.
          Harry Thaw, slayer of Stanford
          White, who lias spent the greater
          part of his time in the state h s
          pita! for the trim Hal insane since
          his convict ion, made his escape fr m
          the institution on Sunday and is
          still at liberty. The dash for liberty
          evidently was prearranged, for when
          Thaw reached the 'gate there was
          an automobile waiting for him and
          he was soon out of reach of his
          irsuers. He is believed to have
          crossed tiie state line in which
          event there is no law under which
          lie can be returned t the aslyum.
          Tile asylum officials are of the
          opinion that Thaw received assist
          ance from some of the employes of
          the nstitulion and it is probable
          that an investigation will he held
          immediately.
          ROSTOV Mass., Aug. is. The
          report is in circulation here that
          I lurry Thaw is in hiding somewhere
          in the lierksh re hills. No steps
          lave neon taken l»y the state au
          ihoritie.-. however, t ascertain the
          troth of tlie rumor.
          I'm GliKKKI'SIK, X. Y Aug. IS.
          Howard Itanium, the attendant
          who opened the gate through which
          Thaw passed to liberty, lias been
          arraigned on the charge of having
          accepted a bribe to release the no
          torious prisoner. Ilarnum stoutly
          asserts bis innocence, denying that
          it was lie who was at the .gate at
          the time.
          XKW YORK. Aug IS Mrs. Mary
          Copely Thaw m liter of the escaped
          prisoner, lias received a letter from
          lnr son In which he says that lie
          will go immediately to Klmhurst.
          the Thaw summer home in 1’ennsyl
          vatCa. She is planning to leave for
          there tonight.
          XKW YORK. Aug. IS. The offi
          i ers of three states are now en
          gaged In the search for Thaw but
          tints far no trace of him lias been
          found.
          MOXTRKAH, Canada, Aug. IS.-
          The police of tills city are keping
          a sharp lookout for Harry Thaw upon
          suspicion that he has crossed the
          line into Canada. If captured, he
          will be deported.
          XKW YORK, Aug. IS.—Hr. Carlos
          McDonald, the eminent alienist, says
          that Thaw undoubtedly is incurable
          and too dangerous to be at large.
          He says the moment lie starts dr lik
          ing his mind diverts to delusons
          that he is being persecuted, at which
          times he ig a menace to society.
          ITfTSIU'RG, I’a., Aug. IS.—Roger
          O'Mara Harry Thaw’s guardian, says
          that he is glad his ward escaped, and
          he expresses the hope that lie will
          not be recaptured.
          ALBANY, X. Y., Aug. 18.—Lieu
          tenant-Governor Glynn announces
          that lie will probe the Mattcawan
          cscaire immediately.
          COATICOOK, Quebec, Aug. 19.
          White, who escaped on Sunday from
          Wh to, who scaped on Sunday from
          the Xew York state hospital for the
          crimina’ 'tisane at Matteawan, was
          taken into custody in this city today
          as he was passing through on the
          train, onr ute to Montreal. He was
          taken immediately to Sherbrooke,
          where he is now confined in tlie
          county ja l awaiting deportation un
          der tlie law wh'ch provides that
          any person, a resident of a foreign
          country, can be deported if he has
          been out of prison or an asylum
          oniv a short time.
          The arrest waa made at the in
          slant r of Sheriff Iv 1-*a who warn
          etl the local officers to he on the
          lookout for the esc aped Anteri« an
          When Thaw was taken front the
          train, he stoutly denied his identity,
          but letters were found on his per
          son addressed to Harry Thaw and
          he was held tint his Idem ty was
          fully established, after which lit* was
          taken to Sherbrooke.
          PlTTSHl RG. Pa.. Aug 13. liar
          ry 'I haw. who is now in ctistoday in
          Sherltr oke. Quebec. has tt‘legraplu*d
          his mother requesting that money
          in* sent to him immediately in or
          br that in may fight deportation.
          NKW YORK. Aug. 19.-—Until the
          arrest of in r son in Canada this
          afternoon. Mrs Thaw was unaware
          of ’lit* whereabouts of the t s. aped
          Matteawan prisoner. It is believed
          that sin* will go at once to Sher
          brooke to assist him in resisting the
          attempt which will be made to send
          him back t this state.
          OTTAWA. Canada. Aug. 19 Sit
          pfrintent Stott of the depart
          ment of immigration, has issued in
          sinnt.ons to the otficials at Sher
          brooke directing them to take Thaw
          io some point oil the New York
          state boundary and there deliver
          him over to the American authori
          ties.
          NKW YORK. Aug. 19. The two
          men who were taken int custody
          with Harry Thaw on suspicion that
          they had ass sled in his escape were
          released this afternoon by the Can
          adian authorities. No charge was
          •■ntered against them.
          SHKRHIvOOK K. Quebec. Aug. 2u.
          —Harry Thaw won his first pout
          today in his fight against deporta
          lion to the United States. Upon
          his arrival here yesterday, he ap
          peal'd immediately to the court for
          a writ of Habeas corpus and was
          granted a preliminary order, which
          was made returnable at lit "clock to
          morrow morning The escaped pris
          oner of Matteawan is elateii over
          bis victory, and is confident lie will
          l*o able to defeat the plans of the
          Amer can officials, w ltoni be accuses
          of conspiring with the Canadian of
          tic als to effect it is return to New
          York state.
          AKUANY. N Y. Aug. 20.—As
          sistant Attorney-General Kennedy of
          the state of New A" rk started for
          Sherhr ok,- this afternoon to repre
          sent the state in the effort which
          is being made to secure Thaw's de
          portation from Canada.
          ROCHKSTKK. N. H„ Aug. 20.
          Governor Felker has informed the
          New A ork State officials that he
          will turn Harry Thaw over to them
          immediately in case the escaped pris
          oner sets toot in New Hampshire.
          The Canadian unclary is now being
          patrolled by American officers, and
          Thaw will be taken into custody the
          moment he crosses the line.
          ORKSSOX, Ca.. Aug. 20.— M/Ts.
          Mary Copely Thaw, mother of Harry
          Thaw, is heartbroken over the re
          capture of her soil, who was taken
          into custody yesterday at Coat cook.
          Quebec, soon after he had er ssed
          the international bolnindary. It is
          understood that Mrs. Thaw has ad
          vanced money for her son's defense.
          SHKRBROOKK. Quebec. Aug. 21.
          The Thaw habeas corpus proceed
          ings. wh cli were to have been taken
          up this morning, have hen post
          poned until next Wednesday. The
          postponement will enable the escaped
          Matteawan prisoner to secure legal
          talent from the States and to fur
          ther prepare his light against de
          le nation.
          Public sentiment in this country
          apparently is with Thaw. It is un
          derstood that several offers of finan
          cial assitance have been made by
          Canadians who desire to help the
          esepi i.il prisoner defeat the plans
          of iiis cantors.
          ALBANY, X. Y., Aug. 21.—Ac
          cording to advices received today
          from Canada, the officials of that
          country will do what they can to
          turn Thaw over to the New York
          state auth rities.
          WASHINGTON. 1>. C„ Aug. 21.—
          Sec rear, el Slate Bryan It a wired
          British Ambassador Rice, informing
          him that the United States govern
          ment will leave the Thaw ease en
          tirely in the hands of the Canadian
          authorit es for settlement in what
          ever manner they deem lust.
          SiHCRBROOKR, Quebec Aug. 21.—
          Late this afternoon Harry Thaw
          scored his second victory over the
          attorneys for the prosecution, who
          made in unsuccessful attempt to se
          cure the escaped Matteawan prison
          er's discharge from the cust d.v of
          the court in order that they might
          i :i i ry oi tlieii deportat on plats.
          SIIKKISROOKK, Quebec, Aug. 22.
          The government physician who liu.s
          hail Harry Thaw under surveillance
          suce his arrival here states that
          there is nothing whatever wrong
          mentally with the escaped Matlea
          wan prisoner. He says he has sub
          jected Thaw to a rigid examination
          and is thoroughly satisfied that the
          mind of the prisoner is sound.
          Thaw’s attorney is urging IPs cli
          ent to become a Canadian and pur
          chase property in this country. He
          claims that if Thaw will do that it
          will lie impossible f r the authori
          ties to deport him.
          It is understood that Thaw’s broth
          er- 11-law, (leorge Carnegie, has a
          private yacht in Canadian waters
          ready to lake Thaw to Virginia the
          moment he is released from custody
          here.
          NEW YORK, Aug. 22.—It is re
          ported here today that arrangements
          have been made by the state officials
          to stati n a number of officers along
          the northern boundary of the state
          in readiness to receive Thaw from
          the Canadian authorities, the latter
          having prom sed to deport their pris
          oner across the New York line.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-stories-by-mark-twain</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85026241/1866-05-10/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens&amp;r=-0.186,0.044,0.569,0.304,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mark Twain, in I -Iter to the Virftini
    Citr Enterprise, deicri'iss aorua of the inoi
    dent of thi teceal pleasure tiip of the
    t'eatner Ajat to tho Sandwich Islands.
    Tbs following is excruciatingly laughable:
    Iw'n LolanJ, proprietor of the Oroidci!
    Ul llstel, was paaiin-rr. The-ro were
    one sasage) griizly boar chained in cage
    on deck. thia night in tha mi 1st of a bur
    risen, which was aecrimranird by rsin ind
    thuadar and lichtuiti.r. Mr. Lelimd came up
    a his way to beJ. Jut as lie stepped wto
    tho pitohv darkness of the dec k, ami reeled
    to the still more pilchy rnolinn nf tlio fessel,
    tho Captain sang out hcarn-ly tlirnuiih his
    speaking-trumpet, "Bear hund alt. there!"
    The words were sadly marred and jumbled
    by the roaring wind. Mr. Liland thought
    tho Captain said, "The bears nre alter you,
    there I "and ho "lot go all holts" and went
    down into his boots. II t murmured, I
    katw how it was en'mn to be I Jut know
    it from the start I said all along that those,
    baars wiuld get I.tose somo time, and nnw
    I'll bo the first man they'll snitch. Cm -tain
    I Captain 1ran't hoar me torm
    roars so. Ob, God, what a Tate I I have
    avoided wild beasts all in v lil, and nnw to
    he eaten by a grittly hoar in tho. mid lln of
    tho ocean, a thmcand mile from Intel I
    Captain I Captain I Oli. Captain I blda
    my aonl, there' nno nf thorn. I'vn rot to
    cut and rin I Ai l hn did out and run,
    and samhe 1 throijuh ihn dunr nf tlio firt
    tato-rootn ha caw to. A r"ritt"rn in and
    his wife woro in it. Tim fnlli'ii.an ex
    claimed, ''Win's t.hit'?" Tlie rul'iK'ou
    gaspsd out, "Oh. grfat Scotland. lb(- heir
    ro looso, and just ruiiin tnorrv b''ll all
    over theshipl" and then sunk down oxlmu it
    1. The gentleman sprang nut r.f l td and
    locked the dnor, and prenarad Hit a sine.
    After while, no a.m't boing mi l'1, a
    reeoDaoissanaa was tnadn frnm the window,
    ad a vivid flaah nf lightning revealed a
    elear deck. Mr. Leland then ma In a dart
    far bis nwn state room, gained it. Ii krd
    himself in, and felt thst his hndv's asla
    vatiun was acoomplihhed, ami hv littlii les
    than tuiracle. Now I bare told this story
    as I heard it, from a passenger, who suid he
    wou'd vouch for evory part of it exoept the
    language, whioh is stronger than Mr. La
    land over indulged in. The next diiy tho
    subject of thix'metunir. thniuh still very
    feeble and nervottn. had tho hardihood t
    Make np a joke nn his adventure. Tie said
    that when he found himself in so tight a
    plies (as ho thought) he didn't boar it with
    much f'r!ituds. and when ho fonnd binimlf
    aate at. last in his state-ronin, ho regarded it
    as the besret naeip, he had ever had in
    his life. lie then went to bed and did not
    list op again for nine days. This unques
    tionably bad joke cist a glnom over the
    whole ship's company, and no effort wis
    sufficient to restore their wonted cheerful
    ness until the vkso readied her port, and
    other scenes erased it from their memories.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86079096/1867-03-09/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.086,0.301,1.363,1.363,0</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mark Twain, in the Akls GaliM ian
    tells the following entertai.ghlt yrof
    the Bcriptural panoramas
    Theb w'a a fellow travelig in that
    Upentry with a moral rein s 1-a
    wrt of a criptiir;1 par: Mea
    hired a woodea-head old e~ab, to play the
    piane forhim- After t ise~ i 'a per
    formancaes the showman sidt :PJMy friend
    'seem to .sow prbt lymeb ll tHthe
    tania and yout worry anleg Ars rite.
    But then did'nt you *otIe as ometimes
    ,Jayt aight, the piece ,ase etagened
    to be,pla is,g was plitl tough up, 4h
    so,. 7 t c idfet rpttl, gg) p'to
    that, w pis uig, athb tiure, as t wer
    ---as you did'at&amp;follow suit nor tramsp, you
    understand."''
    Well, no," thb fJllow'said. "dfe iad
    u't :otice4 it, hbt it mighlt Is bpplasy
    4d along just as it eamre."
    to they iput it up so tbat dt th iinple
    old dummy wrA to keLp 'eiftk etfl tshe
    picture after that, aind so 0oon s aptorn
    ning picture rolled out, "e. was oi1fit it
    to a dot with a piecef -ideelb tht woeIld
    help the audience 'to ge:smI Idr Nll.c."
    uabj et sand wartrtherpikkee a camp
    ne.ting revival. That sfbtM:ifti~'ould
    corral' thelr aympatnp lea; the taowsman
    said,
    There was a big e'P p; putl at
    ofglt-mosly middle-gp abd ol er
    pl, who belonged to -thw h*ti idbk
    a strong interest fi Bibl id t~ i f
    balance were yonurg buctr-nk he r.
    they wi latus a rime ri`sas oe t trn'
    ma you hkow, "bemeousalt t i h ae
    shoopc tI isis n,,aswherar. muagpdi4
    Wel1, the ho so
    .if up for thig Ire,.
    dobber taetltPthe j d
    agertsip an id down;ja oaerse e i
    that she w as all right, w h d e u t wlout
    hind the curtai rgmutv +~u i Eautw
    pietraes. TIa, b ie
    warigh so his rigtli* aa--
    hand, on hie hijia1p ý
    .tbfiehery, a4d' ~auds
    La d L tli nt so 'ti it
    Scm. Observe he
    ieg otier t
    ii·;lmgtty dataC~
    Borne o!
    groane sd
    or -n
    loot o
    'I
    ba/t t K s as
    t"</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84038034/1867-05-24/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Curing: a. Cold.
          Sir. Mark Twain gives Lis experience in
          curing his cold in so quaint and unique a
          style, that we copy it in full lor the bencftC
          ol' our readers
          It is a good thing, perhaps, to write for
          the amusement of the puMic, but it is afar
          higher and nobler thing to write for their
          instruction, their profit, their actual and
          tangible benefit. The latter is the sole object
          of this article. If it prove the means of re
          storing to health one solitary sufferer
          among my race, oflighting up occe more
          the fire of hope and joy in his faded eyes, of
          Dnnging dock to his eieaü heart again the
          quick, generous impulses of other days, I
          ball lie amply rewarded for my labor my
          soul will be permeated with the sacred de
          light a Christian feels when he has done a
          good, unselfish deeeL
          Having led a pure and blameless life, I
          am justified, in believing that no man who
          knows me will reject the suggestions I am
          about to make, out of fear that I am try
          ing to deceive him Let the public do itself
          the honor to read my experience in doctor
          ing a cold, as herein set forth, and then fol
          low in my footsteps.
          When the White House was burned in
          Virginia, I lost my home, my happiness, my
          constitution and my trunk. The loss of the
          two first named articles vas a matter of no
          great consequence, since a home without a
          mother or a sister, or a distant young female
          relative in it, to remind you, by putting
          your soiled linen out of sight, and taking
          your boots down off the mantle-piece, that
          there are thoe who think about you and
          care for you, is easily obtained. And I
          cared nothing for the loss of my happiness,
          because, not being a poet, it could not be
          possible that melancholy would abide with
          me long.
          But to lose a good constitution and a bet
          ter trunk were serious misfortunes.
          On the day of the fire, my constitution
          succumbed to a severe cold caused by undue
          exertion in getting ready to do something.
          I suffered to no purpose, too, because the
          plan I was figuring at for the extinguishing
          of the fire was so elaborate, that 1 never
          got it completed until the middle of the
          following week.
          The first time I began to sneeze, a friend
          told me to go and bathe my feet in hot water
          and go to bed. I did so. Shortly after
          ward, another tnend advised me to get up
          and take a cold shower bath. 1 did that
          also. ltmn tne nour another mend as
          sured me that it was policy to 'feed a cold
          and starve a fever. I had both. So I
          thought it best to fill myself up for a cold,
          and then keep dark and let the fever starre
          awhile.
          In a case of this kind, I seldom do things
          by halves I ate petty heartily I conferred
          my custom upon a stranger who had just
          opened his restaurant that nioruinr; he
          waited near me in respectful silence until I
          Jiad nnisned leeding my cold, wnen he in
          quired if the people about Virginia were
          much afflicted with colds I told him I
          thought they were. I le then went out, and
          took in his sim. I started down toward
          the office, and on the way encountered an
          other bosom friend, who told me that a
          quart of 6alt water, taken wann, would
          come as near curing a cold as anything in
          the world. I hardly thought I had ro 'in
          for it, but I tried it anyhow. Tbe lesult
          was surprising, l Delieve 1 threw up my
          immortal soul.
          Now, as I am nvinr my experience only
          lor the benefit of those who are troubled
          with the distemper I am writing about,
          feel that they will see the propriety of my
          cautioning- them against following1 such
          portions of it as proved inefficient with me.
          and acting upon this conTiction, I warn
          them against warm fait water. It may be
          a good enough remedy, but I thick it is too
          severe. If I had another cold in the head,
          and there were no course left rue but to take
          euner an earxnquaice or a quart or warm
          salt water, I would take my chances on the
          earthquake.
          Aiter tue storm which had been raging
          in my stomach had subsided, and no more
          good Samaritans happening along, I went
          on borrowing handkerchiefs again and
          blowing them to atoms, as had been my
          custom in the earlv stages of my cold, un
          til I came across a lady who had just arriv
          ed from over the plain?, and who said she
          had lived in a part of the country where
          doctors were scarce, and had from necessity
          acquired considerable skill in the treatment
          of simple 'family complaints.' I knew she
          ihusi nave naa uuen experience, ior snerp-
          peared to be a hundred and fifty ycar3 old.
          She mixed a decoction composed of mo
          lasse, aqua fortis, turpentine and various
          other drugs, and instructed me to take
          wine-glass full of it every fifteen minutes.
          I took but one dose; that was enough
          it robbed me of all moral principle, and
          awoke every unworthy impulse of my
          nature. Under its malign influence my
          brain conceived miracles of meanness, but
          my hands were too feeble to execute them
          at that tune, had it not been that my
          strength had surrendered to a succession of
          assault from infallible remedies for my
          cold, I am satisfied that I would have tried
          to rob the Graveyard.
          Like most other people I often feel mean.
          and act accordingly but, until I took that
          medicine, I had never revelled in such
          supernatural depravity and felt proud of iL
          At the end of two days I was ready to go to
          uoewnug ui. a wo m lew more uniail-
          ing remedies, and finally drove my cold
          from my head to my lungs.
          I got to coughing incessantly, and my
          voice fell below zero I conversed in a
          thundering bass, two octaves below my na
          tural tone I could only compass mv rcgu
          lar nightly repose by coughing myself
          uown to a state oi utter exhaustion, ami
          then the moment I began to talk in my
          sleep, my discordant voice woke me up
          again.
          My case grew more and more serious
          evervday. Plain gin was recommended
          I took it. Then gin and r"lasses; I took
          that also. Then gin and ouious 1 added
          the onions, and took all three. I detected
          no particular result, however, except that
          I had acquired a breath like a buzzard's.
          I found I had to travel for my health. I
          went to Lake Bigler with my reportorial
          comrade, Wilson. It is gratifying to me to
          reflect that we traveled in considerable
          style we went in the Pioneer coach, and
          my friend took all his baggage with him,
          consisting of two excellent silk handker
          chiefs, and a daguerreot pe of his grand
          mother. We sailed and hunted and fished
          and danced all day, and I doctored my
          cough all night. By managing in this way,
          I made out to improve every hour iu the
          twenty-four, lint my disease continued to
          grow worse.
          A sheet bath wa9 recommended. I had
          never refused a remedy yet, and it seemed
          poor policy to commence then; there-tore,
          1 determined to take a sheet bath, notwith
          standing I had no idea What sort of an ar
          rangement it v is.
          It was administered at midnight, and the
          weather was very frosty. My "breast and
          back were bared, and a sheet (there ap
          peared to be a thousand yards of it) soaked
          in ice water was wound round me until I
          resembled a swab for a Columbiad.
          It is a cruel expedient. When the chilly
          rag touches one's warm flesh, it makes him
          start with sudden violence and gasp for
          breath just as men do in the death agony.
          It froze the marrow in my bones and
          stopned the beating of my heart. I thought
          my tune had come.
          loung llson said the circumstance re
          minded him of an anecdote about a negro
          who was being baptised, and who slipped
          from the parson's grasp, and came near be
          ing drowned. He floundered around,
          though, and finally rose up out of the
          water considerably strangled and furiously
          angry, and started ashore at once, spouting
          water like u whale, and remarking, with
          great asperity, that One o' these days
          some gen'lman's nigger gwyne to git killed
          wid jes' such dam foolishness as dis
          Never take a sheet bath never. Next
          to meeting a ladv acquaintance, who. for
          reasons best known to herself, don't see vou
          when she looks at you, and don't know you
          when she does see you, it is the most un
          comfortable thing in the wohl.
          But, as 1 was saying, when the sheet
          bath failed to cure my cough, a lady friend
          recommended the application of a mustard
          plaster to my breast. I bcüeve that would
          have cured me etlectuallv, if it had not
          been for young Wilson. When I went to
          bed, I put my mustard plaster which was
          very gorgeous one, eighteen inches
          square where I could reach it when I
          was ready for it. But young Wilson got
          hungry in the night, and ate it up. I never
          saw anybody have such an appetite I am
          confident that lunatic would have eaten me
          up if I had been healthy.
          Alter sojourning a week at Lake Bigler,
          went to Steaintxjat borings, and beside
          the steam baths, I took a lot of the vilest
          medicines that were ever concocted. They
          would have cured me, but I had to go back
          to Virginia, where, notwithstanding the
          variety of new remedies I absorbed every
          day, I managed to aggravate my disease by
          carelessness and undue exposure.
          I finally concluded to visit San Francis
          co, and the first day I got there a ladv at
          the Lick House told me to elrink a quart of
          whisky every twenty-four hours, and a
          mend- at the Occidental recommended pre
          cisely the same course. Each advised me
          to take a quart that made half a gallon. I
          did it, and still live.
          .Now, with the kindest motives in the
          world, I offer for the consideration of con
          sumptive patients the variegated course of
          treatment I have lately gone through. Lt
          them try it; if it don t rare them, it can't
          more than kill them.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85026241/1870-12-15/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens&amp;r=-0.01,0.5,0.458,0.245,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>A Humorous View of the Farmers' Club
          —Mark Twains Report of the Proceedings.
          loiss.
          [From the Buffalo Express.]
          Bx -Cons table Quinn d sired the club
          t'i inforni him bow to make bogs riot.
          Dr. Slow had bt;..n a practical farmer
          lor I i iast six weeks, and in sli his
          parted agricultural experience i.ostieh
          article as bog'a-Foat came under h
          notice: What was it? Was it edible?
          orasefulin any way? or was it, as he
          suspected, another worthless humbag
          devised by the sharpers to defraud as
          practical funnels? Ho kneW not whetbei
          it vas propagated by feeds oreottiags,
          bpt be would advise T.lr. Quiaa lo be
          shy of Bogd-r not, especially if it was a
          new langled or high-priced taber.
          Mr. Mokar, the agricallural writer,
          explaiaa A the anatomy of the bog's pro
          boscis. I; is designed for sul terrain an
          rbiaging, by process vulgarly called
          rooting to e-hiih Mr. Quinti's inquiiy
          probably it fund. H would recoas-.
          mend that Mr. Qui; n wipe l is bog's
          Doee. Ifbefindsil ed,fae tay be 8"ie
          it is tender a id needs protection by a
          loetaiiic shhrld. Some resort to lie
          Hralegic device of inserting a wire i'rg
          i i ne og's !.o-e,iu bis effima to remove
          which lie would naturally t It I list h'3
          sooui into'the soil, and tbns root nnv.il
          liogly. Thai was playing it rather I w i
          on Liae hog, and the metafile shield was!
          preferable on the score of fair flralingj
          and philanthropy.
          .Mr. Greeley exhibited a parapkin of
          l:U owa raising. As U embodied his
          solitary end crowning success, arter sev
          eral years of dianaaagiag raflate in
          pampkua caltare, the club surrounded
          it wiili uncovered heads and mingled
          emolicaa of surprise, admiration and
          envy. It was a superb fruit, and when
          Mr. &amp;e hat was placed on it, to iilus
          tiate Hs skmanO symetry, the bat ai d
          paoi! kin seemed BO perfectly "adapted
          to each other, and together produced an
          Bed so startling, that several enthusi
          BStio members sWom tlicy would have
          known who raised that pumpkin if 'hey
          bad seen ii anywhere. It is to be photo
          graphed by Cinney. a' d next year's
          Tribune subscribers will receive copies.
          The pumpkin was the flattering pro
          line! of one bushel of seed planted aoj
          the farm iu Chataqua. Soon after bios
          mming, the vine manifested an inclina
          tion to wither. I was thereupon trans
          j l.mied to a lar"e ilowerpotau.l remov
          ed to the town residence of its rounder.
          Por some time i: pined and droopedjmd
          they sat Bp nights with it, expecting
          that every ntomeut would he its last;
          but every moment turned oat not lobe;
          its last, and with careful nursing it fi
          nally rallied and same up to maturity,
          as cherished as tough a pumpkin as
          evergrew-
          Dr. Sixhamrner. suggested 'that the!
          result of itr. O'a. indomitabhs struggie
          with this pumpkin showed how every
          city family could provide itsilf with
          pumpkin pic. He hoped to see tbedsyl
          when every window si. I in every eJtj
          would oo adorned with huctifying I
          pumpkin j.-ols, and every workman's
          cottage embowered in pom kin vines.
          Thus. Dodd, of New Bampshire,
          .rri.es lo tire club that be is Qfty years
          old, infirm with consumption, baa
          laiye family, ten doiiais in money, and
          wanta to know what to do.
          Mr. alofcer Go out to Greeley Colony
          and invest in our Irrigating ditch.
          Mr. L-n man Buy a Texas reaohe or
          a Florida orange grove
          iir. Sliasbor His health requires llgh I
          fi'iinng in a braeiag climate. i,,-t bun
          start aa indigo phtntatiea in Alaska.
          Mr. Greeley He atuan't come to Ne
          York. His $10 wouldn't last a year
          tint out West be eau iavestit and grow
          u; with the eoautry. if i hud .(,iie
          West with $Wt hi age, 'should be a
          happy auut-uuw, with two suits of re
          spectable garments, an ollice, and a con
          science guiltless of distracting tariff
          an I farm"! ig essays
          Ux. Herring invited thedub-ro vMi
          his farm, t! i ty miles no i;,e river, I
          We cesdy. and inspect a horse radi'
          that he hud persuaded to vegetate. H'
          had expended upon that plant on ly
          i ton of bone dust, one cart load of ash
          s and a barrel of gurno; yet In spite i
          his neglect it Lad a niiin year git v. a
          to the stZr of his little linger. His fere
          man would exphuu to tbe clerk the
          cniiar diUiculiy of raising this iar exot
          ic" He would 11 cat b to a reglllill
          farmei's diu:'.er, the erialsfoi L:
          n.- had alrea iy engaged at lUs ciiy n ar
          kels.
          The club accept i a ad rned,</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038229/1872-06-14/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens&amp;r=0.733,0.024,0.273,0.146,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>PRIVATE HABITS OF GREELEY.
          Observed in 1867 by Marked Twain.
          An intimate acquaintance with a
          distant relative of the editor ot tie
          Tribune puts it into my power to
          furnish the public with the last
          positively the very last link neces
          sary to perfect the ccaia oi Knowl
          edge already, in its possession con
          cerning" Mr. Greeley: ;I mean his
          private habits. We know all about
          it as regards every other department
          of his life and services. Because,
          whenever a magazinist or a book
          maker is employed to write, and can
          not think of a subject, he writes
          about Horace Greeley.- Even the
          boys in the schools have quit build
          ing inspired "compositions about
          Ihe Horse," and have gone to do
          ing Horace Greeley instead; ana
          when declamation day comes around,
          their voices are no longer "still for
          war" and Patrick Henry, but for
          peace and Horace Greeley. Now, the
          natural result of all this i3 that the
          public have come at last to think
          that this man has no life but public
          life, no nature but a public nature,
          no habits but public habits. This is
          all wrong. Mr. Greeley has a pri
          vate life. Mr. Greeley has private
          habits.
          Mr. Greeley gets up at three
          o'clock in the morning; for it is one
          of his favorite maxims that only ear
          ly rising can keep the health unim
          paired and the brain vigorous. He
          then wakes up all the household and
          assembles them in the library by
          candle light; and, after quoting the
          beautiful lines;
          Early to bed and early to rise.
          Makes a man healthy, wealthy, and wise,
          he appoints each individual's task for
          the day, sets him at it with encour
          aging words, and goes back to bed
          again.
          At half-past eleven o'clock Mr.
          Greeley rises again. He shaves
          himself. He considers that there is
          great virtue and economy in shaving
          himself. He does it with a dull ra
          zor, sometimes humming part of a
          tune (ne Knows partxif a tuna, and
          takes an innocent delight in regard
          ing it as the first half of Old Hun
          dred, but parties familiar with that
          hymn have felt obliged to confess
          that they could not recognize it, and,
          therefore, the noise he makes is
          doubtless an unconscious original
          composition of Mr. Greeley's), and
          sometimes, when the razor is espec
          pecially dull, he accompanies him
          self with a formula like this u
          the razor, and the outcast
          who made it" H. G.
          He then goes out into his model
          garden, and applies his vast store of
          agricultural knowledge to the amek
          ioration of his cabbages; after which
          he writes an able agricultural article
          for the instruction of American
          farmers, his soul cheered the while
          with the reflection that if cabbages
          were worth $11 apiece, his model
          farm would pay.
          He next goes to breakfast, which
          is a frugal, abstemious meal with
          him, and consists of nothing but
          such things as the mirket affords,
          nothing more. He drinks nothing
          but water nothing whatever but
          water and coffee and tea and Scotch
          ale and lager beer and lemonade with
          a fly in it sometimes a hou3e fly and
          sometimes a horse fly, according to
          the amount of inspiration required
          to warm him up to his daily duties.
          During breakfast he reads the Trib
          une ail through, and enjoys the sat
          isfaction of knowing that all the bril
          liant things in it written by Young
          and Cooke and Hazard and myself,
          are attributed to him by a confiding
          and ignorant public
          After breakfast he writes a short
          editorial, and puts a large da3h at
          the beginning of it, thin
          which is the same as if he put H. G.
          after it, and takes a savage pleasure
          in reflecting that none of us under
          strappers can use the dash, except
          in profane conversation when chaf
          ing over the outrage. He write3 this
          editorial in hia own handwriting.
          He does it because he is so vain of
          his penmanship. He always did
          take an inordinate pride in penman
          ship. He hired out once in his
          young days, as a writing master, but
          the enterprise failed. The pupils
          could not translate hi marks with
          any certainty. His first copy was
          "Virtue is its own reward and they
          got it "Washing with soap is low
          and absurd," and so the trustees dis
          charged him for attempting to con
          vey bad morals through the medium
          of worse penmanship. But, as I
          was saying, he writes his morning
          editorial. Then he tries to read it
          over, and can't do it, and so sends i t
          to the printers, and they try to read
          it and can t do it; and so they set it
          up at random, as you may say, put
          ting in what words they can make
          and when they get aground on a
          long word they put it "protection"
          or "universal suffrage," and spar oft
          and paddle ahead, and next morn-
          ing, if the degraded public can tell
          what it is all about they say H, G.
          wrote it, and if they can't they say
          it i3 one of those imbecile under
          strappers, and that is the end of it
          On Sundays Mr. Greeley sits in a
          prominent pew in Mr. Chapin'a
          church and lets on that he is asleep,
          and the congregation regard it is an
          eccentricity of genius.
          When be is going to appear in
          public, Mr. Greeley spends two
          hours on his toilet He is the most
          painstaking and elaborate man about
          getting up his dress that lives in
          America. This is his chiefest and
          his pleasantest foible. He puts on
          his old white overcoat and turns np
          the collar. He puts on a soiled
          shirt, saved from the wash, and
          leaves one end of the collar unbut
          toned. He puts on his most dilapi
          dated hat, turns its wrong side be
          fore, cants it onto the back of his
          head, and jams an extra dent in the
          side of it He puts on his most at
          rocious boots, and spends tea min
          utes tucking the left leg of his pants
          into his boot-top in what shall seem
          the most careless and unstained way.
          But his cravat it is into the ar
          rangement of his cravat that he
          throws all his soul, all the powers
          of his great mind. After fixing at
          it for forty minutes before the glass
          it is perfect it is askew in every
          way it overflows his coat collar on
          one side and sinks into oblivion on
          the other it climbs and it delves
          around about his neck the knot ia
          conspicuously displayed under his
          left ear, and it stretches one of its
          long emls straight out horizontally,
          and the other goes after his eye, in
          the good of Toodleg fashion and
          then, completely and marvellously
          apparelled, Mr. Greeley strides forth,
          rolling like a sailor, a miracle of as
          tounding costumery, the awe and
          wonder of the nations!
          But I haven't time to tell the rest
          of his' private habits. Safaceisthat
          he is an upright and an honest man
          a practical, great grained man a
          useful man to his nation and his gen
          eration a famous man who has
          justly earned, his celebrity rand
          withal the worst dressed man in thu
          or any other country, even though
          he does take so much pains and trafc
          on so many frilla about It</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85025759/1880-05-18/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Arcttiug- Witb a. Utvtu,
          Mark Twain's "A Tramp Abroad."
          One day in a dreamy mood Mark
          Twain wandered among the woods on
          the hills above the Neckar. This new
          melancholy Jacques did not find a sub
          ject for reflection in "poor bankrupt
          deer," but, with his own peculiar vein of
          fancy, he discovered something to moral
          ize about in the croakinsr of ravens over
          head. As au instance of Mark Twain's
          powers of imaginative perception, the
          passage about the conduct of the ravens
          is worth quoting:
          "The world waw bright with sunshine
          outside, but a deep and mellow twilight
          reigned in there, and also a silence so
          profound that I seemed to hear my own
          breathings. When I stood ten minutes,
          thinking and imagining, and getting my
          spirit "in tune with the place,
          and in the right mood to enjoy
          the supernatural, a raven sud
          denly uttered a hoarse croak over my
          head. Jt made me start; and then I was
          angry because I started. I looked up,
          and the creature was sitting on a limb
          right over me, looking down at me. I
          felt something of the same sense of
          humiliation and injury which one feels
          when be finds that a human stranger has
          been clandestinely inspecting him in his
          privacy, and meutally commenting upon
          him. I eyed the raven, and the raven
          eyed mo. Nothing was said during some
          seconds. Then the bird stepped a little
          way along his limb to get a better point
          of observation, lifted his wings, stuck his
          head far down below his shoulders toward
          me, and croaked again a croak with a
          distinctly insulting expression about it.
          If he had spoken iu English he could not
          have said any more plainly than he did
          say in raven, 'Well, what do you want
          here?' I felt as foolish as if I had been
          caught in some mean act by a responsi
          ble being, and reproved for it. However,
          I made no reply; I would not bandy
          words with a raven. The adversary
          waited a while, with his shoulders still
          lifted, his head thrust down between
          thein, and his keen bright eye fixed on
          me; then he threw out two or three
          more insults, which I could not under-:
          stand, further than that I knew a por
          tion of them consisted of language not
          used in church.
          "I still made no reply. Now the ad
          versary raised his head and called. There
          was an answering croak from a little dis
          tance in the wood, evidently a croak of
          inquiry. The adversary explained with
          enthusiasm, and tho other raven dropped
          everything and came. The two sat side
          by side on the limb and discussed me as
          freely and offensively as two great nat
          uralists might discuss a new kind of bug.
          The thing became more and more em
          barrassing. They called in another
          friend. This was too much. I saw that
          they had the advantage of me, and so 1
          concluded to get out of the scrape by
          walking out of it. They enjoyed my de
          feat as much as any low white people
          could have done. They craned their
          necks and laughed at me (for a raven
          can laugh just like a man) they squalled
          insulting remarks after me as long as
          they could see me. They were nothing
          but ravens I knew that -what they
          thought about me could be a matter of
          no consequence and yet when even a
          raven shouts after you, 'What a hall'
          '0 pull down vout vest!' and that sort of
          thing, it hurts you and humiliates you,
          and there is no getting around it with
          fine reasoning and petty arguments."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87052128/1875-05-28/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MARK TWAIN ON SPELLING.
          The Beauty of Unfettered Origin
          altty In Orthography.
          There was a spelling match at the Asy
          lum Hill Congregational Church. Hart
          ford, Conn., on Wednesday evening, and
          Mr. Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain) being
          called on for a tew prclimary remarks
          spoke as follows:
          Ladles and gentlemen; I hare been
          honored with the office of Producing these
          approaching orthographical solemnities
          with a few remarks The temperance cru
          sade swept the land some time ago, that
          is, that vast portion of the land where it
          was needed, but it skipped Hartford.
          Now cornea this new spelling epidemic,
          and this time we are stricken. So, I snp
          pose we needed the affliction. I dont say
          we needed it, for I don't see any use in
          spelling a word right, and never did. 1
          mean I don't see any use in having a uni
          form and arbitrary wny of spelling words.
          We might as well make all clothes alike
          and cook all dishes alike. Sameness is
          tiresome variety is pleasing. I have a
          correspondent whose letters are always a
          relieshmenl to me, there is sncb a breesy
          unlettered originality about his orthog
          raphy. He always spells Kow with a
          large K. Now that is just as good as to
          spell it with a small One. It
          is better. It gives the imagination a
          broader field, a wide scope. It suggests
          to the mind a grand, vague, impressive
          kind ot a eow. Superb efforts can be
          produced by variegated spelling. Now
          there is Blind Tom, the musical prodigy.
          He always spells a word according to the
          sound that is carried to his ear.
          And he is nn entliusinst in
          orthography. When you give him
          a word, he shouts it out puts his soul
          into it. I once heard him called upon to
          spell orang-outang before an audience,
          lie said, "O, r-a-n-g, orang, ger, ger,
          oranger, t-a-n-g, tang, orangger tang
          Now, a body can respect a orang-outang
          that spelts bis name in a vigorous way.
          But that dictionary makes a mere kitten
          ot him. In the old times people spelled
          just as they pleased. That was the right
          idea. You had two chances at a stranger
          then. You knew a strong man from a
          weak one by his iron-clad spelling and
          his hand-writing helped you to verily your
          verdict. Some people have an idea that
          correct spelling cau be taught and
          taught to anybody. This is a mistake
          The spelling faculty is born in a man, like
          poetry, music and art. It is a gilt; it is a
          talent. People who have this gilt in a
          high degree only need a word once in
          print, and its Is forever photographed
          upon their memory. Thcv can not forget
          it. People who haven't it must be con
          tent to spell more or less like thunder
          and expect to splinter the dictionary
          wherever their orthographical lightning
          happens to strike, fhere are 114,000
          words in the unabridged dictiotary. I
          know a lady who can spell only 180 of
          them right. She steers clear ol all the
          t est. She can't learn any more. So her
          letters always consist of those constantly
          recurring 180 words. Now and then,
          when she finds herslf obliged to write
          upon a subfect which necessitates the use
          of some other words, she well, she don't
          write on that subject. I have a relative
          in New York who is almost sublimely
          gifted. She can't spell anv word right.
          There is a game called Verbarium. A
          dozen people are each provided with a
          sheet ot paper across the top of which is
          written a long word like kaleidoscopical,
          or something like that, and the game is
          to see who can make up the most words
          out of that In three minutes, always be
          ginning with the initial letter of that
          word. Upon one occasion the word chos
          en was cofferdam. When time was call
          ed, everybody had built from five to twen
          ty words, except this young lady. Sho
          only bad one calf. We all studied a mo
          ment, and then said, "Why, there is no 1
          in cofferdam." Then we examined her
          paper. To the eternal honor of that un
          inspired, unconscious, sublimely-independent
          soul be it said, she had spelt that
          word "caff!" If anybody here can spell
          calf any more sonsibly than that, let him
          step to the front aad take his milk. The
          insurrection will now begin.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1891-11-29/ed-1/?sp=14&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MEXTA L TELEGRAI'll Y.
          A STORY TOLD _Y MAR.K TWAIN.
          From Harpcr's Mngazlne.
          Now I come to the oddest thlng that evcr h.-tp
          penod to me. Two or three years ago I was lying
          ln bed. iillv muslng one iiiorning?it wa.s tho -&lt;1
          of March?whaa a___ae__ red bot new i.ica eama
          wMstling down luio inv cainp. BBd cxplodcd wlth
          _teh oomprehenalva effwtiveaeea as t?. aweea IM
          vlrlnily rlean of rubhlsby reflecUona, aud till the air
          with thelr dnst und tlylng firagmaata. Thia Btea,
          statcd In simplc pl.ruse, was that thc tlmc was ripe
          umi thc inark.-t ready for a ccrtaln book; a book wnuii
          o.ight to bo wrltten nt once; a book wld.-li must com
          ni,niil attention and be oi pe.-ullnr iBtefBS- ibook about BM Nevada sllver nilncs. The ??(.rea-t
          l;.ui/.a" was a new w.mder th-n, nnd everybody
          was talklng about lt. lt seemed to me that UM
          paraoo i*-st ..uuiitied to witM thia book was Mr.
          William 11. Wright, a Joun.alist of Vir. Inlii, Nevada,
          l,v WB0B8 BBta I had acHbhlad many months when 1
          was a rcpoiter tlicre ten or twclvo years before. Ho
          mlght bo alive still; be mlght l.e tell: bat 1 would wrlte hlm anyway. I began by
          merely and B_a_B__ BBggl-.ing that hc make such
          b,?.k;' but my interest grew as I went tn, nnd I
          veiitui .d to BBBB out wliat I Uiought ouglit
          |0 be thc plan of tho work, Tfc being an
          old frlcnd. and not given to taklng good Intcntlons for
          ill. I even d.-alt with dctalls. and suggcsti-d tho
          order aod seqaeooa arhlel they should follow. I was
          about l&lt;> put thc BB-B-SCriBt ln an eevetoPB, when tho
          UlOlight if'-tirred to BM that If his book should bo
          wrltten at my su.-stlon, and than no pnbllsher
          happen _? wuiit it. I should feel uiiintii liMl.it to K.-.-p my letter ba. k until I sl.o.d.l have
          _ i-nvd B publlalier. I plgeon-holed n\v docnm.'iit,
          and dropped a note t.? n.v own publish..i-, asklng hlir
          to aaaaa a da. for b bualneaa eonanltatton. Ha araa
          ...it of town oa a Bar lourne.. Mv note remalned un
          answered, aad al ihe cnWhole matter In.d passixl out of my mlnd. Of tho
          otli of Manli Ihe postiuan brouglit threo or four
          ttei- and amoii. them B thlck one whose B-Pe.
          rlptl ii waa bl a haad whleh aeemed dimly ramllfar
          t,> nie I could not pln.c" It at tirst. but prosenfly
          I .iin-eili-d. i li'-u I -sai.l to a __t_ag r.-lallvo who
          n;is iir'-si-nt
          ?N,.w I wlll do a mlrnelc. I wlll tell you every
          Ihlng thls kdter cntaius-dale, slgnature and all?
          wlUioul breaUng IBe *e_L It is fr.m a Mr.
          Wright. of Ylrglnla. BB**., and is dated thc _1
          of Mareh?aaVBB days aeo. Mr. Wright BtOBOael
          M make a bo..k about the sllver mities aud thc.
          Great Bonanaa, and a&lt;_s what I, as n frlcnd. think of
          the Idea. Ile says hls siib.eits nre to be so and so.
          thelr order and BeBjaaaee so and so, and he wlll clise
          wlth a history of thc chief feature of tho book, the
          &lt;,.-it Bonanaa." _
          I opencd thc Ielter, and showed that I had statcd thc
          dale and thc eontents correctly. Mr. Wriglrt's Icttci
          s.iuply (ontaiiicd what iny own letter, wrltten on tho
          same'datc, contalncd. and mlne s!lll lay tn Its plgeon
          hota, where lt has h .m lying during the seven
          days altice It was "wrltten.
          There was no clalrvoyance alKiut tnls. If I rlghtly
          i-omprehcnd what cinlrvovance ls. I Uilnk the elair
          Oovant pr_fe_Ra actuallv to -ee eon?M_ed wrlllng. and
          read It ofT wot-d for WO &lt;1. This was not mv cBBB. I onlv
          ?earned to know. ar,of the letter ill detall and due order, but I had to WOTd
          them nT>--lf. I lii.nslatetl tli.-rn. 10 to spcak, out of
          Wright'? langiiag- Into tnv own.
          Wrl.ht's letler nnd th" one whlth I had wrltten to
          him but never sent. were in _____nca thc nune.
          Bereaaarll. this c.ui.i not eooae by aeddent; surti
          ela'.omte atrld?iits eaonot happen. -banee mlgin
          bara dapUeated one or two of the dcUiiis. but sho
          w.iild have _____ down on the rest.. I could not
          doubt?there was no tenal.lc reason for doubtlng?
          that Mr. Wrlirht's mlnd and nilnc had been in c'nso
          nnd rrv-tal lear rninuiiinl. i.llon Wlth ench other
          hon thc BKM_lBg of ti.e -Jd of Man li. I did not .-on
          sldcr tbat both mlnds orlglnated thnt 8Bre____ of
          itakBrapbed Ihem to the oth>r. l was eorhwa to
          know wiii.ii braln was th. teJagraphar and whleh
          the receivcr. so i wiota aa! an.l aaked for parttealarB.
          Mr. Wi-ictif's replv BhnWBd that hls mlnd had douc
          the orlglnaUng nnd tcletrrnplilne nnd mlne the re
          eetvlng. Mark that aignUkmnl thlng, now: eonaldev
          for n moment how many a splcndld -orlglnaP t-lea
          has been uiieonse|onsly iioleil from n mnn throc
          thouaand miles awav! If one should qiieatlOB that
          thls ls o. lef him look Into thc cyclopaedla and con
          unie iiiurv ilnt eaHona UllllL' ln the hl-t ,rv of 1u
          vnntlons whleh has- MBSled everv one |s. the fianaenfj wlth whleh tbe .tn> marhlne or
          other rontrlvanre hns biv-n Invented at the snme (ime
          by scvcral pcr.-ons in (.fTcreiit, qaa__BB of tlio giobe.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1881-11-05/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens&amp;r=0.492,0.689,0.474,0.254,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>"Mark TwainV' New Hotel.
          The following "items" in relation to Mr. Twain's
          new investment are published:
          ki ij5s and regulation's of ift "ha&lt;5h*ry."
          1. This house will be strictly Intemperate, and
          no questions asked.
          2. None but the brave deserve a bill of fare.
          3. Persons owing bills for board will be bored
          for bills.
          4. Boarders who do not wish to pay in advance
          are requested to advance and pay.
          5. Boarders are respectfully requested to wait
          until the cook cooks the meals.
          6. Sheets will be nightly changed on e In every
          six months, or more if unnecessary.
          7. All regular boarders are earnest ly requested
          to pull off all their boots regularly, if they can
          conveniently do so, before retiring for the
          night.
          8. Beds, with or without bugs or fleas, If preferred.
          9. All moneys or other valuables are to be left in
          charge of the proprietor, without cost. This
          he Insists upon, as he will be held responsible
          for no losses on any account.
          10i Inside and outside matter will never be furnished
          newspaper men, under any consideration?excepting
          reporters?who will be always
          kept out.
          11. Single men, with their families, will never be
          "taken in."
          12. Night-Mares?Single fare, $1 an hour.
          13. Stone vaults for snoring boarders.
          14. Children without families preferred.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1907-10-27/ed-1/?sp=27&amp;q=Mark+Twain+Samuel+Clemens</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF
          MARK TWAIN
          Introduction
          T i
          a i 11 ful rap!
          i ntenrl thai
          I and a di I mai
          I i 1
          method
          Etanti

          t act of flint wi 1
          I
          t



          I
          _
          rticularly hum
          reei n 1 i

          "t nd rou


          I

          i t f«>r i




          nd can i
          ilk to

          1 iwn a
          ted j
          Drjwinn by P. Lvii Mon
          in mj How-ells that thus auto-
          I live a o >uple i>f I h&lt; m ;and
          it effort, and w&lt; >uld th(
          I art and live ihe re oi thi time
          He ;ai 1 he believed it would, and Ime if 1
          meant to make
          said t my design but t hat if 1
          should live long enough, the set of volumes could
          not be contained merely in a city, it would require
          .i St. tii-, and that thei ild not be any multi
          n r.iv alive ps. ai any t ime dvi i
          ible to buy full et, ex
          cept oi an
          Howells applauded, and was full
          indorsement, wi him, and judicii >v
          [f he had manife ted a different spirit, I would have
          thrown him oui the window I like xitii im; but
          t must
          CHAPTER I.
          B.\i X of the Vii [in i
          to Noah'
          i
          Bui
          I his is no discredit to thei
          I trade
          In my time
          r'oa lei



          i




          I ha
          flf. pai I
          I.

          I
          I
          I
          me tin .'I



          i t I am i 1"
          II. *S 1
          him,— l do not ki
          I icat es Ai i
          n. Of
          A Question of Ancestry
          A CASK of the kind hapjvned in 8.-r'in several
          rV years ag... William Walter Phelps was our
          minister at the limperor's court then, and one even
          ing hi* had me to dinner to meet Count S a Cabinet
          minister. This nobleman was 'if long ami illustrious
          descent. &lt;>f course I wanted to let out the fact
          that I had some ancestors iw; bu: 1 did not wan:
          to j»u" them out of their graves by the ears. ti t i 1
          never could seem to gel the chance to work tin 1
          in in a wav*hat would >uth"eiently casual. I
          suppose I'hi-lTi- 'a;i. ::i the same difficulty. In fact,
          he l>"ki'il distraught, now and then: just :t> a |>er
          son looks who wants to uncover an ancestor purely
          by accident, and cannot think &lt;>i a way that will
          seem accidental enough. But at last, after dinner,
          he iv. n .1 Try. He took us about his drawing room,
          showing us the pictures, ;tr.a rude and ancient engraving. It was .t picture of
          the emir', that tried Charles I. There '.v.is a pyrami i
          i >f jr.'luo in Puritan slouch hats, and below them
          three ban- headed secretaries seated at a table.
          Mr. I'helps put his finger 'ti*'!'. "th' of the three,
          and said with exulting indi'Terence, "An aneest t
          of mine
          I</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045217/1921-11-27/ed-1/?sp=21&amp;q=mark+twain</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1935-02-03/ed-1/?sp=31&amp;q=mark+twain&amp;r=0.478,0.017,0.615,0.329,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1910-04-22/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=mark+twain&amp;r=0.251,0.199,0.825,0.442,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84036012/1898-10-23/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;q=mark+twain&amp;r=0.126,0.227,0.655,0.35,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86074053/1910-05-12/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=mark+twain&amp;r=0.253,0.547,0.526,0.281,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
